<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Bong Eats | Bengali Recipe Videos</title>
  <subtitle>Bong Eats is about food from Bengal. And that&#39;s not just Bengali food.</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://bongeats.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-02T08:45:43.979Z</updated>
  <id>https://bongeats.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Bong Eats</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pabda Machh&#39;er Tel Jhol</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/pabda-machher-tel-jhol/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/pabda-machher-tel-jhol/</id>
    <published>2017-02-23T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:45:43.979Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A flavourful, light curry with <em>pabda</em> fish</p>

<p class="post-intro">It is unbelievable that something with a handful of ingredients can taste so divine.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he <em>pabda machh</em> is one of the most beloved of Bengal’s fishes. It is sweet to the taste, flaky, and delicately flavoured. To top it all off, it is also extremely easy to eat, as it contains no bones besides the central skeleton. This recipe, <em>pabda machh’er tel jhol</em>, is a delicacy in Bengali cooking. ‘<em>Tel jhol</em>’ is the name given to a light curry, which is infused with <em>kaalo jeere</em>, green chillies, and mustard oil. Because it is sparsely spiced, this style of curry doesn’t overpower the star ingredient—the fish—but lets it shine on its own. If you have managed to procure a batch of fresh <em>pabda</em>, this should be your go-to <em>jhol</em>.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">450 g</td>
<td>Pabda machh (cut and cleaned)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">35 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">7 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">7 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for garnish)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Tomato (roughly chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 pieces</td>
<td>Dal’er bori</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Brinjal (5-cm segments)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g (plus ¾ tsp extra for marinating)</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">6 g (plus ¾ tsp extra for marinating)</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">½ tsp</td>
<td>Atta (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">8 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">400 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPPING THE INGREDIENTS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Smear the cut and cleaned <em>padba machh</em> with ¾ tsp turmeric powder, ¾ tsp salt, and 1 tsp mustard oil. Mix till the fish are well coated, and set aside.</li>
<li>Cut the brinjal into 5-cm segments. We need as many pieces of brinjal as there are fish—in this case, five.</li>
<li>Roughly chop the tomatoes.</li>
<li>Slit the green chillies.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—FRYING THE <em>BORI</em>, BRINJAL, AND FISH</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Heat your <em>kadai</em> well and add 35 g mustard oil to the pan.</li>
<li>Once the oil is completely hot (that is, once it has begun to smoke lightly and changed colour to a pale yellow), add the <em>dal’er bori</em>.</li>
<li>Fry the <em>boris</em> for about 20 seconds till they are golden brown. They colour very quickly, so be alert while frying them.</li>
<li>Remove the <em>boris</em> from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Next, add the brinjal pieces to the oil.</li>
<li>Stir-fry for about 4 minutes till they are golden. Remove them from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Now, in batches, fry the marinated fish. Fresh, sweetwater fish such as the <em>pabda</em> do not need heavy searing. Fry them lightly to preserve their delicate flavour. A minute on each side should do the job.</li>
<li>Remove the fried fish on a plate and reserve for later use.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—MAKING THE <em>JHOL</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Before we start, make a paste with 15 g salt, 6 g turmeric powder, and 50 g water. Mix and keep ready.</li>
<li>Heat 7 g mustard oil in the <em>kadai</em>. (If the oil that you fried the fish in is not burnt, you may use the same oil to prepare the <em>jhol</em>.)</li>
<li>Add the <em>kaalo jeere</em>, tomatoes, and 3 green chillies to the oil.</li>
<li>Fry them for a minute on medium heat.</li>
<li>Add the turmeric and salt mixture to the pan, and fry till the water in the spice mix dries up.</li>
<li>Now, pour 400 g of hot water (either heated in an electric kettle or on the stove) into the pan. This will form the curry.</li>
<li>Once the curry starts to simmer, add in the fried <em>boris</em>.</li>
<li>Simmer for another 2 minutes before lowering in the <em>pabda machh</em>, one by one. Also add the fish drippings that might have collected on the plate that held the fried fish; they are delicious.</li>
<li>Add the fried brinjal to the curry.</li>
<li>Let everything bubble for about 5 minutes. As the curry boils, you will notice that the colour of the <em>jhol</em> has changed from deep yellow to bright yellow. That’s when you know that the turmeric is cooked, and that the curry won’t taste of the raw spice.</li>
<li>Now, pick one of the softened green chillies from the curry onto a small bowl. Add ½ tsp <em>atta</em> to it, along with 1 tbsp of water. Mash the three together, until paste-like.</li>
<li>Add this mixture to the <em>jhol</em>. The mashed green chilli will release the heat, while the flour will help the curry thicken and develop body.</li>
<li>Garnish with 2 more slit green chillies, a drizzle of mustard oil (about 7 g), and chopped coriander.</li>
<li>Allow everything to bubble for a couple of more minutes, before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A light, hearty, delicious delicacy, the padba macher tel jhol is packed with the flavours of Bengal’s prized sweetwater pabda fish.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="pabda machh" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pabda-machh/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Panch Phoron</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/panch-phoron/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/panch-phoron/</id>
    <published>2017-02-16T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:46:05.282Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Bengali five-spice mix for tempering oil</p>

<p class="post-intro"><em>Panch phoron</em> is popularly used to temper dals, vegetables (such as <a href="/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/"><em>panchmishali torkari</em></a> or <em>shada alu’r torkari</em>), <em>chutneys</em> (those with tomatoes or raw mangoes), or <em>achaars</em> (such as raw-mango pickles).</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he cooking of most Bengali dishes starts with the <em>phoron</em>. What this typically involves is heating up the oil (usually mustard oil), and once hot, adding a selection of whole spices to it. This ‘tempers’ the oil, transferring the flavours of the spices to it. This might seem like a tiny, inconsequential step (the process of tempering doesn’t take more than a few seconds), but no Bengali cook has ever skipped it. Is is what prepares the oil for cooking. In many cases, the choice of <em>phoron</em> defines the flavour profile of the recipe (think of a dish like <a href="/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/"><em>panchmishali torkari</em></a>, or a fish curry like <em>tel jhol</em>). There are myriad combinations of spices used for <em>phoron</em> in Bengali cooking, and while that is subject for another post, here we look at the most definitive of Bengali tempering spices—the <em>panch phoron</em>.</p>
<p><em>Panch phoron</em> literally means five spices used for tempering. Apart from the Bengali cuisine, variations of this spice mix are used in Assamese, Oriya, and Nepali cooking as well. The Bengali version comprises <em>mouri</em> (fennel seeds), <em>methi</em> (fenugreek seeds), <em>kaalo jeere</em> (nigella seeds), <em>shorshe</em> (mustard seeds), and a typically Bengali spice, called <em>radhuni</em>. If you can’t find <em>radhuni</em> where you live, cumin seeds make an acceptable substitute.</p>
<p>The <em>panch phoron</em> is used like any other <em>phoron</em>. You heat up the mustard oil thoroughly, till it starts to smoke lightly and turns pale yellow in colour. You then add as much <em>panch phoron</em> as the recipe calls for to the oil. The spices will start cracking immediately (mostly because of the mustard seeds in the mix) and give out a distinctive, bitter-sweet-anisey aroma. However, watch the <em>methi</em> in the mix carefully; it tends to redden, burn quite easily, and turn bitter. So, always have the next ingredient in line prepped and ready, to add to the pan, and bring down the temperature of the oil.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 5 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 50 g of <em>panch phoron</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tbsp</td>
<td>mouri (fennel seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tbsp</td>
<td>methi (fenugreek seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tbsp</td>
<td>kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tbsp</td>
<td>shorshe (mustard seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tbsp</td>
<td>radhuni</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>A small storage container</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p>Mix all the whole spices together in equal proportions and store in an airtight container.</p>
<h2 id="Used-to"><a href="#Used-to" class="headerlink" title="Used to"></a>Used to</h2><ul>
<li>Temper <a href="/tags/dal/">dals</a></li>
<li>Temper vegetarian dishes such as the delicious <a href="/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/">panchmishali torkari</a></li>
<li>Temper chutneys</li>
<li>Flavour pickles</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Easy-to-make, authentic, Bengali five-spice tempering mix, using fennel seeds, fenugreek seeds, mustard seeds, nigella seeds, and radhuni.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
      <category term="masala" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/masala/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Phulkopi&#39;r Bora | Cauliflower fritters</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/phulkopir-bora/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/phulkopir-bora/</id>
    <published>2017-02-09T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:47:07.658Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Crispy, golden cauliflower fritters</p>

<p class="post-intro">In all their batter-fried goodness, these humble fritters are sure to brighten up your meal.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">P</span><em>hulkopi’r bora</em> are ideal to make in the gorgeous winter months, when the cauliflower is in season. They are so easy to prepare that they make for excellent last-minute addition to the day’s menu. The batter is simple. It is flour and water, mildly seasoned with some salt, sugar, and green chillies. <em>Kaalo jeere</em> provides a subtle fragrance, while <em>posto</em> adds crunch. We top batter off with a bit of raw, pungent mustard oil for crispiness. Golden-brown and crisp from the outside, and soft inside, these fried <em>phulkopi’r bora</em> are best had with some <a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">hot rice</a> and <a href="/tags/dal/">dal</a>, although they make a pretty good afternoon snack too.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">150 g</td>
<td>Cauliflower (3-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">50 g</td>
<td>Maida (all-purpose flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 pinch</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 pinch</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Posto (poppy seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>green chilli (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">75 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">~ 250 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for deep-frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Sauce pan | boiling pot (with lid)</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Forks</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Divide the cauliflower into florets, 3 cm large, and transfer them to a saucepan.</li>
<li>Add hot water to the pan and steam the florets, with the lid on, for 3 minutes. Remember, we don’t want to cook the cauliflower completely at this stage. The florets will be deep-fried later; we just want to give them a head-start. Three minutes of steaming should do the trick.</li>
<li>Drain the florets immediately and set aside to cool.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, prepare a batter by mixing flour, salt, sugar, turmeric, <em>kaalo jeere</em>, <em>posto</em>, green chilli, mustard oil, and water in the given proportions.</li>
<li>Mix the batter till well combined.</li>
<li>Set a <em>kadai</em> on the stove and heat it up. Add vegetable oil to the pan, at least 4 cm deep.</li>
<li>On medium flame, allow the oil to heat up completely (200 degree C). You can check by dropping some batter into the oil, and if it floats to the top immediately, with bubbles all around it, the oil is good to go.</li>
<li>Dunk the steamed cauliflower florets into the batter one at a time and coat them well.</li>
<li>Gently drop them into the oil. You can fry about 4 to 8 florets at a time, depending on the size of your pan. But be sure not to overcrowd the pan, or the florets won’t fry evenly from all sides.</li>
<li>Turning them over occasionally, fry the fritters till they are golden-brown.</li>
<li>Once done, remove them from the oil with the help of a perforated spoon. The best way to drain oil is by holding the <em>boras</em> against the side of the hot pan for about 20 seconds.</li>
<li>Sprinkle with some rock salt (<em>beet noon</em>) and serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Cauliflower fritters, coated with a simple flour batter and traditional Bengali spices, and deep-fried till golden-brown and delicious.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
      <category term="cauliflower" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/cauliflower/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bhaja Moong Dal Shobji diye</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/bhaja-moong-dal-shobji-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/bhaja-moong-dal-shobji-diye/</id>
    <published>2017-02-02T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:38:18.587Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Roasted dehulled moong dal with fresh, winter veggies</p>

<p class="post-intro">Bright and colourful, the <em>shobji diye bhaja moong’er dal</em> is bound to floor you with its heady, nutty aroma.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">W</span>hat makes <em>bhaja moong’er dal</em> the most beloved of all <a href="/tags/dal/"><em>dals</em></a> is the fact that it is rich and comforting, without being entirely over-the-top. With this <em>dal</em>, you can get away with serving the simplest of <a href="/tags/torkari/"><em>torkari</em></a> or <a href="/tags/bhaja/"><em>bhaja</em></a> as it elevates any meal that it is part of. This version of the <em>bhaja moong’er dal</em>—one with cauliflower, carrots, and peas—is best enjoyed in the winter months, when these vegetables are fresh and in season. Even though this <em>dal</em> is reserved for special occasions, it is so incredibly simple to make that there is no reason it cannot become part of your regular winter fare.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Moong dal (split gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">550 g</td>
<td>Water (for boiling dal)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Dried red chilli (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaf (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Clove (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Carrots (1-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Cauliflower (2-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes (roughly chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Peas (shelled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">7 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Boiling pot | saucepan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Weigh out the <em>dal</em> and add it to a dry pot (preferably a <em>kadai</em> or wok), set on medium heat.</li>
<li>Dry-roast the <em>dal</em>, stirring continuously, till it changes colour from yellow to a pinkish brown. Here, it is important to keep the <em>dal</em> moving while it is in the pan to ensure that all surfaces of the grains roast evenly. Be particularly alert once the <em>dal</em> has taken on a light, brown colour, as it is during this stage that the <em>dal</em> has the tendency to burn easily.</li>
<li>Transfer the roasted <em>dal</em> into a boiling pot immediately (do not hold it in the hot pan, as it will continue to brown when kept in contact with heat).</li>
<li>Wash and rinse the <em>dal</em> thoroughly.</li>
<li>Add 550 g water to the washed <em>dal</em>.</li>
<li>Boil it on medium heat for about 20 minutes. While we want the <em>dal</em> to be completely cooked, we still want the individual grains to remain unbroken. So, check frequently to ensure that the dal doesn’t turn into mush and lose its texture.</li>
<li>Chop the cauliflower into 2-cm florets, the carrot into 1-cm cubes, and the tomatoes roughly. Shell the peas and slit the green chillies.</li>
<li>Heat up the <em>kadai</em> once more and add 10 g mustard oil.</li>
<li>Once the oil has smoked lightly and lost its pungent smell, temper it with the dried red chilli, bay leaf, cardamom, cinnamon, clove, cumin seeds, and 1 green chilli.</li>
<li>Add the carrots and stir-fry them for 1 minute.</li>
<li>Next, add the cauliflower florets and fry them for another minute.</li>
<li>Add the tomatoes and peas, one at a time, and fry them for a minute after each addition.</li>
<li>Pour in the roasted, boiled <em>dal</em> with its water.</li>
<li>Add the salt, sugar and turmeric, and stir them in.</li>
<li>Allow the <em>dal</em> to bubble for about 6 minutes on low heat. Don’t increase the heat level or the liquid in the <em>dal</em> may dry up.</li>
<li>Garnish with chopped coriander leaves, a slit green chilli, <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/"><em>garam masala</em> powder</a>, and <em>ghee</em>.</li>
<li>Cover the pan with a lid and allow the <em>dal</em> to soak up the flavours from the garnish before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/torkari/">Torkari</a> | <a href="/tags/bhaja/">bhaja</a> | <a href="/recipe/alu-sheddho/">alu sheddho</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A gorgeous-looking traditional Bengali vegetarian dal with roasted yellow mung beans, simmered with cauliflowers, carrots and peas.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
      <category term="moong dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/moong-dal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Panchmishali Torkari</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/</id>
    <published>2017-01-26T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:46:28.834Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Simple Bengali mixed veggies with <em>panch phoron</em> tempering</p>

<p class="post-intro"><em>Panchmishali torkari</em> is any Bengali mixed-vegetable preparation, in which the vegetables are first stir-fried and then steamed in their own juices till they are tender and well-integrated.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>s you might have guessed, the stars of this dish are the veggies themselves. This is not a preparation in which you spice up things with ginger or cumin powder or red chilli powder. The only spice this recipe calls for is a touch of turmeric. Mostly, it relies on the salt and sugar to help draw out the moisture from the vegetables, and allow their flavours to mingle while cooked together. We don’t add water to form a gravy. Rather we cook this <em>torkari</em> on low heat, with the lid on, for nearly 30 to 40 minutes. At the end of this slow cooking process, it reaches a state where no vegetable stands out, yet each has still held on to its flavours and integrity.</p>
<p>Coming to the selection of the veggies themselves, some type of starchy item such as a potato or sweet potato is used. These, being otherwise neutral in taste, are the perfect receptacle of the juices from the other vegetables. The mushy texture is usually contributed by pumpkin, while radish is used for the more sharper notes. Some kind of beans (such as <em>borboti</em> or <em>sheem</em>) add crunch and colour. In the winter months, cauliflower lends the most sublime flavour to the <em>torkari</em>, in addition to providing texture. Finally, slimier vegetables such as brinjals, or cabbage or leafy greens that are prone to wilting on application of heat and salt, coat the mix with their juices and hold everything together.</p>
<p>There are several versions of <em>panchmishali torkari</em>. The choice of <em>phoron</em> (or tempering) will depend on the vegetables used. In this particular recipe, we are using potatoes, sweet potatoes, pumpkin, cauliflower, <em>borboti</em> (yardlong beans), cabbage, and brinjal, with a tempering of <em>panch phoron</em>.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>OIL</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">40 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>TEMPERING (PHORON)</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Bay leaves (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Dried red chillies (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Green chilli (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tsp</td>
<td>Panch phoron</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>THE VEGETABLES</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Brinjals (5-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">200 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (4-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Sweet potatoes (4-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">200 g</td>
<td>Pumpkin (4-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">200 g</td>
<td>Cauliflower (5-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Borboti or yardlong beans (5-cm segments)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Cabbage (5-cm segments)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>THE SEASONING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">½ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">12 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>THE GARNISH</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">½ tsp</td>
<td>Bhaja masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPPING THE VEGETABLES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Peel and cut the potatoes, sweet potatoes, and pumpkin in 4 cm cubes.</li>
<li>Cut the <em>borboti</em>, brinjal, and cabbage in segments of 5 cm each.</li>
<li>Cut the cauliflower in florets, 5 cm large.</li>
<li>In order to cook <em>panchmishali torkari</em>, the vegetables are stir-fried, and the order in which they are added to the pan depends upon their hardness. So, the potatoes and sweet potatoes, which are the hardest of all the veggies, are the first to enter the pan, followed by pumpkin, cauliflower, <em>borboti</em>, and cabbage. We deal with the brinjals separately, as explained in the next step.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—FRYING THE VEGETABLES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Heat mustard oil in a pan till it starts to smoke lightly and the pungent smell is gone.</li>
<li>Keeping the pan on medium heat, add in the brinjals and fry them for about 3 minutes till they are golden.</li>
<li>Remove them from pan and reserve for later use. Frying the brinjals separately enhances their flavour.</li>
<li>Now, in the same oil, add the tempering of dried red chillies, bay leaves, green chilli, and <em>panch phoron</em>. <em>Panch phoron</em> is a mix of the following whole spices in equal proportion: fenugreek seeds (<em>methi</em>), fennel seeds (<em>mouri</em>), mustard seeds (<em>shorshe</em>), nigella seeds (<em>kaalo jeere</em>), and a typically Bengali spice called <em>radhuni</em>.</li>
<li>Once the spices start to crackle, add in the potatoes and sweet potatoes to the oil.</li>
<li>Fry these for about 3 minutes before introducing the next vegetable, that is, pumpkin.</li>
<li>Fry the pumpkin, sweet potatoes, and potatoes together for another 3 minutes before adding the cauliflower. Basically, at intervals of 3 minutes, we add the next vegetable and stir-fry it together with the veggies already in the pan.</li>
<li>Once the cauliflower is fried, add the <em>borboti</em>, and then, after 3 minutes, the cabbage.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—STEAMING THE VEGETABLES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Once all the veggies have been fried, add in the salt and turmeric, and stir them in.</li>
<li>At this point, lower the heat and cover the pan with a lid. The salt will help release the moisture from the vegetables, and gently steaming them with the lid on will help soften them up.</li>
<li>Cook the vegetables like this for about 15 minutes. Stir occasionally to prevent them from sticking to the bottom of the pan. While doing so, be gentle, as the we don’t want the vegetables to turn into mush. (Always use a folding motion to stir the veggies around.)</li>
<li>After 15 minutes, add the sugar and the fried brinjals, and cover and cook for another 10 minutes or so, stirring occasionally.</li>
<li>You will know that the <em>torkari</em> is done when the vegetables are completely tender and have integrated themselves into the dish, but still have the integrity to not fall apart to the touch.</li>
<li>At this point, garnish with the chopped coriander leaves, green chillies, <em>bhaja masala</em>, and <em>ghee</em>.</li>
<li>Turn off the heat, cover the pan, and allow it to rest for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | Roti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Video recipe of authentic, vegetarian Bengali dish of cauliflower, beans, sweet potatoes, eggplants, cooked with panch phoron tempering.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Koi Machh&#39;er Jhol Phulkopi diye</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/koi-machher-jhol-phulkopi-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/koi-machher-jhol-phulkopi-diye/</id>
    <published>2017-01-19T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:43:41.089Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Everyone’s favourite <em>machh’er jhol</em> for the winter months</p>

<p class="post-intro">This is a light curry of the climbing perch fish (<em>koi machh</em>) and fried cauliflower florets.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span><em>oi machh</em> is a delicacy in Bengali cooking. Also known as the climbing perch fish because of its ability <em>climb</em> out of water and walk on land for short distances, <em>koi machh</em> is <em>always</em> bought live at fish markets. It has an extremely slippery exterior, making the use of ash rather necessary while handling the fish for cleaning. Even if the <em>koi machh</em> is scaled, degilled, and cleaned by your fish-seller, it might still be quite slimy to the touch. At home, you may need to rub the fish against an abrasive surface to get rid of the slipperiness (a perforated, steel colander-plate does this job quite well).</p>
<p>Coming to this recipe, its main ingredients, <em>koi machh</em> and <em>phulkopi</em> (cauliflower), are fried separately to enhance their flavours, and then added to the delicious <em>jhol</em>. The <em>jhol</em> itself is a hot, gingery, <em>garam-masala</em>-infused curry that is mildly sweet, but never too spicy. It uplifts the taste of anything it gets soaked up in—potatoes, cauliflower, <em>bori</em>, or the fish. Eaten with a generous helping of steaming hot rice, this dish, the <em>phulkopi diye koi machh’er jhol</em> is the Bengali’s favourite fish curry for the winter months.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">30 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">350 g (or 5 pieces)</td>
<td>Koi machh (climbing perch fish)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">150 g (or 5 pieces)</td>
<td>Cauliflower (5-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g (or 5 pieces)</td>
<td>Potatoes (cut lengthwise)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 pieces</td>
<td>Dal’er bori</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">20 g</td>
<td>Tomato (3-cm quarters)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">7 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4 g (plus ¾ tsp for marinating)</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 g</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">18 g (plus ¾ tsp for marinating)</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">350 g</td>
<td>Water (hot)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">6 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPPING THE INGREDIENTS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Smear the <em>koi machh</em> with ¾ tsp each of salt and turmeric till they are evenly coated. Set them aside.</li>
<li>Cut a cauliflower into chunky florets, about 5 cm large. Take as many florets as there are pieces of fish (in this case, five).</li>
<li>Peel and cut the potatoes lengthwise. Again, we need as many pieces of potatoes as there are fish.</li>
<li>Chop the tomato into 3-cm quarters.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—FRYING THE <em>BORI</em>, CAULIFLOWER, AND FISH</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Heat a <em>kadai</em> till it is completely hot. Drizzle 30 g mustard oil into the pan till it starts smoking lightly, and changes colour from deep to pale yellow.</li>
<li>Add all the <em>dal’er bori</em> into the oil and fry them till they are golden. This should take about 15–20 seconds. The bori tend to brown quickly, so stay on the watch.</li>
<li>Remove the fried <em>bori</em> from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>Now, add the cauliflower florets, along with ¼ tsp of salt, to the pan and fry them till they develop a light-brown colour. This should take about 4 minutes in all.</li>
<li>Remove the cauliflower from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>Finally, add the marinated <em>koi machh</em> to the same oil, one at a time, and fry them for no longer than a minute on each side. This is a freshwater fish with delicate flavours. So be sure not to sear the fish too long.</li>
<li>Remove the fish from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>You now have fried <em>bori</em>, fried cauliflower, and fried fish ready for use at a later stage, and can now move on to the preparation of the curry.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—MAKING THE <em>JHOL</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>At this point, inspect the oil in your pan. If it looks too burnt, replace it with 10 g of fresh mustard oil. If it is alright, use the same oil to cook the curry in as it contains all the flavour from the fried fish.</li>
<li>Temper the oil, set on medium heat, with the bay leaf, cardamom, cinnamon, cumin seeds, and 2 slit green chillies.</li>
<li>Add the potatoes to the pan and fry them, with the lid on, for 4 minutes.</li>
<li>While the potatoes are frying, make a paste by combining cumin powder, turmeric powder, red chilli powder, salt, sugar, and 50 g water.</li>
<li>Add this mixture into the pan and fry it, with lid on, till the water dries up.</li>
<li>Now, add in the ginger paste and the tomatoes, and incorporate them with the spices. Introduce another 50 g water to the pan and sauté the spices again till the water dries off.</li>
<li>The key here is to cover and cook because, alongside sautéing the spices, we also want to allow time for the potatoes to become tender.</li>
<li>Add in the fried cauliflower florets, fold them into the spices, and cook them for a minute or so.</li>
<li>Now, add 350 g of hot water to the pan. This will form the curry.</li>
<li>Once it comes to a boil, add in the fried <em>bori</em>, fried fish, and two (more) of the slit green chillies.</li>
<li>Using a spoon, gently try and submerge the fish in the curry. Be delicate as the fish is quite fragile at this stage.</li>
<li>Cover the pan and allow the curry to simmer for about 6 minutes.</li>
<li>Chop fresh coriander and add it to the pan. Let it simmer in the curry for another minute before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Video recipe for traditional Bengali fish curry made with koi fish simmered in a light gravy along with cauliflowers, bori and potatoes
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="koi machh" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/koi-machh/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Patishapta (with kheer filling)</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/patishapta-with-kheer-filling/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/patishapta-with-kheer-filling/</id>
    <published>2017-01-12T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:46:48.187Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A thin, delicate crêpe filled with sweetened, reduced milk or <em>kheer</em></p>

<p class="post-intro">Winter is a Bengali’s favourite season. And what would winters in Bengal be without all the sweet <em>pithe</em>?</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he rice-harvest festival in Bengal, <em>poush sankranti</em>, is celebrated by making the most wondrous of sweets—the pithe. This is an umbrella term used to describe a variety of items prepared using rice, date-palm syrup (<em>patali gur</em>, only available in winter), coconut, milk, and flour. <em>Pithe</em> is no single dish, but a category of sweets that are part of the Bengali cooking tradition dedicated exclusively to turning the season’s harvest into delectable foods.</p>
<p><em>Patishapta</em> is a type of <em>pithe</em>. It is a light crêpe filled with either <em>kheer</em> or a coconut-and-<em>gur</em> mixture. In this recipe, we show you how to make the version with <em>kheer</em>.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 3 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 16–17 <em>patishaptas</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><p><strong>FOR THE CRÊPE</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">75 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">30 g</td>
<td>Sooji (semolina)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Rice grains</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">280 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">30 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 g</td>
<td>Ghee (for greasing)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>FOR THE <em>KHEER</em> (FILLING)</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1.5 kg</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">65 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tsp</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Balloon whisk | fork (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Ladle (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Non-stick pan | <em>appam chatti</em> (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Long spatula | <em>khunti</em> (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Heavy-bottom saucepan | boiling pot (for the <em>kheer</em>)</li>
<li>Wooden spoon (for the <em>kheer</em>)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—MAKE THE CRÊPE BATTER</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Add the rice grains to an electric grinder and blitz them to a fine powder. You now have rice flour.</li>
<li>In a mixing bowl, add the <em>maida</em> (75 g), <em>sooji</em> (30 g), rice flour (10 g), sugar (30 g), salt (¼ tsp), and milk (280 g).</li>
<li>Mix the ingredients together till they are more or less combined. Do not over-mix or your crêpes may turn out chewy.</li>
<li>Cover the batter and set it aside to rest, for 2 hours. This will allow time for the <em>sooji</em> to swell up and the sugar to melt.</li>
<li>While your batter is resting, prepare the <em>kheer</em>, which will form the filling for our <em>patishapta</em>.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—MAKE THE <em>KHEER</em> <a href="https://youtu.be/PzFXjD8D3AY?list=PLGX3dcCcJDYweaL6mlxJ54UAoKZAjNluz" target="_blank" rel="external">WATCH HOW TO MAKE <em>KHEER</em></a></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Take 1.5 kg milk in a heavy-bottom saucepan and set it to boil.</li>
<li>Once bubbling, stir in 65 g sugar.</li>
<li>Keep boiling the milk, while stirring it continuously, for about 90 minutes.</li>
<li>During this entire time, the pot should be on medium to low heat.</li>
<li>At regular intervals of 3–4 minutes, be sure to scrape the solids from the bottom and sides of the pot, and incorporate it into the boiling milk. This step, as well as the previous one, is crucial. We don’t want our <em>kheer</em> to burn at any point.</li>
<li>Once the milk has thickened such that when you lift some of it on your spoon and drop it, it falls in clumps, make a paste of 1 tsp flour and 1 tbsp milk.</li>
<li>Add this paste to the pot. Stir and cook for another 5 minutes.</li>
<li>Allow the <em>kheer</em> to cool before proceeding to the next stage.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—MAKE THE <em>PATISHAPTA</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Divide the <em>kheer</em> in equal portions of 22 g each.</li>
<li>Give your batter a quick stir till it is uniform.</li>
<li>Now, set a non-stick pan on medium-low flame and allow it to heat up completely.</li>
<li>Once the pan is hot, smear it with a very, <em>very</em> light coating of <em>ghee</em> (remember, we are already using a non-stick pan).</li>
<li>Using a ladle, take about 25 g of the batter and drop it in the centre of the pan.</li>
<li>Swirl it around gradually to form a thin crêpe, about 12 cm in diameter.</li>
<li>Roll a portion of the <em>kheer</em> between your palms to form a log (about 8 cm long), and flatten it with your fingers.</li>
<li>Place it at one end of the crêpe and start folding the crêpe into a roll, with the help of a spatula. [Note that we are cooking only one side of the crêpe.]</li>
<li>Transfer the <em>patishapta</em> from the pan to a plate and proceed making the rest. These can be eaten hot, or they can be cooled and stored in the refrigerator for up to 7 days.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This Bengali sweet recipe is a type of &quot;pithe&quot;. It is a light crêpe filled with either kheer (reduced milk) or a coconut-and-gur mixture.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="pithe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pithe/"/>
    
      <category term="sweets" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/sweets/"/>
    
      <category term="jolkhabar" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/jolkhabar/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Doodh Cha | Spiced Milk Tea</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/doodh-cha/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/doodh-cha/</id>
    <published>2017-01-05T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:42:22.534Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A sweet, milky, aromatic concoction steeped with orange pekoe tea</p>

<p class="post-intro">What better way to unwind your days with than with a steaming mug of <em>doodh cha</em>?</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">E</span>ven though commercial cultivation of tea in the country was introduced by the British in the early 19th century, there is nothing else that India has made more its own than its <em>chai</em>. A popular drink across most of South Asia, from posh drawing rooms to humble street shacks, this is a boiled concoction of water, milk, sugar, tea, and occasionally, aromatic spices. Ours is a lighter version of the famed “masala chai” (spiced tea), a perfect accompaniment to an evening snack, be it simple <em>moori-chanachur</em> or something more elaborate. Make yourself this cup of “doodh cha”, not when you desperately need it, but when you feel like you’ve deserved it.</p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 15 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 2 mugs of tea</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">300 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">300 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">8 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Clove</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">8 g</td>
<td>Orange pekoe tea</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mortar and pestle</li>
<li>Saucepan with lid</li>
<li>Tea strainer</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Using a mortar and pestle, roughly crush the clove and cardamom pod. This will help release their flavours.</li>
<li>Wash, peel, and dice the ginger roughly.</li>
<li>Set a saucepan over medium-high heat and add the water, clove, cardamom, and ginger.</li>
<li>Cover the pan and let the water come to a boil. Allow the spices to bubble in water for about 4 minutes.</li>
<li>Add the milk, and once it has heated up, add in the tea and sugar.</li>
<li>Allow this milky mixture to boil vigorously. Just when the tea is about to boil over, drop the heat and let it simmer for about 4 minutes. You can see the tea change colour from light brown to a rosy kind of orange.</li>
<li>Strain and serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Biscuits | rusk</li>
<li>Evening snack</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The Bengali version of the famous masala chai, or tea steeped milk flavoured with cardamom, ginger and spices
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="drink" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/drink/"/>
    
      <category term="tea" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/tea/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Begun Bhaja | Spicy Fried Eggplant or Brinjal</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/begun-bhaja/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/begun-bhaja/</id>
    <published>2016-12-29T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:36:57.199Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">The goodness of perfectly seasoned, pan-fried brinjals</p>

<p class="post-intro">This is a recipe of brinjal fried to an amber-coloured crust on the outside, while remaining soft and mushy inside.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he taste of <em>begun bhaja</em> is difficult to explain to anyone who hasn’t eaten fried brinjals. Suffice it to say that it is probably unlike anything you’ve ever tasted, especially if seasoned with the right amount of salt and sugar. And we won’t even go into how drop-dead gorgeous the finished product is. The recipe is ridiculously simple. You smear thickly sliced brinjals in turmeric and seasoning, and fry them on medium heat in a skillet. The sugar in the marinade allows the brinjals to develop a wonderfully amber-coloured crust, and deepens the flavour of the dish. If you have 20 minutes to spare, give this recipe a try. Eat it along with steaming rice and dal, and you will not regret it.</p>
<p>This recipe uses one large brinjal. When shopping for the vegetable, be sure to select a specimen of the male variety as it is likely to contain far fewer seeds than its female counterpart. You can identify the type of the brinjal by looking at the indentation on its bottom. If the indentation is elongated and deep, it’s a female brinjal. And if it is round and shallow, that’s the seedless, male brinjal.</p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 slices of <em>begun bhaja</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Large brinjal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">a pinch</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¾ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1½ tsp</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¾ tsp</td>
<td>Flour (atta)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">~80 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Frying pan | skillet</li>
<li>Long spatula | <em>khunti</em> | fork</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash the brinjal and chop off its stalk. Cut the vegetable along the cross-section into discs, 2 cm thick. A large brinjal should yield about 6 slices.</li>
<li>In a mixing bowl, combine the turmeric powder, red chilli powder, salt, sugar, and <em>atta</em>.</li>
<li>Add the brinjal slices to the bowl and coat them with the spices.</li>
<li>Cover and let them rest for at least 15 minutes. During this time, the salt and sugar will draw out the water from the brinjal slices and soften them up. The moisture generated will also help all the flavours mingle nicely. So, don’t skip this step.</li>
<li>Now, heat mustard oil in a skillet till it starts smoking lightly. For even frying, the depth of the mustard oil in the pan should be at least 1 cm.</li>
<li>Lower the marinated brinjal slices into the oil one by one and fry them on each side, for about 3 minutes, till they are golden. Make sure that the pan is set on medium-low heat; we want to cook the brinjal slices from the inside while allowing them to develop a nice crust on the outside. Also, keep a close eye on the pan, as the sugar in the marinade may burn.</li>
<li>When golden, lift the <em>begun bhaja</em> from the oil. Hold them against the side of the pan for about 20 seconds to drain out excess oil, or use paper towels to soak it up. Serve hot.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | <em>luchi</em></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Begun Or baingan bhaja is a Bengali vegetarian recipe of shallow-fried eggplant disks. Crunchy outside, soft inside. Cooks in 15 minutes!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Jhinge Alu Posto</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/jhinge-alu-posto/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/jhinge-alu-posto/</id>
    <published>2016-12-22T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:42:44.339Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Potatoes and ridged gourd cooked in a poppy paste</p>

<p class="post-intro">Subtle to taste and mellowing in its effect, this classic preparation is the ultimate comfort food of the siesta-loving Bangali.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">J</span><em>hinge-alu posto</em> is a classic Bengali dish. Sparing in its use of spices, this preparation relies on the flavours inherent in the vegetables (potatoes and ridged gourd) for its taste. What stands out, however, is the nutty flavour of the roasted poppy paste, which also provides body and texture to the gravy. Overall, the taste of this dish is so understated that it is difficult to imagine how its key ingredient, the poppy seed, was actually a residual by-product of the violent history, fraught with all manner of power imbalances and exploitation, of opium trade.</p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Poppy seeds (soaked in water for at least 4 hours)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4 pieces (2 for the paste + 2 for phoron)</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">40 g</td>
<td>Onions (cubed)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">300 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (2 cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">250 g</td>
<td>Jhinge or ridged gourd (2 cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">125 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Frying pan | <em>kadai</em></li>
<li>Long spatula | <em>khunti</em></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak the poppy seeds in hot water for at least 4 hours. You can also soak them overnight in water at room temperature.</li>
<li>Drain the water and place the poppy seeds in a small grinder jar, along with 2 green chillies and cubed onions.</li>
<li>Grind these to a smooth paste, using about 50 g of water. The finer the grind, the better the flavour. So take your time with this step. Once done, set the poppy paste aside.</li>
<li>Heat 25 g vegetable oil in a pan. We don’t use mustard oil in this recipe to preserve the white colour of the dish.</li>
<li>Temper the oil with <em>kaalo jeere</em> and 2 slit green chillies.</li>
<li>Once the spices start crackling, add the cubed potatoes and fry them on medium heat for 4 minutes. The potatoes should not brown, but remain white. Stir them frequently.</li>
<li>Next, add in the <em>jhinge</em>. Fry them for another 4–5 minutes.</li>
<li>Now, add the poppy paste to the pan, along with the salt.</li>
<li>Sauté the vegetables in the poppy paste for around 5–7 minutes. Keep the heat on low and stir often to prevent the paste from sticking to the pan.</li>
<li>Once the poppy paste starts releasing a nutty aroma, add 125 g of hot water along with the sugar.</li>
<li>Let simmer on low heat for another 8–10 minutes, till the potatoes are tender and the gravy has thickened.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | roti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Bengal&#39;s favourite traditional vegetarian dish of potatoes braised in poppy seed paste. Perfect for your afternoon siesta.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to Cook the Perfect Rice</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/</id>
    <published>2016-12-15T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:41:36.983Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A simple technique for that much-yearned-for <em>jhurjhure bhaat</em></p>

<p class="post-intro">In this tutorial, we show you how you can cook the perfect, fluffy, non-sticky rice on an everyday basis to go along with your <em>dal</em>, <em>torkari</em>, or <em>mangsher jhol</em> for the day.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">R</span>ice is Bengal’s staple carbohydrate. Grown in vast quantities in paddy fields across the region, rice is eaten in various forms—boiled, steamed, puffed, or beaten. While the keeper of the Bengali kitchen might break out the precious <em>gobindobhog</em> for <em>polao</em>, <em>payesh</em>, or <em>khichuri</em>, and the <em>basmati</em> for <em>biryani</em>, it is the <em>sheddho chal</em>, or parboiled rice, that is piled onto plates daily. <em>Sheddho chal</em> is named after the technique used to separate the grain from the husk. This process is said to enhance the nutritional profile of the rice and make it easier to digest.</p>
<p>There is something extremely satisfying in sitting down to a meal before a plate of perfectly cooked, non-sticky, pearly-white, fluffy rice. While there are innumerable ways of boiling rice and there appears to be no set formula, keeping a few things in mind is useful. (1) Washing the rice thoroughly and repeatedly helps get rid of the starch that usually contributes to its stickiness. (2) Rice, like pasta, must be boiled in a large pot of water. The water must measure at least 5 times in volume than the volume of uncooked rice. Doing so dilutes the starch and ensures that most of it gets drained out at the end, along with the water. (3) Once the rice is cooked to the desired softness, use a large strainer to remove the excess water. Letting the rice sit in the boiled, starchy water (or not draining off as much of the liquid as possible) will yield a sticky, mushy end product. (4) Sometimes, the iron content in the water tends to produce yellowish rice. For fluffy, white rice, you may add a tablespoon of vinegar or a teaspoon of <em>fitkari</em> (alum) to the boiling pot. (5) Finally, as for boiling time, it will depend on the rice and water you use. Ours usually takes about 25 minutes. We highly recommend that you determine the cooking time for <em>your</em> rice. Once you’ve done that, set a timer whenever you put a pot to boil. When the timer goes off, all you need to do is drain out the water, and you have perfectly cooked rice every single time.      </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>TIME TAKEN</strong> 20 to 30 minutes, depending on the rice and water you use</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 cup</td>
<td>Rice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 cups</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 tbsp</td>
<td>Vinegar (optional)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot | saucepan</li>
<li>Lid for the boiling vessel</li>
<li>Large strainer | colander</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliance"><a href="#Appliance" class="headerlink" title="Appliance"></a>Appliance</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Measure out the rice and place it in a boiling vessel.</li>
<li>Fill the pot with water and wash the rice thoroughly to remove dirt and any excess starch. Rinse and repeat this process till the water runs clear.</li>
<li>Fill the pot with water once again and set it to boil, with the lid on. Rice is a starch that loves water. Be sure to boil it in sufficient water (at least 5 parts water to 1 part rice) if you want your rice to not be sticky.</li>
<li>For fluffy, pearly-white rice, you may also add 1 tbsp of vinegar or 1 tsp of <em>fitkari</em> (alum) to the pot.</li>
<li>Cook the rice till it is just done. Check by lifting a grain between your fingers and mashing it gently. Do not overcook if you want the rice grains to remain firm and separate.</li>
<li>Strain immediately over a colander and allow the water to drain off completely before serving.   </li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The best and wuickest way to cook steamed rice. This detailed video tutorial yields the perfect Bengali jhurjhure bhaat in 30 minutes.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="how to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/how-to/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Rice" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Rice/"/>
    
      <category term="kitchen hacks" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kitchen-hacks/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mughlai Porota</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/mughlai-porota/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/mughlai-porota/</id>
    <published>2016-12-09T06:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:44:55.700Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A layered, deep-fried pastry filled with egg and minced meat</p>

<p class="post-intro">Making this dish at home may seem like a daunting task. And we won’t lie, it does require a fair bit of planning. But for the <em>mughlai porota</em> aficionado, the pay-offs are enormous!</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">M</span><em>ughlai porota</em> is essentially a flaky flour pastry, filled with a mixture of beaten eggs, <em>keema</em>, spices, and seasoning. It differs from other stuffed <em>porotas</em> in that filling cooks inside the <em>porota</em>, and that it is layered.</p>
<p><em>Mughlai porota</em> can be made at home with a little bit of organisation. Plan for the following elements individually, and in this order:</p><p></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>The <em>keema</em></strong>—This is an important component of the filling. We like to use cooked mutton or beef <em>keema</em> (minced meat sautéed with onions, ginger, garlic, green chillies, turmeric, and <em>garam masala</em>). It needs to be prepared in advance.</li>
<li><strong>The dough</strong>—This will form the pastry within which the filling is enclosed. Be sure to knead the flour and set it to rest for at least 30 minutes.</li>
<li><strong>The filling</strong>—While your dough is resting, use this time to chop the onions, green chillies, ginger, and fresh coriander. Toast some peanuts and roughly crush them. Get the bread crumbs and salt out. Beat an egg in a bowl along with all the ingredients and your filling is ready to go!</li>
<li><strong>The sides</strong>—<em>Mughlai porota</em> is served with a cabin-style salad of cucumber, onion, and beet, <em>alu’r torkari</em>, chicken or mutton <em>kosha</em>, and some ketchup. If you want some or all of these sides, be sure to prepare them before your start making the <em>mughlai</em>.</li>
<li><strong>The <em>Mughlai porota</em></strong>—Now that the filling has been prepared, the sides are organised, and the dough has had time to rest, we are ready to bring all these elements together. See below for the full recipe.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 1 <em>mughlai porota</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><p><strong>FOR THE POROTA/PASTRY</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">75 g</td>
<td>Flour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 g</td>
<td>Oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">40 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>FOR THE FILLING</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Egg (beaten)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">20 g</td>
<td>Keema (cooked mutton or beef keema)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Onions (finely diced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Ginger (finely diced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">3 g</td>
<td>Coriander (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5 g</td>
<td>Peanuts (toasted and roughly chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Bread crumbs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">~300 ml</td>
<td>Oil for frying</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl or dish</li>
<li>Rolling pin | large rolling surface</li>
<li>Frying pan</li>
<li>Frying spoon | <em>jhanjhri</em></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>PART I—KNEADING THE DOUGH</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Place the flour, salt, sugar, and 5 g oil in a mixing bowl, and distribute the ingredients evenly.</li>
<li>Add 40 g warm water to the bowl and knead the dough for 5 minutes.</li>
<li>Coat the dough with 2 tablespoons of oil, cover the bowl, and set aside for 30 minutes.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>PART II—PREPARING THE FILLING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Finely dice the onions, and ginger, chop green chillies, and fresh coriander.</li>
<li>Toast the peanuts in a pan till they are lightly coloured, and chop them roughly.</li>
<li>Now, crack an egg in a bowl. Add in the cooked <em>keema</em>, onions, ginger, green chillies, coriander, peanuts, breads crumbs, and salt.</li>
<li>Beat till all the ingredients are well combined.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>PART III—ROLLING THE PASTRY</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Oil your rolling surface and rolling pin.</li>
<li>Place the dough on the surface and start rolling into a thin, rectangular sheet, about 2 mm thick, and 30 cm by 40 cm in dimension.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>PART IV—BRINGING IT ALL TOGETHER</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a frying pan, set over medium heat, pour vegetable oil till it reaches a height of about 3 cm from the bottom of the pan.    </li>
<li>While the oil is heating up, place the filling in the centre of the rolled dough.</li>
<li>Form an envelope by folding the sides of the rolled sheet inward, starting with the longer sides. Press down gently to seal.</li>
<li>Now, fold the shorter sides such that the you have a pocket of filling, securely enclosed within the pastry sheet.</li>
<li>Lower the <em>mughlai</em> into the hot oil and fry on both sides till golden brown. Occasionally pat it down with the frying spoon to make sure that the filling is cooked thoroughly.</li>
<li>Remove the <em>mughlai porota</em> from the oil and place it on a chopping board. The residual heat will cook the egg to perfect doneness. Cut it into square segments and serve while still warm.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Alu’r torkari</li>
<li>Mutton or chicken kosha</li>
<li>Cabin-style salad</li>
<li>Ketchup</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Kolkata cabin-style food is defined by this classic Bengali Mughlai recipe of layered pastry pockets filled with minced meat and eggs.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="cabin food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/cabin-food/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Badhakopi&#39;r Ghonto | Dry Cabbage and Peas Curry</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/badhakopir-ghonto/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/badhakopir-ghonto/</id>
    <published>2016-12-02T04:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:36:22.613Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A dry curry of cabbage</p>

<p class="post-intro">This is a beautifully spiced cabbage-and-peas preparation that is a little hot, a little sweet, and with hints of ginger, <em>ghee</em>, and <em>garam masala</em>.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">B</span><em>adhakopi’r ghonto</em> is essentially prepared by steaming fine shreds of cabbage (about 2 mm wide) in their own moisture, which is drawn out with the help of salt. There are five important points to remember while cooking this dish—(1) The cabbage must be cut as finely as possible. Larger strips will not only take longer to cook, they will fail to give the <em>badhakopi’r ghonto</em> the desired texture; (2) Once you add the cabbage to the pan, don’t add any extra water; (3) Cook on low heat. This will ensure that the moisture extracted from the cabbage doesn’t evaporate too quickly and cause the cabbage to stick to the pan; (4) Always cover the pan with a lid. This will also prevent the moisture generated by the cabbage from evaporating too quickly; (5) Stir intermittently to prevent sticking.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 45 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Dried red chilli (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaf (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Clove (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g (or ¼ tsp)</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">400 g</td>
<td>Cabbage (cut into thin shreds, 2 mm wide)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (diced; 3 cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">50 g</td>
<td>Peas (shelled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">30 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes (diced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">75 g</td>
<td>Prawns (optional; shelled and deveined)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">20 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 g</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">3 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1 g</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Garam masala powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | wok</li>
<li>Lid for cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>PART I—CUTTING THE CABBAGE</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Cut the cabbage into the thinnest possible shreds that you can manage. To make this process easier, deal with the vegetable in sections of 5 cm each. Take a segment, one at a time, and shave off shreds along its cross-section with your knife. Take your time with the cutting, because the outcome of the dish will depend on this step. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wn3EUuW5S7s" target="_blank" rel="external">Watch this video, which shows you how to cut cabbage</a> for <em>badhakopi’r ghonto</em>.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>PART II—TEMPERING THE OIL (<em>PHORON</em>)</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Heat 15 g mustard oil in a pan till it begins to smoke.</li>
<li>Add the <em>phoron</em> (comprising the dried red chilli, bay leaf, cardamom, cinnamon, clove, and cumin seeds) to the oil.</li>
<li>Once the spices start crackling, add in the cubed potatoes.</li>
<li>Fry the potatoes for 3 minutes on low heat, with the lid on.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>PART III—SAUTEEING THE SPICES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Make a paste by mixing together the ginger paste, cumin powder, coriander powder, turmeric powder, red chilli powder, and 80 g of water.</li>
<li>Add this mixture to the potatoes and cook on medium heat till the water dries off.</li>
<li>Add in the diced tomatoes and shelled peas.</li>
<li>Then, add another 80 g of water and sautee the spices till the water dries off.</li>
<li>Add a slit green chilli and cook with the lid on for another minute.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>PART IV—STEAMING THE CABBAGE</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Add the shredded cabbage to the pan, along with the salt.</li>
<li>Fold in the spices and cook on low heat with the lid on. The salt will start dehydrating the cabbage and drawing out its moisture.</li>
<li>Steam the cabbage on low heat, with the lid on, for 12 minutes, stirring intermittently. Keep an eye on the pan to ensure that the cabbage doesn’t stick to the bottom.</li>
<li>Add the sugar and cook for another 15 minutes, stirring intermittently. The sugar will soon start to caramelise. Be sure to scrape down and integrate the lightly browned bits of the <em>torkari</em> that stick to the bottom of your pan (they are yummy!).</li>
<li>This step is optional. You can coat a couple of cleaned prawns in a pinch of salt and turmeric powder, and fry in a separate pan for 30 seconds on each side. Chop the fried prawns in chunks of 1 cm, and add to the <em>ghonto</em>.</li>
<li>Garnish with <em>ghee</em>, powdered <em>garam masala</em>, and a  slit green chilli.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | roti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A mildly spiced dry cabbage curry with peas-a kind of Bengali vegetarian ghonto with delicate flavours of ginger, garam masala and ghee.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="ghonto" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/ghonto/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
      <category term="cabbage" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/cabbage/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bengali Garam Masala - Fresh Homemade</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/</id>
    <published>2016-11-25T04:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:37:41.556Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A fragrant blend of three simple spices</p>

<p class="post-intro"><em>Garam masala</em> is an important component of much of South Asian cooking. It is a blend of whole spices, whose proportions vary from cuisine to cuisine. The Bengali version comprises three simple spices—cardamom, cinnamon, and cloves.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">W</span>hile the <em>garam masala</em> used in most northern and western Indian cooking might contain everything from coriander and cumin seeds to mustard seeds, the Bengali version, in its most basic form, is made up of cardamom, cinnamon, and cloves. The preparation is simple. We dry-roast a blend of the whole spices to awaken their dormant flavours and powder them—either by hand on in an electric grinder. If stored in an airtight container, the <em>masala</em> can keep for months.  </p>
<p>In Bengali cooking, <em>garam masala</em> is used to flavour egg, chicken, mutton, lamb, or beef curries. Along with <em>ghee</em>, it is also used as garnish for several vegetarian preparations (most <em>ghontos</em> and <a href="/tags/dalna/" title="Bengali dalna recipes"><em>dalnas</em></a>, <em>khichuri</em>, and <em>panchmishali torkari</em>). This spice is particularly handy if you want to quickly refresh leftovers. Just add a pinch of it (along with a sliver of <em>ghee</em>) to your day-old <em>torkari</em> while reheating, and no one need be any the wiser!</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 10 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 10 g of <em>garam masala</em> powder</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">7 g</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Cloves (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | wok | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Airtight container</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder | mortar and pestle</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Measure out the whole spices in the given proportion. You may lightly crush them with a pestle or rolling pin before roasting, if you like.</li>
<li>Heat a pan on medium-low flame and add the whole spices to the pan.</li>
<li>Dry-roast them evenly on all sides, stirring continuously, for about 5 minutes. You should be able to smell the fragrance of the <em>garam masala</em> by this point.</li>
<li>Add the toasted spices to a grinder and blitz them till you have a fine powder. You can also use a mortar and pestle to grind by hand.</li>
<li>Store the <em>garam masala</em> powder in an airtight container.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A refined Bengali version of the common Indian garam masala made with just three spices. A pinch can transform your vegetables or protein.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="masala" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/masala/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to Clean and Devein Prawns</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/how-to/clean-and-devein-prawns/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/how-to/clean-and-devein-prawns/</id>
    <published>2016-11-18T05:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:41:15.093Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A step-by-step guide to prepping your prawns</p>

<p class="post-intro">In this tutorial, we show you how to go about cleaning a batch of prawns. It’s not as difficult as you imagine.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">C</span>leaning prawns doesn’t have to be a tedious or messy task. With a bit of organisation, you can get a batch done in no time, and with minimal cleaning-up to do after. As for tools, all you need is a pair of scissors. Apart from that, keep a bin or plastic bag ready to catch the discarded shells and a bowl for the clean prawns. Put on a playlist, podcast, or audiobook of your choice. This last step is optional, but you might as well be entertained while cleaning up some crustacean.</p>
<p>Now, coming to the anatomy of the prawn, consider the parts you want to keep, and those you want to throw away. We usually eat fleshy bits, and discard the shells and other scalier parts. For most Bengali dishes, including <em>chingri malai curry</em> and <em>chingri bhaape</em>, we leave the head and tail of the prawn intact—the head contains all the wonderful flavour and tasty, creamy goodness, while the tail adds a nice presentation detail.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>TIME TAKEN</strong> 20 minutes for 500 g of prawns</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">500 g</td>
<td>Prawns</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>A pair of scissors</li>
<li>A dish or bag for scraps</li>
<li>A bowl or plate for clean prawns</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Things-to-remove"><a href="#Things-to-remove" class="headerlink" title="Things to remove"></a>Things to remove</h2><ul>
<li>The snout</li>
<li>The eyes</li>
<li>The walking legs</li>
<li>The shell</li>
<li>The vein</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Things-to-keep"><a href="#Things-to-keep" class="headerlink" title="Things to keep"></a>Things to keep</h2><ul>
<li>The body or the fleshy part</li>
<li>The head (for flavour and taste)</li>
<li>The tail (for presentation)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Use your scissors and cut off the snout, which is located on the head of the prawn, between the eyes.</li>
<li>Next, snip off the eyes.</li>
<li>Gather together all the walking legs (can be found under the head) and snip them off with your scissors as well.</li>
<li>Now, hold the prawn so that its head faces you, and its dorsal side is pointed upward. Cut through the shell along the (non-existent) spine of the prawn, from the head all the way to the tail.</li>
<li>You should now be able to peel off the shell. If it gets stuck anywhere, give it a tug and it should come loose easily.</li>
<li>Locate the vein along the spine of the prawn.</li>
<li>Pull the vein out and discard it.</li>
<li>You should now have a clean prawn, minus the shells and other pointy parts.</li>
<li>This step is optional, but we don’t throw the scraps away. Place them in a pot of water and simmer for 30 minutes. Strain the liquid and you now have a shrimp stock. Freeze them in ice trays and use the stock cubes while making shrimp fried rice or <em>chingri malai curry</em> for instant flavour-boost.  </li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The best video tutorial to clean, cut and devein shrimps or prawns. Works for Bengali golda or bagda chingri (tiger prawns) too.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="how to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/how-to/"/>
    
    
      <category term="prawns" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/prawns/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="kitchen hacks" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kitchen-hacks/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Chingri Bhaape | Prawns Steamed in Mustard Sauce</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/chingri-bhaape/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/chingri-bhaape/</id>
    <published>2016-11-11T05:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:38:58.283Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Prawns steamed in a spicy mustard paste</p>

<p class="post-intro">Cooks in minutes and posh to look at, this is a potent curry, not for the faint of heart.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">C</span><em>hingri bhaape</em> is a divine treat, and yet, it is ridiculously simple to make. It incorporates the rich flavours of freshly ground mustard, mellowed down with some coconut and yoghurt. While traditionally this dish has always been prepared in a steamer or double-boiler over a stove, we’ve used a microwave in this recipe.</p>
<p>This is an ideal dish to have on the menu if you are having guests over. You can prepare most of it (till Step 10 below) ahead of time, and steam the prawns in the microwave oven when the guests are ready to eat.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">300 g</td>
<td>Shelled and deveined prawns (400 g before cleaning)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">20 g</td>
<td>Mustard seeds (soaked overnight in water)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">20 g</td>
<td>Coconut (chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (3 chopped + 1 slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">40 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">3 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">12 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Scissors | knife (for shelling and deveining the prawns)</li>
<li>Microwaveable bowl (preferably ceramic)</li>
<li>Plastic wrap</li>
<li>Water-tight metal container (optional; if not using a microwave)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Microwave oven</li>
<li>Stove (optional; if not using a microwave)</li>
<li>Pressure cooker | boiling pot with lid (optional; if not using a microwave)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak the mustard seeds in hot water for at least 2 hours. Alternatively, you can also soak them in regular water, overnight.</li>
<li>Shell and devein the prawns. Keep the heads intact; they have all the flavour. The tails add a visual flair, so we keep them as well.</li>
<li>Strain the mustard seeds and add to a grinder jar, along with the salt and 3 green chillies.</li>
<li>Blitz into a fine paste with the help of 50 g water. Scrape down the sides as often as you need, and grind again. Repeat this process till you have a smooth paste.</li>
<li>Now, while the mustard paste is still in the grinder, add the sugar, turmeric powder, and chopped coconut. Blitz again till the coconut breaks down.</li>
<li>Transfer this paste to a microwave-safe bowl.</li>
<li>Add in the yoghurt and mix till uniform.</li>
<li>Fold in the prawns.</li>
<li>Top off with mustard oil and a slit green chilli.</li>
<li>Cover the bowl with a plastic wrap.</li>
<li>Microwave for 5 minutes.</li>
<li>IF YOU ARE NOT USING A MICROWAVE OVEN, place the prawns-and-mustard mixture in a covered steel container (such as a water-tight tiffin box). Bring an inch of water to boil in your pressure cooker or boiling pot. Now, carefully lower the tiffin box in the water. Be sure to check that the water level does not does not reach the lid of your tiffin box. If it does, throw away some of the water till it clears the lid. Cover up the pot/pressure cooker and allow the prawns to steam (for 10–12 minutes in the boiling pot OR for one whistle in a pressure cooker).  </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A traditional Bengali dish of Prawns or shrimps steamed in a sharp mustard and yoghurt sauce. Takes just 5 minutes to cook in microwave!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="prawns" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/prawns/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="mustard" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mustard/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Alu Sheddho | Spicy Mashed Potato</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/alu-sheddho/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/alu-sheddho/</id>
    <published>2016-07-29T04:39:47.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:35:52.528Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Boiled potatoes, flavoured with green chillies and a fat of your choice</p>

<p class="post-intro">This is the Bengali version of the mashed potato in its most basic form. It is made up of just four simple ingredients.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his recipe yields balls of warm, fluffy, buttery mash that you can eat with steaming rice and dal. While there are any number of ways in which you can boil the potatoes, for this recipe, we’ve found that cooking potatoes in an open pot of boiling water will get you the best results. You don’t want the potatoes to absorb too much water while they are cooking, as usually happens in the pressure cooker. In an open pot, you can always stick a fork into the potatoes to check if they are tender. Peeling the potatoes before you add them to the pot is also useful. It eliminates the need to handle hot spuds while removing their skins.</p>
<p>Our favourite way, however, to cook potatoes for this recipe is to put the halved or quartered pieces into the same pot of water as your rice. That way, your <em>alu sheddho</em> is ready at nearly the same time as your rice and there is one less pot to wash at the end of the meal.</p>

<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 balls of <em>alu sheddho</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">340 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (boiled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">12 g</td>
<td>Ghee or butter or mustard oil (any one)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Peel the potatoes and cut them in quarters.</li>
<li>Place the pieces in a pot of water and set them to boil.</li>
<li>Cook the potatoes till they are tender. Use a fork or knife to check if they are done.</li>
<li>Drain the water and transfer the boiled potatoes onto a plate or mixing dish.</li>
<li>While they are still hot, mash the potatoes with a fork.</li>
<li>Add the fat of your choice (ghee or butter or mustard oil), green chillies, and salt.</li>
<li>Continue mashing with a fork or by hand till the mixture is smooth and lump-free.</li>
<li>Form into balls and serve.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The naughtier Indian cousin of the mashed potato-flavoured with ghee or mustard oil and green chllies-a tribute to Bengali love for aloo
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="boiled" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/boiled/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Narkol&#39;er Bora | Coconut fritters</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/narkoler-bora/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/narkoler-bora/</id>
    <published>2016-07-29T04:39:47.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:45:16.421Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Delicately spiced coconut fritters</p>

<p class="post-intro">Q: What’s better than freshly grated coconut?<br>A: Freshly grated coconut, mildly spiced, rolled into balls, and fried till golden brown and delicious.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>hese coconut fritters are a great way to take your <em>bhaat-dal-bhaja</em> game to the next level. They also make for a ridiculously tasty snack.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 9 <em>boras</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">150 g</td>
<td>Coconut (grated)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Rice grains (ground to powder)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">6 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">30 g</td>
<td>Flour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Frying pan | skillet</li>
<li>Perforated frying spoon | <em>jhanjhri</em></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grater | grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>In a dry grinder, finely powder the grains of rice.</li>
<li>Grate the coconut using a grater or an electric grinder.</li>
<li>Chop the green chillies.  </li>
<li>Now, place all the ingredients in a mixing bowl and combine well by hand.</li>
<li>Portion the mixture into balls of 25 g each.</li>
<li>Shape each ball into a disc, making sure the top and bottom are flat for even frying.</li>
<li>Heat oil in a skillet.</li>
<li>Shallow-fry the <em>boras</em> till they are golden brown on both sides.</li>
<li>Remove them from the oil and drain on a rack, colander, or over paper towels.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Coconut fritters- traditional Bengali recipe of fresh coconuts grated, spiced with green chillies, then shallow-fried.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="fritters" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fritters/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Dim&#39;er Dalna or Duck Egg Curry</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/dimer-dalna/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/dimer-dalna/</id>
    <published>2016-07-29T04:39:47.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:41:58.544Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A spicy egg curry</p>

<p class="post-intro">This is one of those rare dishes that manages to be decadent and comforting at the same time</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">E</span>very part of India has its own iteration of the egg curry. The genius of this version is that it makes use of pan-fried boiled eggs. The boiled eggs, lightly coated in salt and turmeric, are fried in oil till they are golden. The crust makes the gravy adhere to the egg, rather than it just sliding off its smooth surface. This is a hearty, filling curry, best served with a plate of steaming rice.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> a serving of 4 eggs</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Sl</th>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"></td>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>OIL</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">1</td>
<td style="text-align:right">20 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">2</td>
<td style="text-align:right">20 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"></td>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong><em>PHORON</em> (TEMPERING)</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">3</td>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Dried red chillies (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4</td>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaves (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">5</td>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">6</td>
<td style="text-align:right">2 pieces</td>
<td>Cloves (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">7</td>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">8</td>
<td style="text-align:right">1 g (or ¼ tsp)</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"></td>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>EGGS AND VEGETABLES</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">9</td>
<td style="text-align:right">4 pieces</td>
<td>Duck or chicken eggs (boiled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10</td>
<td style="text-align:right">4 pieces</td>
<td>Potatoes (diced; 5 cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">11</td>
<td style="text-align:right">100 g</td>
<td>Onions (thinly sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">12</td>
<td style="text-align:right">25 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes (diced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">13</td>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">14</td>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Garlic paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right"></td>
<td style="text-align:right"><strong>SPICES AND SEASONING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15</td>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">16</td>
<td style="text-align:right">2 g</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">17</td>
<td style="text-align:right">4 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder (for the curry)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">18</td>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder (for coating the eggs with)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">19</td>
<td style="text-align:right">1 g</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">20</td>
<td style="text-align:right">6 g</td>
<td>Salt (for the curry)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">21</td>
<td style="text-align:right">6 g</td>
<td>Salt (for boiling potatoes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">22</td>
<td style="text-align:right">¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt (for coating the eggs with)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">23</td>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">24</td>
<td style="text-align:right">1 piece</td>
<td>Green chilli (slit)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Saucepan | boiling pot</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | wok | frying pan | cooking pot</li>
<li>Lid for cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Microwavable bowl (optional)</li>
<li>Plastic wrap (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Microwave (optional)</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>PART I—BOILING AND FRYING THE EGGS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Bring a pot of water to a boil.</li>
<li>Lower the eggs (which should be at room temperature; eggs from the refrigerator might crack when added to boiling water) in the water and cook them on low heat for 6 minutes (duck eggs) or 5 minutes (chicken eggs), with the lid on.</li>
<li>Turn off the heat and let the eggs sit in the hot water for another 3 minutes. We want the yolks gooey.</li>
<li>Drain the water and remove the shells.</li>
<li>Prick the eggs all around with a toothpick. This will prevent the eggs from bursting when fried and also allow the gravy to seep to the yolk.</li>
<li>Coat the eggs in ¼ tsp each of salt and turmeric powder.</li>
<li>Fry the eggs in 10 g mustard oil on medium heat for 5 minutes, till they develop an even amber-coloured crust.</li>
<li><p>Set aside.</p>
<p><strong>PART II—BOILING THE POTATOES</strong></p>
</li>
<li>Peel and cut the potatoes in chunks of 5 cm. We need as many pieces of potatoes as there are eggs (four, in this case).</li>
<li>Place them in a microwaveable bowl with 6 g of salt and 2 tablespoons of water.</li>
<li>Cover with cling film and microwave for 3 minutes. Alternatively, you can also boil them on the stove till partially cooked.</li>
<li><p>Set aside.</p>
<p><strong>PART III—PREPARING THE CURRY</strong></p>
</li>
<li>Now, heat 20 g mustard oil in a pan.</li>
<li>Temper the oil with the <em>phoron</em> (dried red chillies, bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and cumin seeds).</li>
<li>Once the whole spices start to crackle in oil, add the chopped onions and sugar to the pan and fry on medium heat for 5–7 minutes.</li>
<li>Add the ginger paste and minced garlic to the pan, and fry for another 3–4 minutes.</li>
<li>Make a spice paste by adding 50 g water to the cumin powder, coriander powder, turmeric powder, red chilli powder, and salt.</li>
<li>Add this mixture to the pan and cook on medium heat till the water dries off.</li>
<li>Then, add another 50g of water, along with the tomatoes and green chilli, and cook till the water dries off again.</li>
<li>Add the parboiled potatoes and cook on low heat for 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Then add the eggs. Cook for another minute. Stop here if you want <em>dim’er kosha</em>, a rich gravy to accompany your fried rice or <em>luchi</em>. For a lighter curry to eat with steamed rice, proceed to the next step.</li>
<li>Now, add 225 g hot water to the pan. This will form the curry.</li>
<li>Boil for 5–7 minutes with the lid on before removing from the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Steamed rice</a></li>
<li>Fried rice</li>
<li>Luchi</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The ultimate Bengali egg curry made with duck eggs-boiled, fried golden, then cooked in onion-garlic-ginger-tomato-garam masala sauce.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="dalna" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dalna/"/>
    
      <category term="curry" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/curry/"/>
    
      <category term="egg" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/egg/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Luchi</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/luchi/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/luchi/</id>
    <published>2016-07-29T04:39:47.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-02T08:44:01.852Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A light, flaky, puffed-up, deep-fried, sublime bread</p>

<p class="post-intro">We share with you the tips and tricks to making the perfect <em>luchis</em>, including a special hack for beginners.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">L</span><em>uchis</em> are made from finely milled flour, as opposed to their close cousins, the <em>puris</em>, which are usually prepared with whole-wheat flour. Our recipe calls for a soft dough, reasonably well-hydrated, that should be kneaded for no less than 5 minutes continuously. With the proportion of the flour to water specified here, the dough may seem tacky at first, but fight the urge to add more flour to counter the wetness. Instead, continue kneading and the water will soon be absorbed into the flour.</p>
<p>Another tip that a lot of beginners would benefit from is this: allow the dough to rest at each stage—after kneading, after portioning, and after shaping the portions into little balls. This relaxes the dough, and makes it easier to handle. Finally, if you have trouble rolling out the <em>luchis</em>, try doing so between two sheets of well-greased baking paper. This helps apply even pressure, which is important if you want the <em>luchis</em> to inflate when fried.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 20 <em>luchis</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:right">Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">200 g</td>
<td>Flour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">4 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">15 g</td>
<td>Oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:right">110 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Lid for the bowl | plastic wrap</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
<li>Frying pan | <em>kadai</em> | wok</li>
<li>Perforated frying spoon | <em>jhanjhri</em></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Place the flour in a bowl with the salt, sugar, and oil, and distribute the ingredients well by hand.</li>
<li>Add the hot water.</li>
<li>Set your timer for 10 minutes and knead the dough till it is soft and supple. The dough might seem a bit sticky at first, but take your time and knead it well, incorporating all the water.</li>
<li>Cover the dough with either a lid, wet towel, or plastic wrap, and allow it to rest for at least 30 minutes.</li>
<li>Portion the dough in 20 equal balls of 16–17 g each.</li>
<li>Shape each portion of the dough into a round ball. Resting the dough for 5 minutes each before shaping and rolling will make the job easier.</li>
<li>Roll each ball into a disc of about 10 cm in diameter. Beginners may roll out the <em>luchis</em> between two sheets of well-oiled baking paper. This will help apply pressure evenly.</li>
<li>Lower the discs into hot oil set over medium heat and fry the <em>luchis</em> one at a time, gently patting their tops with the flat end of your frying spoon to make them puff.</li>
<li>Drain the fried <em>luchis</em> on a rack, colander, or over paper towels.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Chhola’r dal</li>
<li>Alu’r torkari</li>
<li>Shada phulkopi’r torkari</li>
<li>Alu’r dom</li>
<li>Dim’er kosha</li>
<li>Kosha maangsho</li>
<li>Payesh</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The ultimate video recipe for Bengali breakfast dish-luchi (or Indian poori) served best with kosha mangsho, chholar dal, or alur dom
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="breakfast" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/breakfast/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
