<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Bong Eats | Bengali Recipe Videos</title>
  <subtitle>Bong Eats is about food from Bengal. And that&#39;s not just Bengali food.</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://bongeats.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-12T04:08:40.247Z</updated>
  <id>https://bongeats.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Bong Eats</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Nolen Gur’er Payesh</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/nolen-gurer-payesh/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/nolen-gurer-payesh/</id>
    <published>2018-01-12T04:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T04:08:40.247Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Bengali rice pudding with date palm jaggery</p>

<p class="post-intro">A good nolen gur’er payesh (Bengali rice pudding) is one with a rich, creamy, silky texture and just the right amount of sweetness.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>Getting the <em>nolen gur’er payesh</em> recipe right is one of life’s most rewarding experiences. Also known as <em>khejur patali gur’er payesh</em> because it uses date palm (<em>khejur</em>) jaggery in solid form (<em>patali</em>) as a sweetener, this Bengali sweet recipe can double as a snack and an after-meal dessert. Whether you call it ‘payesh’ or ‘payasam’ or ‘kheer’, this is one of those quintessential Indian sweet dishes that transcends cultures and cuisines.</p>
<p><em>Nolen gur’er payesh</em> (rice pudding with date palm jaggery) is made by boiling rice and milk together to produce a creamy reduction. It is a Bengali winter specialty since <em>nolen gur</em> is available during the season. Used in a wide variety of Bengali sweet dishes during the winter months, <em>nolen gur</em> brings a depth of flavour and smell, in addition to mellow sweetness, to whatever dish it is added. </p>
<p>The key ingredients required for making a good payesh are fragrant <em>gobindobhog</em> rice (<em>notun aatop chaal</em>—new, freshly harvested, non-parboiled rice), full fat milk, and good quality <em>nolen gur</em>. The milk to rice ratio is quite high in this recipe (1 litre milk for 50g rice). The fat in whole milk lends creaminess to the <em>payesh</em> and starch in ‘new’ rice helps thicken it. In case you can’t find <em>gobindobhog</em> rice where you live, the ‘kalijira’ or ‘jeera samba’ varieties will also do in a pinch. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 316 kcal per paratha</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 litre</td>
<td>Full fat milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>New Gobindobhog rice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Nolen gur (date palm jaggery)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Cashew</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Raisins (soaked and drained)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Strainer</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak the rice in water for 30 minutes. Do not overwash the rice as we don’t want to lose too much starch. After 30 minutes, strain the rice and spread it to dry. Coat the soaked rice in ¼ tsp of ghee and set aside. </li>
<li>Soak the raisins in some water to allow them to swell. Heat ghee in a pan and fry the cashewnuts on medium heat until they are golden. Remove from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>Transfer the milk to a heavy pan or kadai. On medium heat, wait for it to come to a boil. After that, reduce the milk for about 15 minutes. Stir regularly so that the milk does not catch the bottom or sides of the pan. </li>
<li>Add the ghee-coated rice to the milk and keep cooking on low heat until the rice is fully cooked. This will require patience, as at several points it will appear as if the rice has cooked. However, you need to keep boiling it until you reach a stage where a grain mashed between your fingers faces no resistance at all. It should be mushy soft, as rice will harden when payesh is cooled. Stir gently throughout this process. Not only will that ensure that the payesh doesn’t burn, stirring will also release the starch from the rice, which will help thicken the payesh.</li>
<li>Now is it is time to add the gur. But you need to be sure of two things before that.<br>(a) The rice should be fully cooked because after adding the gur, the rice will not cook any further.<br>(b) The payesh should be slightly thicker than how you actually want it as gur will loosen it up slightly. Right. Now <em>turn off the heat</em> and  add the gur, along with salt, soaked raisins, and fried cashew. Keep <em>heat turned off</em> as any impurities in the gur will cause the milk to split. Fold everything in and cover the pan. Allow the residual heat to melt the gur fully. Serve hot or cool. </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/luchi/">Luchi</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A good nolen gur’er payesh (Bengali rice pudding) is one with a rich, creamy, silky texture and just the right amount of sweetness.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="rice" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rice/"/>
    
      <category term="sweet" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/sweet/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Parshe Machh’er Jhal Shorshe Diye</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/parshe-macher-jhal-shorshe-begun-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/parshe-macher-jhal-shorshe-begun-diye/</id>
    <published>2018-01-04T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-05T06:27:54.112Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Parshe fish cooked in a mustard curry</p>

<p class="post-intro">Fresh parshe simmered in a potent and flavourful mustard gravy, this Bengali fish curry is easy to prepare and insanely delicious.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">S</span>horshe diye parshe macher jhol (or parshe macher jhal) is a simple and delectable Bengali fish curry. Here, fresh parshe is simmered in a potent and flavourful mustard gravy. This Bengali fish-curry recipe is easy to prepare, insanely delicious, and requires only a handful of ingredients. The star of the show is, of course, fresh parshe. A freshwater catch with a soft sheen, parshe (a kind of mullet) is identifiable by its small, triangular mouth and slender shape. The fish is soft, flaky, and sweet to the taste—all of which are perfectly complemented by the fiery, potent flavours from the mustard gravy.<br></p><p></p>
<p>This parshe macher jhal recipe is rather simple. The only finicky bit is grinding mustard seeds to a smooth paste until completely non-grainy. We’re using a mix of yellow and black mustard for a balance of flavour and sharpness. Besides fresh parshe, this recipe uses dal’er bori (sun-baked lentil dumplings) and brinjal, both of which soak up the flavourful curry, and provide a contrast of tastes and textures to this warm, comforting parshe macher jhol.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 45 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Parshe machh</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 pcs</td>
<td>Dal’er bori (sun-baked lentil dumplings)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Brinjal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Yellow and black mustard seeds (soaked for 2 hours)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt (beaten)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking and garnish)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Salt (plus ¾ tsp for coating fish with)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder (plus ¾ tsp for coating fish with)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Clean the fish, and coat it with ¾ tsp each of salt and turmeric. Let it rest for 15 minutes. </li>
<li>Meanwhile, add the soaked-and-strained mustard seeds to a grinder jar along with 2 roughly chopped green chillies and 80 g water. Blitz everything into a smooth paste. The finer and non-grainier the paste, better the flavour. You may need to scrape down the sides of your jar and keep blending until the mustard paste is smooth.</li>
<li>Coming to the veggies, roughly chop the tomato and cut the brinjal in 5-cm long pieces.</li>
<li>In a kadai set on medium heat, heat 35 g mustard oil until it is smokes lightly and changes colour to a pale yellow. Add the dal’er bori and fry for about 20 seconds, or until the bori is golden brown. Strain from the oil and set aside. Now, in the same pan fry the brinjal until it is golden too (about 4 minutes), and starin and set aside. Finally, lower the marinated fish, one at a time. Fry fish in batches in a single layer, for a minute on each side. Drain from the oil and set these aside too. </li>
<li>Check your oil at this point. If it is not too burnt from all the frying, add kaalo jeere to it (if it is burnt, you may want to replace it with fresh oil). Then add the chopped tomato and fry for about 10 seconds, after which add the green chillies. Fry until they crackle (another 10 seconds). </li>
<li>Add the mustard paste and sauté on medium heat for about 4 minutes. Add the salt and turmeric, and cook for another 6 minutes until the raw smell from the spices in gone. Whenever the mixture dries out, add a splash of water and keep frying. </li>
<li>Add the yoghurt and sugar, and cook for 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Now add 300 g hot water. This will form the curry. Add the fried bori and allow the curry to come to a boil. Then add the fried brinjal. Simmer gently for about 3 minutes, after which lower the fried parshe one by one, making sure the fish are submerged in the curry. Do not stir or disturb too much because the fish is going to be delicate at this point and likely to break. Cook the fish in the curry for about 5 minutes on low heat. </li>
<li>Finish off with freshly chopped coriander leaves and a drizzle of raw mustard oil (about 5 g). </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Fresh parshe simmered in a potent and flavourful mustard gravy, this Bengali fish curry is easy to prepare and insanely delicious.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="parshe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/parshe/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Niramish Alu’r Dom</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/niramish-aloo-dum/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/niramish-aloo-dum/</id>
    <published>2017-12-28T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-29T06:42:14.189Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Bengali ‘vegetarian’ curried winter potatoes</p>

<p class="post-intro">Bengali-style juicy curried new baby potatoes cooked in a savoury, tangy sauce and sprinkled with green peas.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>lu’r dom is the Bengali avatar of the popular Indian dish of spicy curried potatoes, commonly known as ‘aloo dum’ or ‘dum aloo’ (Kashmiri aloo dum is perhaps its most famous variant). Prepared in Bengal during the winter months using the newly harvested baby potatoes or ‘notun alu’, alu’r dom is best enjoyed with luchi, koraishuti’r kochuri, polao, fried rice, or porota. This simple recipe is for the <em>niramish</em> (vegetarian) version, which, in Bengali cuisine means it makes no use of onion or garlic. It can, therefore, be served as bhog.<br></p><p></p>
<p>The key to a good alu’r dom is perfectly tender and uniformly salted potatoes, because who enjoys under-seasoned spuds? In this recipe, the baby potatoes are twice boiled—first in heavily salted water (with skin on) and then again in the curry—for a total of nearly one hour. ‘Notun alu’ are notorious in that they don’t allow salt and spices to penetrate easily. They must, therefore, be cooked longer than one would normally cook potatoes.</p>
<p>This is not a strictly traditional version of the Bengali niramish alu’r dom, but our take on this classic and well-loved recipe. It produces juicy alu’r dom with a rich, dry gravy, ready to be mopped up with a piece of light, fluffy luchi. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 75 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 187 kcal</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>700 g</td>
<td>New baby potatoes (notun alu)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Peas (blanched)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Hing (asafoetida)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1½ tsp</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Amchur (dried mango powder)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Beetnoon (black salt)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Green chilli paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Tomato ketchup</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Cashewnuts (ground)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Kasuri methi (dried fenugreek leaves)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45 g</td>
<td>Total salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Bengali garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Hot water (for the gravy)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot with lid</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Mortar and pestle</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Place the baby potatoes in a saucepan or boiling pot along with 30 g salt and 1 litre water. Boil the potatoes until tender. This should take about 30 minutes. Boiling the potatoes in heavily salted water ensures that they are uniformly seasoned. Besides, it also causes the potatoes to lose water, because of osmosis, improving their texture.</li>
<li>Once the potatoes are tender, drain the water and peel them immediately. Coat with 10 g of salt while the potatoes are still hot. This will help in further absorption of salt.</li>
<li>Before you begin make a paste of cumin powder, coriander powder, amchur, black salt, ginger paste, and 25 g water, and keep at the ready.</li>
<li>Heat 30 g mustard oil in a pan. Temper it with dried red chillies, bay leaves, cloves, cardamom, cinnamon, cumin seeds, and hing. Allow the hing to fry for about 10 seconds before adding turmeric powder and kashmiri red chilli powder. Fry for 20 seconds. We would normally add turmeric and red chilli to the paste we made earlier, but for this dish, frying them directly in oil will lend the gravy a rich red colour. However, dry spices are prone to getting burnt in oil, so be very careful and keep the heat low.</li>
<li>Next, stir in the spice paste. Cook until the smell of raw spices is gone and they have started to release oil. This should take about 5 minutes. Meanwhile, beat the yoghurt until it is lump-free. Add it to the pan, stirring vigorously to prevent it from splitting. Cook off the raw yoghurt for a couple of minutes before stirring in the ketchup.</li>
<li>Now add the boiled and salted potatoes, and fold them in. Sauté them with the spices for about 4 minutes. We’ve chosen not to fry the potatoes before adding them, as boiling them directly in the curry leads to juicier potatoes. </li>
<li>Add the remaining salt (5 g) and all of the sugar to the pan, along with 400 g of hot water. This will form the gravy. Crumble kasuri methi and add that to the pan too. Cover and allow the potatoes to simmer in the curry for about 20 minutes until the gravy has reduced and the potatoes are juicy and tender. Stir regularly so the bottom doesn’t catch.</li>
<li>Once the gravy has reduced, add the ground cashew and blanched peas. Cook for a minute before garnishing with ghee and <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">garam masala</a>. Turn off heat, cover, and allow alu’r dom to rest for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/koraishutir-kochuri/">Koraishuti’r kochuri</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/luchi/">Luchi</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/">Fried rice</a></li>
<li>Polao</li>
<li>Porota</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Bengali-style juicy curried new baby potatoes cooked in a savoury, tangy sauce and sprinkled with green peas.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="potato" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/potato/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Vegetable Chop or Cutlet</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/vegetable-chop/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/vegetable-chop/</id>
    <published>2017-12-21T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-29T06:47:33.723Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Croquettes of seasonal beetroot, carrots, potatoes and peas</p>

<p class="post-intro">Bengali-style vegetable chops—a popular winter snack—are breaded, deep-fried croquettes made of seasonal beetroot and carrots.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">B</span>engalis look forward to nothing more on winter evenings than a batch of hot-off-the-oil fried snack and a cup of sweet, milky tea. Once such snack is the delicious (may we even say nutritious?) Kolkata-style vegetable chop, also known as ‘beet chop’ or ‘veg cutlet’. Best championed by patrons of roadside shacks, ‘telebhaja dokan’, and cabins, this popular and easy-to-make Bengali vegetarian snack is enjoyed with a simple salad of onions and cucumbers, and a dollop of kasundi. Full of the goodness of the seasonal beetroots and carrots, both of which are winter vegetables in Bengal, the vegetable chop (or veg cutlet) is crunchy on the outside, soft on the inside, and rather sweet to taste. It is a landmine of flavour and texture, which come from the veggies, spices, and nuts used.<br></p><p></p>
<p>In this Bengali vegetable chop recipe, we recreate a Kolkata street food, which is also one of the most beloved Bengali snacks of all time. The main ingredient of this easy Bengali veg recipe is beetroot, which lends the chop its characteristic vibrant maroon colour. Besides that, this recipe also uses a unique blend of spices. Follow this video to learn how to make a Kolkata-style vegetable chop of the perfect texture and flavour.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 90 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 16 chops<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 141 kcal per chop</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Beetroot</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Carrots</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Potatoes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Fennel seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 pc</td>
<td>Peppercorns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Amchur (dry mango powder)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Coconut (sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Peanuts (halved)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Panch phoron</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR BREADING CHOPS</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Flour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Eggs (beaten)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Breadcrumbs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~300 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for deep frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot | steamer </li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li><em>Jhhanjhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—MAKE THE FILLING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Halve or quarter the potatoes and steam them until they are tender. Peel the skins and mash thoroughly. Steaming keeps the potatoes dry and fluffy.</li>
<li>Chop beetroot and carrots into 3-cm matchsticks. Finely chop the green chillies and coriander. Divide the coconut into 5 mm chunks. </li>
<li>Grind together cumin, fennel, cloves, cinnamon, cardamom, peppercorns, bay leaves, dried red chillies, and amchur.</li>
<li>In a pan, heat 30 g vegetable oil. Add the coconut slices and fry them until they are golden. This should take about 30 seconds. Remove them from the oil and set aside. Next, add the peanuts and fry them too until they are golden (about 75 seconds). Drain and set aside.</li>
<li>Temper the same oil with panch phoron. Wait for it to crackle. Add the chopped green chillies and ginger paste, and fry for about 2 minutes. </li>
<li>Follow these with the chopped beetroot, along with a large pinch or two of salt (to help soften the beet). Cook until the beet turns slightly limp, about 3 minutes, after which add the chopped carrots. Add the remaining salt and cook the veggies on medium heat until they are soft. However, don’t let them turn mushy or disintegrate, or we’ll lose texture.</li>
<li>Once the vegetables are well done, add the ground spices, cover the pan, and allow everything to cook for about 2 minutes. After that, add the sugar followed by mashed potatoes. Mix everything gently until uniform so that the strands of carrots and beet do not break. </li>
<li>Turn off the heat and add ghee, fried coconut and peanuts, and chopped coriander. Mix well. Allow the mixture to cool completely.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—BREADING AND FRYING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Divide into 50 g portions and form cylindrical croquettes about 7 cm long and 3 cm in diameter. Once all the chops are formed, it’s time to bread them.</li>
<li>Dredge the chops lightly in flour and dip them in the eggwash. Transfer them on to a dish of breadcrumbs and cover them entirely, pressing them so that they stick. Repeat this eggwash-and-breadcrumb routine one more time to form a second layer of the coating. This will give extra crispy chops. You may prepare the chops up to this stage and freeze them in airtight containers for up to a month. Fry them as you need them—there’s no need to defrost.</li>
<li>Fry the chops in hot oil (180°C) on medium heat until they are golden brown. Drain and serve hot.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/doodh-cha/">Doodh Cha (masala tea)</a></li>
<li>Cabin-style salad</li>
<li>Kasundi</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Bengali-style vegetable chops—a popular winter snack—are breaded, deep-fried croquettes made of seasonal beetroot and carrots.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="potato" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/potato/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Calcutta Christmas Fruitcake</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/calcutta-christmas-fruitcake/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/calcutta-christmas-fruitcake/</id>
    <published>2017-12-15T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-15T04:21:51.707Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A boozy, fruit-and-nut encrusted indulgence</p>

<p class="post-intro">The tradition of eating Christmas cakes in Calcutta is an old one, popularised by bakers like Nahoum and Saldanha.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">F</span>ruitcakes are a big deal in Calcutta. Come Christmas, shops spring up all over the city selling Christmas cakes, or ‘Borodin’er cake’. The tradition of baking, gifting, and eating plum cakes around Christmas is an old one. Families celebrating Christmas in Kolkata soak their dried fruits weeks in advance and book their slots with their local bakers for community baking of their cakes. Making a Christmas fruitcake at home is easy, to say nothing of rewarding.  Such fruitcakes contain their characteristic booze-soaked fruits and nuts, which can be customised in dozens of ways. In this recipe, we show you how to bake an indulgent Christmas fruitcake at home.<br></p><p></p>
<h2 id="About-the-tin"><a href="#About-the-tin" class="headerlink" title="About the tin"></a>About the tin</h2><p>We like our Christmas cake as a good-sized loaf. A 9 × 4 inch (25 × 11 cm) rectangular loaf tin perfectly holds our batter for a 4-pound cake. This is a deep tin, which produces a hefty fruitcake that can be portioned into slices. However, since such a tin is so deep and narrow, we’ve taken some special precautions to ensure that the cake (a) rises evenly, (b) doesn’t crack or dome on the top, (c) cooks to a rich brown colour right up to the centre, without (d) the sides drying out during its long stint in the oven.</p>
<h3 id="Preparing-the-tin"><a href="#Preparing-the-tin" class="headerlink" title="Preparing the tin"></a>Preparing the tin</h3><ul>
<li>Butter the inside of the tin, making sure to get into all the corners. </li>
<li>Line the tin with two sheets of baking paper <a href="https://youtu.be/Cd0x661PujE?t=2m43s" target="_blank" rel="external">as shown in the video</a>, leaving about 5 cm excess overhanging paper on both sides for easier cae removal later on.</li>
<li>Optionally, <strong>wrap a cake strip</strong> to the outside of the tin for added protection. You can easily make a cake strip at home as follows:</li>
<li>Measure the circumference and height of your tin. </li>
<li>Cut a sheet of newspaper about 4–5 times as wide as the height of your tin and long enough to wrap around it.</li>
<li>Keep folding the newspaper into a strip as wide as the height of the tin.</li>
<li>Wet this strip with water, squeezing out any excess.</li>
<li>Cover the whole strip in aluminium foil.</li>
<li>Wrap it around the tin and secure it with a piece of wet cotton twine.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="The-oven"><a href="#The-oven" class="headerlink" title="The oven"></a>The oven</h2><p>This cake bakes at a low temperature of 150°C. In a deep and narrow loaf tin like the one we’re using here, it takes around 3.5 hours. If you try to bake this cake faster by raising the temperature, the outside will brown while the inside remains pale and undercooked. Having said that, keep in mind that every oven is different. Be sure to check on your cake after the first 2 hours in the oven. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 4 hours (including 3 hours of oven time)<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4-pound cake (serves 20–25 people)<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 316 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>SOAKING THE FRUITS</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Raisins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Pitted dates</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Dried apricots</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Tutti frutti</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Crystallised ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>125 g</td>
<td>Orange/mixed peels</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>180 ml</td>
<td>Dark rum/whiskey/brandy</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>BAKING THE CAKE</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>275 g</td>
<td>Flour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>275 g</td>
<td>Salted butter (softened; extra for greasing)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>275 g</td>
<td>Brown sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5</td>
<td>Eggs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Almonds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Cashewnuts</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Pistachio</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>From one orange</td>
<td>Orange zest</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4-cm stick</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Nutmeg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 pcs</td>
<td>Allspice berries (optional)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><amp-img alt="Equipments used in baking the cake" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/dmpeew57x/image/upload/q_auto:good/v1511470622/tools_v2_mmmg7w.png" width="1920" height="1111" layout="responsive"><br></amp-img></p>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Balloon whisk</li>
<li>Spatula</li>
<li>9 × 4 inch rectangular loaf tin</li>
<li>Greaseproof baking paper</li>
<li>Aluminium foil (optional)</li>
<li>Weighing scale</li>
<li>Knife</li>
<li>Sieve</li>
<li>Grater</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>OTG or convection oven (you can’t bake this in microwave mode)</li>
<li>Grinder | spice grinder | mortar and pestle</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><h3 id="Soaking-the-fruits"><a href="#Soaking-the-fruits" class="headerlink" title="Soaking the fruits:"></a>Soaking the fruits:</h3><p><amp-youtube data-videoid="Wgrv5ithNrg" layout="responsive" width="480" height="270"><br></amp-youtube></p>
<ol>
<li>Chop dates, apricots, ginger, and orange peels into 1 cm chunks.</li>
<li>Put the chopped dates, apricots, ginger, and orange peels along with the raisins, and the tutti frutti into an airtight glass jar.</li>
<li>Pour 180 ml of dark rum (we are using Old Monk), or brandy, or whiskey or a mixture into the jar over the fruits.</li>
<li>Shut the jar and leave it in a cool, dark place for 20 days. Give the jar a mild shake every couple of days.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="Baking-the-cake"><a href="#Baking-the-cake" class="headerlink" title="Baking the cake:"></a>Baking the cake:</h3><ol>
<li>Grind the cloves, cinnamon, nutmeg, and allspice to a fine powder. Also grind up the almonds separately. Set these aside.</li>
<li>Zest an entire orange, making sure not to grate any of the white pith as it is bitter. Chop up the cashew and pistachio into 5 mm pieces.</li>
<li>Prepare the tin as explained above and set your oven to preheat at 150°C.</li>
<li>In a large mixing bowl, cream the butter until it is airy and pale. Add in the brown sugar and cream again.</li>
<li>Now whisk in the eggs, one at a time. Follow this with the ground almond, spice mix, and orange zest. Incorporate everything thoroughly. Get rid of your whisk; you won’t need it after this point. </li>
<li>Sift in the flour and fold it in using a rubber spatula. Make sure to not overmix the batter after you add the flour as the cake may turn chewy.</li>
<li>Add the chopped cashew and pistachio. Also add your rum-soaked dried fruits. The fruits should have absorbed all the alcohol, but if they contain excess liquid, strain and add just the fruits.</li>
<li>Mix everything until well combined, but don’t overwork the batter.</li>
<li>Spoon the batter into your prepared cake tin, pushing it into all the corners and leveling the top. Tap out any trapped air bubbles.</li>
<li>Place it in the preheated oven and bake for 3.5 hours, checking on it regularly after the first 2 hours. Your cake is done when a thermometer inserted in the centre registers a temperature of 95°C, or when a skewer comes out clean. Your cake should develop a rich brown colour.   </li>
<li>Remove the cake from the oven and allow it to cool completely in the tin. This should take about 5 hours or so.</li>
<li><strong>Feed the cake:</strong> This step is optional. Poke holes in the cake with a skewer. ‘Feed’ a spoon of rum, brandy, or whisky through the holes. You can do this once a week for as long as you want, until you are ready to cut the cake. Store it at room temperature wrapped in baking paper and aluminium foil. </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>A cup of Darjeeling or coffee</li>
<li>Mulled wine</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The classic Calcutta fruitcake—a fixture in many homes around Christmas-time—is a rum-soaked, fruit-and-nut encrusted indulgence.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="Christmas" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Christmas/"/>
    
      <category term="cake" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/cake/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="sweet" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/sweet/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Koraishuti’r Kochuri</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/koraishutir-kochuri/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/koraishutir-kochuri/</id>
    <published>2017-12-07T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-08T05:12:36.877Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Deep-fried, puffy bread stuffed with a spiced green-peas-and-hing filling</p>

<p class="post-intro">Koraishutir kochuri is a deep-fried, puffy bread, stuffed with a filling of mildly spiced, hing-infused green peas or ‘koraishuti’.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span><em>oraishutir kochuri</em> is a deep-fried, puffy bread, stuffed with a filling of mildly spiced green peas (or <em>koraishuti</em>!). Making <em>koraishutir kochuri</em> is not difficult, as this recipe will tell you, if you follow each step one at a time. Also known as <em>motorshutir kochuri</em>, this Bengali vegetarian delight is one of the most beloved breakfast, <em>jolkhabar</em> (snack), or <em>biyebari</em>-menu (wedding feast) items. Follow our step-by-step <em>koraishutir kochuri</em> recipe to learn how to make to make light, puffy, non-greasy <em>kochuris</em>. Serve these hot with <em>alu’r dom</em> or <em>chhola’r dal</em>. </p>
<p>There are several factors which impact how your will <em>kochuris</em> turn out. First, the dough must be kneaded until smooth and rested for at least 30 minutes. Second, care must be taken while stuffing and rolling to ensure that the filling and dough are uniformly distributed. Finally, while frying, the oil should be hot (200°C+) to allow the <em>kochuris</em> to puff up. </p>
<p>This <em>koraishutir kochuri</em> recipe takes you through the process of preparing, stuffing, rolling out, and frying the most delicious and flaky <em>koraishutir kochuris</em> you’ve had! As a bonus, we’ve also thrown in a special tip for beginners and an ingenious hack for how you can prepare and store these ahead of time for a party, courtesy of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ehGnsllaqHs&amp;t=396s" target="_blank" rel="external">Foodie’s Hut</a>!</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 90 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 10 servings<br><strong>calories</strong> 138 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE DOUGH</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Maida (all-purpose flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 pc</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 pcs</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE FILLING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Green peas (shelled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Hing (asafoetida)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>Oil for frying</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Saucepan with lid</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li><em>Jhhanjhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>In a mixing bowl, combine <em>maida</em>, 3 g salt, 7 g sugar, and 15 g oil. Add warm water and knead for 5 minutes into a smooth dough. Cover and allow the dough to rest for 30 minutes.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, shell the peas and drop them in a saucepan of boiling water. Cover and cook until the peas are soft (about 3 minutes). Strain and transfer to a grinder jar. Add green chillies, 4 g salt, and 3 g sugar. Blitz to a fine paste, scraping sides and adding a little water, as needed. </li>
<li>In a small bowl, combine the ginger, cumin powder, coriander powder and 1 tbsp water to form a paste. Set aside.</li>
<li>Heat 10 g oil in a pan. Temper it with <em>kaalo jeere</em> and <em>hing</em>. Add the ginger, cumin, and coriander paste, and fry for 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Now add the ground peas. Sauté on medium heat for about 6 minutes until the mixture dries out and gathers around the spatula in a lump. Set the filling aside to cool.</li>
<li>Divide the dough in 25 g portions and the filling in 10 g portions. </li>
<li>Stuff the dough with the filling as shown in the video.</li>
<li>Oil the rolling pin and surface well. Roll the <em>kochuris</em> with a gentle hand, applying even pressure, to a diameter of 14 cm.</li>
<li>Lower it into hot oil (200°C+). Gently press down to allow the <em>kochuris</em> to puff up. Fry both sides evenly until golden. Drain from the oil and serve hot.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Alu’r dom</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/cholar-dal">Chhola’r dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/begun-bhaja">Begun bhaja</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Koraishutir kochuri is a deep-fried, puffy bread, stuffed with a filling of mildly spiced green peas (or koraishuti!)
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="winter" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/winter/"/>
    
      <category term="kochuri" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kochuri/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Chhola’r Dal</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/cholar-dal/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/cholar-dal/</id>
    <published>2017-11-30T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-01T05:16:30.428Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Savoury-sweet preparation of curried split Bengal gram</p>

<p class="post-intro">Breakfast, lunch, dinner—this is a dal recipe for all occasions.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">E</span>very family has its own the classic Bengali <em>chholar dal</em> recipe. In fact, the Bengali culinary tradition is replete with easy <em>dal</em> recipes for every occasion. This is the <em>niramish</em> or vegetarian version of the Bengali <em>chholar</em> (or <em>chholar</em>) <em>dal</em>, prepared without onions or garlic. <em>Hing</em> (asafoetida) supplies the necessary sharpness that one would generally get from the use of onions. The best part about this warm, mellow, delicious coconut-and-raisin (<em>narkel aar kishmish</em>) strewn <em>chholar dal</em>? It can be served for breakfast, lunch or dinner, with rice, <em>polao</em>, <em>luchi</em>, <em>kochuri</em> or <em>porota</em>! It doesn’t get more versatile than this. Master this Bengali <em>chholar dal recipe</em> and it is sure to become the secret weapon in your culinary arsenal for when you are looking for an impressive, yet quick, easy, Bengali vegetarian <em>dal</em> preparation.</p>
<p>In this video recipe, we show you how to make <em>chholar dal</em> (or <em>chana dal</em>, as it is known in Hindi) that has the perfect balance of sweet and savoury flavours, and the right consistency and texture. Although this preparation is a Bengali classic, other parts of India, and Pakistan and Bangladesh, too, enjoy their own versions of this delicious and nutritious <em>chana dal</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 45 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>calories</strong> 197 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Chhola or chana dal (split Bengal gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Coconut (thinly sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Raisins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Hing (asafoetida)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala">Bengali garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>700 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot | pressure cooker</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Rinse the <em>chhola’r dal</em> well and soak it in water for at least 2 hours. After this time, strain the <em>dal</em> and transfer it to a boiling pot or pressure cooker. Add 700 g water, 6 g salt, and the bay leaves. Boil the <em>dal</em> until it is tender, but the grains are still whole. The texture of this dish will depend a whole lot on how well the <em>dal</em> is boiled. We want each grain of lentil to be perfectly cooked, but not turned to mush. On medium heat, our <em>chhola’r dal</em> cooks to the desired doneness in 2 whistles. The time may vary for you.</li>
<li>Before you begin cooking, make a spice slurry by mixing together the ginger paste, cumin powder, coriander powder, turmeric powder and 50 g water. Also, slice the coconut and slit the green chillies. </li>
<li>Heat mustard oil in a pan (on medium heat) and once it starts to smoke lightly and changes colour to a pale yellow, add the thinly sliced coconut. Fry until the coconut turns golden brown. This should take about a minute. Remove from the oil and set aside. </li>
<li>Temper the same oil with the dried red chillies, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and cumin seeds. Stir in the <em>hing</em>, allowing it to fry for about 10 seconds. </li>
<li>Add the spice slurry we made earlier to the pan. Fry on medium heat until the raw smell of the spices is gone. This should take about 6 minutes. Add the slit green chillies and raisins, and continue frying until you see oil leaving the sides of the spice mixture. </li>
<li>Now add the boiled <em>dal</em> along with the water to the pan. (If you feel there’s a lot of excess water with the <em>dal</em>, reserve some in a bowl.) </li>
<li>Add the remaining salt (12 g) and allow the <em>dal</em> to bubble until it thickens (about 6 to 8 minutes). Depending on how soft or hard your <em>dal</em> is, you may have to adjust the flame and water accordingly. For example, if your <em>dal</em> is still slightly hard, boil on low heat, adding water to maintain consistency, until it is cooked. If it is on the softer, mushier side (first of all, you need to make note of where you went wrong and try correcting the boiling time on your next attempt!), turn up the flame to thicken the dal quickly. </li>
<li>Pick out a softened green chilli from the <em>dal</em>, mash it with the back of a spoon and add it back to the dal. Add the sugar and bubble for about a minute before stirring in the <em>ghee</em>, <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala"><em>Bengali garam masala</em></a>, and fried coconut. Allow the <em>dal</em> to rest, covered, for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/luchi/">Luchi</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/begun-bhaja">Begun bhaja</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/">Bengali fried rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The savoury-sweet cholar dal is a Bengali classic. Bursting with warm, mellow flavours, it is easy to make and insanely delicious.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Momo Soup</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/momo-soup/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/momo-soup/</id>
    <published>2017-11-23T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-24T06:02:20.351Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A clear, comforting, fortifying broth</p>

<p class="post-intro">In many places in India, Nepal or Bhutan, momos are typically accompanied with a bowl of clear, comforting pork, beef or chicken soup.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">O</span>rder a plate of momos anywhere in and around the Himalayan region, and in most cases it is sure to be accompanied with a bowl of hot momo soup. It is a clear broth, comforting—you can even call it fortifying—and always complimentary. The momo soup recipe is the result of trying to use up throwaway items such as animal or bird carcass and bones, vegetable shavings, and so on. </p>
<p>This is a momo soup recipe that can be customised for pork, beef, or chicken bones. Normally, you would serve pork soup with pork momos, beef soup with beef momos, and so on. Here, we show you how you can get a potent and flavourful soup, with tips that will help produce a clear, non-cloudy, broth.</p>
<p>This broth can also be used as stock in the base of other, more elaborate soups, gravies, curries, etc.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 3–5 hours (including 2–4 hours of boiling time)<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 1 litre / 5 cups of broth</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Pork/beef/chicken bones; feet are best</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>350 g</td>
<td>Onions (quartered)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>350 g</td>
<td>Carrots (5-cm chunks)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 pcs</td>
<td>Peppercorns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.8 litres</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 tbsp</td>
<td>Salt (for cleaning bones plus seasoning)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Vinegar (for cleaning bones)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
<li>Strainer | colander</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p>[<em>Note: Follow the steps from the beginning for pork or beef soup. Start from Step 3 for chicken soup.</em>]</p>
<ol>
<li>Sprinkle 1 tbsp of salt over the bones and rub them well. Salt acts as an abrasive, helping clean the bones and remove their sliminess.</li>
<li>Add 1 tsp vinegar, cover the bones with water, and allow them to soak for 30 minutes. After 30 minutes, discard the water and rinse the bones thoroughly.</li>
<li>Transfer the bones to a boiling pot. Fill the pot with hot water and gently simmer for 10 minutes. This will dislodge any impurities present in the bones and they will float to the top. Do not stir or disturb the pot. Simply discard the water, getting rid of all the impurities. This will help get a clear broth later on. </li>
<li>Rinse the bones thoroughly, one last time, and return them to the pot, along with the onions, carrots, bay leaves, peppercorns, and 1.8 litres of water (at room temperature). </li>
<li>Boil on the lowest possible heat for 2–4 hours. Don’t let the broth bubble; it should just simmer very gently. Don’t cover the pot. All these measures will also ensure that you get a clear soup.</li>
<li>Strain the broth and season it with salt. Garnish with spring onions and freshly cracked pepper before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/pork-momo/">Pork momo</a></li>
<li>Beef momo</li>
<li>Chicken momo</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/red-momo-chutney">Momo chutney</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      In many places in India, Nepal or Bhutan, momos are typically accompanied with a bowl of clear, comforting pork, beef or chicken soup.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="chicken" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/chicken/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="soup" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/soup/"/>
    
      <category term="beef" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/beef/"/>
    
      <category term="momo" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/momo/"/>
    
      <category term="pork" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pork/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Momos Chutney</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/momo-chutney/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/momo-chutney/</id>
    <published>2017-11-23T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-24T06:04:16.489Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A red, hot, chilli sauce</p>

<p class="post-intro">A no-cook, easy-to-make, red, hot momo chutney is designed to provide the perfect contrast to the mildly spiced momos.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his is a momo chutney recipe for the hot chilli sauce that is usually served with momos or kotheys. Besides the heat from the dried red chillies, vinegar lends it a slight tang and the garlic provides flavour. Just a dab of this is enough with each bite of the momo—it packs quite a punch.</p>
<p>We love juicy <a href="/recipe/pork-momo">pork momos</a> and beef momos best.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 15 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 35 g chutney</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 g</td>
<td>Vinegar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g (1 large clove)</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Scissors</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Slit open the dried red chillies using a pair of scissors and empty them of their seeds.</li>
<li>Place these deseeded chillies into a bowl and soak them in vinegar for about 2 hours.</li>
<li>Transfer the chillies to a grinder jar, reserving some of the liquid. Add the garlic and salt.</li>
<li>Grind everything together until smooth. Add some or all of the remaining vinegar to adjust consistency and blend again. Store in the refrigerator.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/momo-soup/">Momo soup</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/pork/momo">Momo</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This no-cook, easy-to-make, red, hot momo chutney is designed to provide the perfect contrast to the mildly spiced momos.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="momo" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/momo/"/>
    
      <category term="chutney" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/chutney/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pork Momos</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/pork-momo/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/pork-momo/</id>
    <published>2017-11-16T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-01T01:58:59.095Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Juicy, flavourful pork dumplings!</p>

<p class="post-intro">Calcutta has embraced the momo with an unconditional love Bengalis reserve only for good food.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his pork momo recipe is ideal for chilly winter evenings. Here, we show you how make momos—steamed dumplings that originated possibly in Tibet and are a staple in Nepal, Sikkim, Darjeeling and Bhutan. There is nothing quite like biting into juicy a momo that is bursting with the juices and fat from the meat and vegetables. A good pork momo is a joy to eat. </p>
<p>This recipe for the momo filling calls for some very simple ingredients, the most essential among which is fatty minced pork, containing at least 30 to 50 per cent fat. If you are shopping for pork in Calcutta, just ask for ‘momo pork keema’ at shops such as UP Cold Storage (New Market) or Chaman’s (Beckbagan), and the butchers will be able to give you a mince with the ideal fat to meat ratio! The pork shoulder and pork belly are good cuts for using in momos.</p>
<p>Serve it with a simple hot momo chutney and a bowl of momo soup.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 5 hours (including 3 hours of wait time)<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 48 momos (6 servings)<br><strong>calories</strong> 76 kcal per momo</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>540 g</td>
<td>Fatty minced pork (30–50% fat)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>135 g</td>
<td>Onions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>135 g</td>
<td>Green onions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Pork fat / butter</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Pepper</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>MSG</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Soy sauce</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>48 pcs</td>
<td>Momo wrappers</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 tsp</td>
<td>Oil (for greasing)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Steamer</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Finely chop the onions, green onions, coriander, ginger, and green chillies. In a momo, since all the ingredients are steamed at the same time, cutting the vegetables finely ensures that they all cook together. Besides, you don’t want a large chunk of, say, onion in your momo, rather a little bit of everything in each bite. This step is the most important, so take you time with the chopping.</li>
<li>If using pork fat, hack it to a mince using your knife. If using butter, melt it in a microwave or over the stove.</li>
<li>To a mixing bowl, transfer the minced pork, chopped vegetables, and the fat/butter. To these, add the salt, pepper, MSG, and soy sauce.</li>
<li>Mix thoroughly until everything is well combined. Cover and set it in the refrigerator to chill for at least 4 hours, although it is best if you can do this overnight. This standing time will allow all the flavours to mingle together. Moreover, chilling the pork mix makes the job of filling the momos infinitely easier.</li>
<li>Now make the momo wrappers as shown in this video.</li>
<li>Divide the pork mix into 20 g portions. Place these back in the fridge to chill until you need them. We like to portion our filling on two separate plates, so that one can stay in the fridge until the one you’re currently using gets warm, in which case you can just switch out the plates. That way, you always have a batch of chilled pork.</li>
<li>Take a momo wrapper and place the pork mix at its centre. Apply water all around the edges of the wrapper and start pleating. Use your left hand to form the pleats and keep the filling inside, and right hand to pinch the pleats closed. If you’re just starting out, try resting the momos on the table for easier shaping. Beginners may also use a little less filling to practice with. For a demonstration, watch this video. Make sure that the momos are perfectly sealed and that there are no air pockets within. These might cause the momos to burst while steaming.</li>
<li>Grease the steaming dish with oil and arrange the momos on it. Don’t crowd the steamer. Place it over boiling water and steam for around 12 minutes (±2 minutes). You don’t want to overcook the momos, or they’ll become dry and chewy. </li>
<li>Transfer to a plate immediately and serve with hot <a href="/recipe/momo-soup/">soup</a> and <a href="/recipe/red-momo-chutney">chutney</a>. </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/momo-soup/">Momo soup</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/red-momo-chutney">Momo chutney</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Soft and juicy steamed pork dumplings, momos are a staple in Darjeeling, Sikkim, Nepal and Bhutan.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="momo" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/momo/"/>
    
      <category term="pork" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pork/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to make momo wrappers</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/momo-wrapper/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/momo-wrapper/</id>
    <published>2017-11-16T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-11-24T00:37:16.364Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">An easy, step-by step guide</p>

<p class="post-intro">The perfect, percise how-to video for momo or dumpling wrappers at home from scratch.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">M</span>aking momo wrappers from scratch is very easy, not least because the momo dough requires only four ingredients, including water! The trick is to make a stiff dough, knead it extremely well, and rest it in a plastic bag. The dough then becomes smooth and ready to be portioned and filled with a momo filling of your choice. In this recipe for the momo dough, we take you through the steps of kneading and rolling out the wrappers to the perfect diameter and thickness. Since the edges of a momo are crimped together, we need to ensure that the sides of the wrapper are thin so that they cook at the same time as the rest of the momo. The rolling method shown in this video is a traditional one, which ensures that your momo covering turns out soft and perfectly cooked no matter what you fill it with!</p>
<p>We love juicy <a href="/recipe/pork-momo">pork momos</a> and beef momos best.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 2 hours (including 1 hour of standing time)<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 50 wrappers<br><strong>calories</strong> 30 kcal per wrapper</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Maida (all-purpose flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Baking powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>A cylindrical rolling pin (not spindle-shaped), preferably thin.</li>
<li>Plastic / Ziploc bag</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>In a bowl, combine the flour, salt, baking powder and warm water until they more-or-less come together, after which transfer everything to a clean surface and start kneading. The dough might seem dry at first, but keep kneading continuously for about 10 minutes and it’ll start getting wetter. At this point, the dough will still appear stiff and rough. That’s okay.</li>
<li>Place the dough inside a large plastic bag or a Ziploc bag and allow it to rest for at least 60 minutes. </li>
<li>After 60 minutes, knead the dough for about 5 seconds and you will notice that it is considerably smoother now.</li>
<li>Work in sections and reserve the ones you’re not using in a plastic bag so that they don’t dry out. Divide the dough in 12 g portions. Roll each portion using your palms into a disc. Keep these discs covered with the plastic bag until you need them. </li>
<li>Roll out into wrappers about 9 cm in diameter as shown in <a href="&#39;https://youtu.be/hVRRaYjjUis?t=4m1s&#39;">this video</a>. </li>
<li>Dust with flour so that the wrappers don’t stick. </li>
<li>Fill them with a momo filling of your choice.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/momo-soup/">Momo soup</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/red-momo-chutney">Momo chutney</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The perfect, percise how-to video for momo or dumpling wrappers at home from scratch.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
      <category term="momo" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/momo/"/>
    
      <category term="kitchen-hacks" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kitchen-hacks/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to make paneer (chhana) at home</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/how-to/make-paneer/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/how-to/make-paneer/</id>
    <published>2017-10-27T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-27T03:18:20.736Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Fresh, Indian cottage cheese</p>

<p class="post-intro">Paneer might be widely popular all over India, but its close cousin <em>chhana</em> is the ultimate conqueror of the world of Bengali sweets.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">P</span>aneer is one of the most neutral ingredients in Indian cooking, which makes it ideal for use in a wide array of curries. A good paneer must be well formed and not crumbly. Its structure shouldn’t be too tight, otherwise it will become tough and not absorb any curry. </p>
<p>While paneer is especially adored among aficionados of some branches of north Indian cuisine in particular—it is the vegetarian’s delight—its close cousin <em>chhana</em> (or <em>chhena</em>) holds a special place in Bengali cooking. From being the base for all manner of Bengali sweets (<em>sondesh</em>, <em>roshogolla</em>, anyone?), it is also used to make <em>chhana’r torkari</em>, a curry with mildly spiced <em>chhana koftas</em>, which is a beloved delicacy.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 300 g paneer (6 people)</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1.5 kg</td>
<td>Whole milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>White vinegar or lime juice</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
<li>Wooden spoon</li>
<li>Large bowl</li>
<li>Strainer</li>
<li>Muslin | cheesecloth</li>
<li>Sharp knife</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>In a saucepan, bring the milk to a boil. Turn off the heat and add vinegar/lime juice.</li>
<li>Stir until you notice the ‘curds’ separating from the ‘whey’ (a translucent liquid). </li>
<li>Place a strainer over your mixing bowl, and the cheesecloth over the strainer. Pour the contents of your saucepan over this contraption. By doing so you are collecting the curds in the cheesecloth and allowing the whey to drain into the bowl below. </li>
<li>Gather the edges of the cheesecloth and lift the paneer in a bundle. Using your palm, gently mould the sides and top of the sack so as to close any gaping holes or cracks.</li>
<li>Hang it over your sink and allow the remaining water in the paneer to drip naturally (for about 30 minutes). Do not squeeze or put any weight on it. Trying to force the water out or compress it too much will compact the paneer, closing all its pores and not allowing it to absorb the curry later on. </li>
<li>If you need <em>chhana</em>, you can now unwrap the bundle and proceed to crumble/mash it according to your recipe. But if you’re going for paneer, after 30 minutes of hanging, place the bundle in the refrigerator and chill it for at least an hour. This will harden the fat in the curds and allow for the cutting of sharp, clean cubes. It also helps to warm the blade of your knife in a glass of hot water. When cutting the paneer into cubes, slide your knife instead of pressing it down. This will give you perfect, clean cuts. Divide the paneer in cubes as specified by your recipe.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Recipes-that-use-paneer"><a href="#Recipes-that-use-paneer" class="headerlink" title="Recipes that use paneer"></a>Recipes that use paneer</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/paneer-dalna/">Paneer’er dalna</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Paneer is one of the most neutral ingredients in Indian cooking, which makes it ideal for use in a wide array of curries.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="how to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/how-to/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
      <category term="paneer" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/paneer/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mutton Kosha | Kosha Mangsho</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/mutton-kosha/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/mutton-kosha/</id>
    <published>2017-10-18T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-27T03:15:46.904Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Slow-cooked, rich, Bengali mutton curry</p>

<p class="post-intro">There are no special ingredients to making a good mutton <em>kosha</em>. All it takes is patience.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">M</span>utton <em>kosha</em> is an iconic Bengali delicacy. The word <em>kosha</em> is similar in meaning to <em>bhuna</em>, which involves slowly cooking a gravy over low flame for a very long time to get a rich, dark-brown gravy and melt-in-the-mouth mutton pieces. It is worth pointing out that in Bengal, as well as in India, mutton is commonly used to refer to goat’s meat. Mutton <em>kosha</em> (or <em>kosha mangsho</em>) can be served with <em>porota</em> or <em>polao</em>. It tastes great even with plain rice. One of the most famous shops selling this style of mutton <em>kosha</em> is Golbari at the Shyambazar crossing in Calcutta. While we are not certain that our version is exactly like Golbari’s, we can assure you it certainly tastes very good.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1.5 to 2 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>calories</strong> 560 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Mutton</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE MARINADE</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Onion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Shahi garam masala powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE CURRY</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 cm</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 pcs</td>
<td>Green cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Black cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Onions (sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Green chillies (plus 4 extra pieces for garnish)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150–200 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt (based on how tart you want your curry)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~1 litre</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Mortar and pestle</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan with lid</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>For the marinade, add 100 g quartered onions, 5 g roughly chopped garlic, 100 g yoghurt, 15 g salt, turmeric, and shahi garam masala to a grinder jar. Blitz to form a smooth paste. </li>
<li>Coat all the mutton pieces with the marinade, making sure to get into all the nooks and crannies of the meat. Cover and allow the mutton to marinate in the refrigerator for about 8 hours. </li>
<li>Coming to the prep: Cut 400 g onions into thin slices. For this recipe, sliced onions define the texture of the curry. Diced, chopped, or puréed onions won’t give you the same result. Using a mortar and pestle, crush together 10 g garlic and 20 g green chillies to a paste. For ease while stirring later on, you may also cut all the bay leaves in 3-cm sections using a pair of scissors.</li>
<li>Heat a large <em>kadai</em> and add mustard oil to it. Once the oil has started to smoke lightly and changed colour to a pale yellow, add the dried red chillies, bay leaves, cinnamon, green cardamom, black cardamom, and cloves. </li>
<li>Add the onions and fry them on medium flame for about 15 minutes until they are light brown in colour. Then, add the ginger paste, and garlic and green chilli paste, and fry for another 5 minutes. Keep the flame medium to low, depending on whether your onions are sticking to the pan or not, and stir often. We want to fry the spices as well as develop colour on the onions. Next, add the dry spices (coriander, cumin, and red chilli) mixed with 100 g of water. Continue frying the onions along with the spices for about 15 more minutes. By now (it’s been 30 minutes since we started), your onions should have taken on a reddish-brown colour and the spices started releasing their oils. </li>
<li>Add the marinated mutton to the pan. The mutton has been in the fridge, so it is cold. Raise the heat and mix everything thoroughly. Fry the mutton, stirring frequently to check that it’s not sticking to the pan, for 15 minutes on high heat. Beat 150–200 g yoghurt until it is lump-free and add it to the pan. Also add 8 g salt and 10 g sugar at this point. Mix everything and keep frying. Once the moisture (from the cold mutton and yoghurt) starts to dry out, drop the heat to medium.</li>
<li>There’s not much to it now. On medium heat, for the next 75 to 90 minutes,  repeat the following steps:<br>–Add a splash of <em>hot</em> water to the pan (~30 ml at a time)<br>–Stir it in<br>–Cover the pan and cook for a minute<br>–Uncover and stir everything thoroughly <br><br><em>What we’re doing here is a kind of controlled browning. Stir, scrape, and incorporate any of the browned bits that may have stuck to the bottom of the pan, as that is what will allow the mutton to develop a rich colour. However, be alert so that the gravy doesn’t burn and turn bitter. Keep adding water a little at a time and cooking the meat in the gravy.</em></li>
<li>Once you are happy with the colour, add as much water as you’d like for the gravy/curry. Also add about 4 slit green chillies for flavour. Cover and cook until the mutton is tender. You should be able to tear it apart with two fingers.</li>
<li>Turn off the heat and top off with a little bit of ghee. Cover and let it rest for about 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li>Polao</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/">Fried rice</a></li>
<li>Porota</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/luchi/">Luchi</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Mutton kosha—meat slowly cooked in gravy over low heat—is characterised by a rich brown gravy and melt-in-the-mouth mutton pieces.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="mutton" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mutton/"/>
    
      <category term="kosha" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kosha/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Paneer’er Dalna</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/paneer-dalna/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/paneer-dalna/</id>
    <published>2017-10-13T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-13T02:11:53.476Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Bengali cottage-cheese curry</p>

<p class="post-intro">Understated, warm paneer curry with flavours of ginger, ghee and garam masala. Rich and comforting without being flashy.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">P</span>aneer is a late entrant to the Bengali food scene; Bengal is more fond of its <em>chhana</em> (<em>chhena</em>). <em>Paneer’er dalna</em> (Bengali paneer curry with potatoes and peas) is infused with the flavours of ginger, cumin, garam masala and ghee. This recipe also uses capsicum, which imparts a lovely peppery aroma to the dish. Here, fresh cubes of homemade paneer are shallow-fried and then added to the curry and cooked until they are soft and juicy. This is a very quick paneer recipe, that is prepared using no onion or garlic and is served with rice and dal, or with a light vegetable polao or luchi.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 45 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 307 kcal per portion</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Paneer (3-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for frying paneer)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (3-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Peas (blanched)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Capsicum (2-cm squares)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Garam masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>11 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
<li><em>Jhuri</em> | colander</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Divide the paneer into 3-cm cubes and smear it with ¼ tsp each of salt and turmeric. Heat a flat frying pan on medium heat. Once the pan is completely hot, add a millimetre of oil. Wait until the oil heats up fully and then place the paneer cubes in it in a single layer. Ensuring that the pan and oil are both hot will prevent the paneer from sticking to the pan. After about 45 seconds, flip the cubes and fry their opposite surfaces until they are golden. Fry just two of the surfaces, as frying all round will make the paneer rubbery and won’t allow absorption of curry later on. Remove from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Peel and chop potatoes in 3-cm cubes. Cut the capsicum in 2-cm squares.</li>
<li>Heat 15 g mustard oil in a <em>kadai</em> until it starts smoking and changes colour to a pale yellow. Temper the oil with dried red chillies, bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and cumin seeds.</li>
<li>Once the whole spices start crackling, add the potatoes. Cover and fry them on medium heat until the turn slightly golden (about 4 minutes).</li>
<li>Meanwhile, make a paste with ginger, cumin powder, kashmiri red chilli powder, turmeric powder, and 100 g water. Add it to the pan and cook it along with the potatoes until the smell of raw spices is gone. This should take about 6 minutes. If you find that the spices have dried out, add a splash of hot water and continue frying.</li>
<li>Add capsicum and 3 slit green chillies. Cover and cook for about 3 minutes until the capsicum softens.</li>
<li>Whip the yoghurt until it is lump-free. <em>Lower</em> the heat and add it to the pan. Stir quickly prevent the yoghurt from splitting. Cook <em>uncovered</em> for 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Add the blanched peas (if you’re using raw peas, add them along with the potatoes earlier on) and sugar, and cook for 2 more minutes. </li>
<li>Now add 250 g hot water to the pan. This will form the curry. Once it comes to a boil, drop the chunks of fried paneer in it. Bubble on medium heat for about 6 minutes until the curry thickens.</li>
<li>Garnish with <em>garam masala</em>, <em>ghee</em>, and a slit green chilli. Cover the pan and rest it for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/">Fried rice</a></li>
<li>Polao</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/luchi/">Luchi</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Understated, warm paneer curry with flavours of ginger, ghee and garam masala. Rich and comforting without being flashy.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="dalna" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dalna/"/>
    
      <category term="paneer" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/paneer/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ghugni</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/ghugni/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/ghugni/</id>
    <published>2017-10-05T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-06T06:36:56.815Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Spicy, curried snack made with yellow peas</p>

<p class="post-intro">Ghugni is an iconic vegetarian Bengali snack made with dried yellow peas and served with luchi or pauruti</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">G</span>hugni is one of the most beloved of Bengali snacks. It is a dish of curried whole-yellow peas or motor (matar) dal. A good ghugni is one in which the motor dal is well-cooked, but remains whole. The key is to not overboil the dal. The consistency also needs be just right—slurpy but never watery. With just about 180 kcal per serving, you’d be hard-pressed to find an evening snack more filling, healthy <em>and</em> delicious than this. </p>
<p></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6-8 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Motor dal (whole yellow peas)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (1.5 cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Coconut (thinly sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes (diced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Onions (thinly sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>FOR THE GARNISH</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/gGmCPwauVBs" target="_blank" rel="external">Bhaja masala</a></li>
<li>Chopped onions</li>
<li>Chopped green chillies</li>
<li>Tamarind pulp</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
<li><em>Jhuri</em> | colander</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Rinse and soak the dal in water overnight (at least 12 hours). Drain it from the water and transfer it to a saucepan.</li>
<li>Add 800 g water, 10 g salt, and 20 g onions to the the saucepan. Cover and boil the dal on low heat. The dal should be soft but remain unbroken. So be sure to keep an eye on it so that it doesn’t disintegrate. Once done, strain the dal and reserve the water for later. </li>
<li>Cut potatoes into 1.5-cm cubes, onions and coconut into thin slices, and roughly chop the tomato. Also crush the garlic and green chillies into a paste using a mortar and pestle.</li>
<li>Set a pan on medium heat and add 15 g mustard oil with 5 g ghee. Once hot, add the coconut slices and fry them until they are golden-brown. Remove them from the oil and set aside. Temper the oil with dried red chillies, bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and cumin seeds. </li>
<li>Once the whole spices are crackling, add the onions and fry them until brown. This should take about 6 minutes. Next add the potatoes and fry for 3 minutes before adding the tomatoes. Cook the tomatoes until they are soft (about 2 minutes).</li>
<li>Add the garlic-and-green-chilli paste, and ginger paste. Fry these for about 3 minutes. During this time, make a paste of turmeric powder, coriander powder, cumin powder, kashmiri red chilli powder, and 100 g water. Add it to the pan.</li>
<li>Fry until the smell of raw spices is gone. This should take about 8 to 10 minutes. If the spices dry out, add a splash of the dal water that we reserved earlier and continue frying.</li>
<li>Once the spices have started releasing their oils, add the boiled <em>motor</em> dal to the pan. Fold it with the spices and cook for 2 minutes before add the reserved water. </li>
<li>Add the remaining salt and sugar and turn up the heat. Bubble on high flame for about 6 minutes until the curry loses its watery consistency. Stir in two slit green chillies and the fried coconut. Cover and rest for 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Before serving, garnish with <a href="https://youtu.be/gGmCPwauVBs" target="_blank" rel="external"><em>Bhaja masala</em></a>, chopped onions, chopped green chillies and tamarind pulp. Serve piping hot.  </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>White quarter pound bread loaves toasted over an open flame</li>
<li>Luchi</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Ghugni is an iconic vegetarian Bengali snack made with dried yellow peas and served with luchi or pauruti
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bengali Fried Rice</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/</id>
    <published>2017-09-22T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-06T06:30:19.082Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Rice and crunchy veggies with a Bengali twist</p>

<p class="post-intro">Easy-to-cook and nutritious, this fried rice is loaded with the goodness of fresh, seasonal veggies.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">V</span>egetable <em>pulao</em>, often called ‘vegetable fried rice’, is an easy-to-cook, nutritious recipe. It is a common item on Bengali wedding menus and is often served with fish fry, mutton <em>kosha</em>, or fish <em>kaliya</em>. This fried rice can easily be modified to include seasonal vegetables aside from the peas, beans, and carrots we’ve used here. Long-grained, fragrant Basmati rice is ideal for this preparation. The mark of a good fried rice is long unbroken grains of rice and vibrant, crunchy veggies. In this recipe, we show you techniques to help the vegetable retain their colour and crunch as well as prevent the breakage of cooked rice while mixing. </p>
<p></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Basmati rice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Carrots</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Beans</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Peas</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 stick</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Cashew nuts</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Raisins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Peppercorns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>26 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
<li><em>Jhuri</em> | colander</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and boil the rice in a pot full of water until it is 90 per cent tender. Drain the water and spread the rice over a colander so that it doesn’t cook any further.</li>
<li>Dice the carrots in 1-cm cubes. Chop the beans on the bias (in 1-cm sections) for a nice trapezoid shape. Shell the peas. Slit the green chillies.</li>
<li>Freshly grind the peppercorns so that you have about ½ tsp pepper. Mix it with the garam masala powder, salt, and sugar. Combining the spices and seasoning before adding them to the rice will ensure even distribution.</li>
<li>Set a pan on medium heat and add vegetable oil and ghee to it. Once hot, temper the oil with the bay leaves, cinnamon, cardamom, cloves, and about five peppercorns.</li>
<li>Add the cashewnuts and fry them until they are lightly coloured. We don’t want them completely golden at this stage as they will fry throughout the cooking process.</li>
<li>Turn up the heat and add the carrots. Stir-fry them for 2 minutes before adding the beans. Fry the beans for 2 minutes and then add the peas and raisins. Keeping the heat high ensures that the veggies retain their vibrant colours and don’t lose crunch.</li>
<li>Turn off the heat and layer half the cooked rice over the vegetables. Sprinkle half the premixed seasoning. Top off with the remaining rice and seasoning. Also add the green chillies.</li>
<li>To mix the rice thoroughly while ensuring minimal breakage of the grains, use the fold and rotate motion as shown in the video. Do this until everything is well combined.  </li>
<li>Cover the pan and set it over the lowest heat setting for about 20 minutes and steam until the rice has cooked completely. Check once or twice to see that the rice isn’t sticking to the bottom of the pan. Rest for at least 10 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/dimer-dalna/">Dim’er kosha</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/chicken-curry/">Chicken kosha</a></li>
<li>Alu’r dom</li>
<li>Paneer’er dalna</li>
<li>Chilli chicken</li>
<li>Salad</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Bengali fried rice, easy-to-cook and nutritious, is common on wedding menus and loaded with the goodness of fresh, seasonal veggies.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="rice" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rice/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kamranga Nimki or Elo-Jhelo</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/nimki/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/nimki/</id>
    <published>2017-09-14T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-15T04:34:12.732Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A crisp, savoury, dainty tea-time snack</p>

<p class="post-intro">A Bijoya Doshomi essential, but also a great thing to have in your cupboard all year round.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span><em>amranga</em> or <em>elo-jhelo nimki</em> is a Bijoya staple in most Bengali households. It takes its whimsical name from its twisty-lacy structure. Also known as <em>kamranga nimki</em> after the shape of the fruit by the same name, this deep-fried shortcrust pastry is characterised by its elegant spindle shape. A perfect nimki is not chewy but crisp. It breaks with a satisfying snap. In this recipe, we show you how to achieve <em>nimki</em> of the desired shape, colour, texture, and of course, flavour.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 90 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 16 pieces</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>a pinch</td>
<td>Baking soda</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Jowan (carom seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25–30 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Lime juice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 250 g</td>
<td>Oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Jhhanjhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
<li><em>Jhuri</em> | colander | cooling rack</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Take flour, salt, sugar, baking soda, <em>jowan</em>, and <em>ghee</em> in a large bowl and mix together thoroughly. Like any shortcrust pastry, we need to distribute the fat (<em>ghee</em> in this case) well within the flour before we add the liquid. So, take your time and rub the flour between your fingers until it resembles bread crumbs in texture. </li>
<li>Now add water and lime juice, and bring everything together. For the <em>nimki</em> to be crisp and flaky we must ensure as little gluten-formation as possible. So, don’t overknead the dough.</li>
<li>Cover the dough and let it rest for about 30 minutes. After this time, divide it into little portions of 20 g each. Flatten by rolling it between your palms. Do this for all the dough balls and keep them covered so that they don’t dry out. </li>
<li>Roll each disc into a thin, round pastry with a diameter of 10 cm. </li>
<li>Using a knife, cut parallel lines inside the rolled circle, 7 mm apart, leaving the edges intact. WATCH the video for a clearer picture. Apply a little water on the two edges perpendicular to the direction of the cuts. Carefully lift the pastry and pleat the dampened edges. Pinch each side to secure all the pleats together. You should now have a spindle-shaped, lacy pastry. Repeat this for the remaining dough.</li>
<li>Heat oil (about 3 cm deep) in a frying pan to 150°C. The oil should not be too hot otherwise the pastry will remain chewy inside, whereas we want it to be crisp and have a nice snap. Lower the <em>nimkis</em> in the oil one by one. Do not overcrowd the pan. Turn over every 45 seconds and fry each batch for about 8 to 10 minutes until the <em>nimkis</em> take on a  rich, golden colour. Remove them from the oil and transfer to a basket or cooling rack.</li>
<li>Cool completely before storing them in an airtight jar, in which they should keep well for up to a month.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/doodh-cha/">Tea (Doodh Cha)</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Nimki (from ‘namkeem’ or savoury) is an elegant, golden, deep-fried, shortcrust pastry that’s perfect with a cup of hot milky tea.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="bijoya" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bijoya/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Calcutta Egg Rolls</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/kolkata-egg-roll/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/kolkata-egg-roll/</id>
    <published>2017-09-01T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-10-06T06:43:05.730Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Calcutta’s most popular and iconic street food</p>

<p class="post-intro">Of all the rolls, wraps, and frankies we have had, nothing comes close to a Calcutta roll—neither in taste, nor in sound architecture.</p>

<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he egg roll is certainly Calcutta’s most recognizable and popular street food. But what makes a good roll? It should be served hot. So the assembly process, once the <em>paratha</em> has been fried,  needs to be quick and efficient. The outer shell, the <em>paratha</em> itself, must be flaky yet soft. It should not be too chewy, that is to say, you should not have to tug at it with your teeth. Most importantly, the <em>paratha</em> should be fully cooked and crisp. The filling should be evenly distributed so you get a little of everything with each bite. Finally, the mark of an excellently wrapped roll is that you can eat it using just one hand. Simply bite into your roll and when you reach the paper, gently grip the roll with your teeth to slide it out as you go along. No overflowing filling, no leaking sauces. Everything is contained within a neat package that you can enjoy on the go.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 530 kcal per paratha</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE WRAP</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Dalda (shortening)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>180–200 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE FILLING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Eggs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Onions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 large</td>
<td>Lime</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1–2 tsp</td>
<td>Chaat masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1–2 tsp</td>
<td>Rocksalt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>80 g</td>
<td>Tomato ketchup</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cucumber (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 75 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
<li>Flat frying pan | skillet</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Sheets of thin, absorbent paper</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>For the outer <em>paratha</em>/wrap, add the flour, salt, sugar, and <em>dalda</em> to a mixing bowl. Combine the ingredients until the fat is well dispersed in the flour. Take your time and rub the flour between your fingers until it resembles breadcrumbs in texture. This will lead to a flakier crust.</li>
<li>Now add the warm water and knead the dough for about 5 minutes until it is soft and smooth. Coat it with oil, cover the bowl, and allow it to rest for 30 minutes.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, mix together finely sliced onions, chopped green chillies and the juice of half a lime. Pickling the onions in lime juice reduces their sharpness. If using cucumber, peel it and remove the central seeds. Then chop them into thin matchsticks. Create an assembly station where you gather all the items required for the filling. This will allow you to easily put together the roll once the <em>paratha</em> is off the stove.</li>
<li>Back to the dough: once it has rested, divide it in 130 g portions. For an extra-flaky exterior, we will roll the dough in the <em>lachcha paratha</em> style, incorporating layers of flour and oil. To do this, form a ball and roll it out to a disc about 12 cm large. Apply a thin layer of oil on the surface and sprinkle some dry flour. Make an incision on the disc along a radius and roll it in the shape of a cone [WATCH THE VIDEO]. Press down to flatten. Rest the dough for about 5 minutes to relax it again, after which roll it for a second time to disc 22 cm in diameter.</li>
<li>Beat an egg with a pinch of salt and keep at the ready.</li>
<li>Heat about 4 tsp oil (12 g) in a flat frying pan or skillet. Add the <em>paratha</em> and fry it on both sides until golden. Rotate the <em>paratha</em> continuously, flipping often, for a uniform crust. Pay special attention to the sides to ensure that they crisp too. Once the <em>paratha</em> is completely cooked, spread the beaten egg over it. Before it settles, turn over to fry the side with the egg. Transfer it to the assembly station, with the egg side facing up.</li>
<li>Sprinkle it with <em>chaat masala</em> and rocksalt. Add a row of the pickled onions a little off the centre of the <em>paratha</em>. Squeeze some lime juice over it. Top it with cucumber if you like. One of our favourite variations of the egg roll is the egg-potato roll. If we have it on hand, we like to add some leftover spicy <em>alu’r torkari</em> as well. Finish everything off with a few squirts of ketchup.</li>
<li>Form a tight roll, making sure the filling is all enclosed within the <em>paratha</em>. Wrap a paper around two-thirds of the roll and tuck any excess at the bottom.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Green chillies</li>
<li>Lime wedges</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thums_Up" target="_blank" rel="external">Thums up</a>!</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The iconic Calcutta egg roll, ladies and gents! Nothing else will do.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Shami Kabab</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/shami-kabab/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/shami-kabab/</id>
    <published>2017-08-24T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-25T02:51:37.452Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Pan-fried, delicately spiced, ground-meat <em>kababs</em></p>

<p class="post-intro">If you are just getting into the wonderful world of <em>kabab</em>-making, these are the easiest ones to start with.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">S</span><em>hami kabab</em> is well loved not least because it is one of the easier <em>kababs</em> to make. While producing good <em>kababs</em> generally requires special grilling, charring or <em>tandoori</em> techniques, <em>shami kabab</em> can be easily prepared at home with no special equipment. Popular on the Indian subcontinent, this snack resembles a pan-fried, ground-meat patty. It is best made with a lean, boneless red meat of your choice (mutton, beef, lamb, etc.). It is important that the meat has a low fat but high muscle content. Fat within the meat tends to melt the kabab when it is fried, while we want it to hold itself together. More muscle and fibre, on the other hand, will ensure that the meat has some texture when it is ground, providing a satisfying resistance with each bite. The use of <em>chhola’r dal</em> (split Bengal gram) adds nuttiness. Besides that, the other flavours come from chopped mint leaves, green chillies, <em>garam masala</em>, and ghee. We use a beaten egg to bind everything together. Depending on the recipe, such kababs may sometimes be coated in eggs or bread crumbs before they are fried. We, however, fry them directly so that the meat itself forms a rich, brown, caramelised crust.  </p>
<p></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 2 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 16–17 kababs</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Boneless mutton or beef (lean)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Chhola’r dal (split Bengal gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Onions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Mint leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Raisins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Lime juice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td><a href="recipe/shahi-garam-masala/">Shahi garam masala</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Beaten egg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 200 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (1-cm deep, for frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
<li>Flat frying pan | skillet</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
<li><em>Jhuri</em> | draining rack | colander </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and soak <em>chhola’r dal</em> overnight. Drain the water in the morning.</li>
<li>In a boiling pot, add the boneless meat cut into 3-cm cubes, soaked <em>dal</em>, roughly chopped onions, ginger and garlic, bay leaves, dried red chillies, and salt. Add about 400 g water and set the pot to boil. For this dish, the meat needs to be absolutely tender, but remain dry. It’s best, therefore, to add water a little at a time and keep an eye on the pot so that the bottom doesn’t catch, and yet there’s no extra water. Once the meat has cooked (this should take about 60 to 90 minutes depending on the meat and your location), on high heat dry off any excess water. </li>
<li>Pick out the bay leaves from the pot and discard them.</li>
<li>Transfer the mixture to a grinder jar and grind it on the lowest setting until it is uniform. You may need to scrape the sides of your jar a couple of times. Remember that a good <em>shami kabab</em> has texture. Your grind should not be too smooth or pasty. Rather, the meat fibres should still be visible.</li>
<li>Transfer this ground mixture to a mixing bowl. Add chopped green chillies, chopped mint leaves, raisins, lime juice, <em>shahi garam masala</em> powder, ghee, and a beaten egg. Mix everything together thoroughly by hand.</li>
<li>Portion the mixture into balls weighing 60 g each. Apply some ghee on your palms so the mixture doesn’t stick to them and form discs 6 cm in diameter, making sure to patch up as many cracks as you can. This will prevent breakage while frying.</li>
<li>On medium flame, heat your flat frying pan or skillet. Once hot, add vegetable oil, about 1 cm deep. For a good crust, its level should reach half the height of the <em>kabab</em>. Once the oil is about 180°C, gently lower the <em>kababs</em> one by one. Do not crowd the pan; fry no more than 4 to 5 <em>kababs</em> at a time.</li>
<li>Fry each side for about 2 minutes until they are brown. Drain from the oil on to a perforated vessel to keep them crisp. </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Coriander and coconut chutney</li>
<li>Mint and yoghurt chutney</li>
<li>Tomato ketchup</li>
<li>Salad (onions, cucumber and tomatoes)</li>
<li>Slider buns</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A mellow spiced easy pan fried kabab made from ground beef, mutton, or lamb and popular in India, Bangladesh and Pakistan.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="beef" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/beef/"/>
    
      <category term="mutton" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mutton/"/>
    
      <category term="kabab" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kabab/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Churmur</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/churmur/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/churmur/</id>
    <published>2017-08-17T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-25T02:38:31.013Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">What you get when you deconstruct your <em>phuchka</em></p>

<p class="post-intro">This Calcutta street snack combines myriads of flavours and textures into a tangy-savoury-mushy-crunchy explosion in your mouth.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">C</span>hurmur is a type of <em>chaat</em> and one of the more inspired offerings to come out of a <em>phuchkawala</em>’s cart. It contains the usual suspects—potatoes, boiled <em>motor dal</em>, tamarind, green chillies, coriander, and a variety of spices and seasoning—all mixed together and heaped upon a <em>shalpata</em> plate. From its onomatopoeic name that recalls the sound (‘<em>chur-mur</em>’) a crisp <em>papri</em> makes when crushed to its vibrant amalgamation of flavours and textures, there’s nothing about this dish that is not delightful. When you are not ready to leave your <em>phuchka</em> stall yet, but must, it is <em>churmur</em>—<em>puchka</em> deconstructed—that you can take home with you in a paper bag. </p>
<p>In this video we should you how to reproduce this astoundingly addictive <em>chaat</em> at home.</p>
<p></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 2 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Potatoes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>60 g</td>
<td>Phuchka papri</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Chhola (whole Bengal gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Motor dal (whole yellow peas)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Tamarind</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 tsp</td>
<td>Lime juice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Rocksalt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td><a href="https://youtu.be/gGmCPwauVBs" target="_blank" rel="external">Bhaja masala</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Chilli flakes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pressure cooker | boiling pot</li>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak the <em>chhola</em> and <em>motor dal</em> for about 12 hours. Wash them after that. Drain the <em>chhola</em> and set it aside. Boil the <em>motor dal</em> until it softens but remains whole (it should not disintegrate). Drain the <em>motor dal</em> and leave it to cool.</li>
<li>Boil the potatoes till they are tender. Peel and dice into 1-cm cubes, and transfer them to a mixing bowl.</li>
<li>While the potatoes are boiling, add 75 g hot water to the tamarind and allow it to soak for 15 minutes. This will soften the tamarind and ensure easy extraction of the pulp. Work the tamarind between your fingers to separate the skin and seeds. Press to squeeze out all the juice and discard the seeds. You should be left with some smooth tamarind pulp.</li>
<li>At this point, also roughly crush the green chillies using a mortar and pestle, chop coriander leaves, and slice the lime.</li>
<li>Back to the mixing bowl with the diced potatoes: add soaked <em>chhola</em>, boiled <em>motor dal</em>, chopped coriander, crushed green chillies, lime juice, tamarind pulp, salt, rocksalt, chilli flakes and <em>bhaja masala</em>. Crush the _papri_s and add them too.</li>
<li>Mix until everything is evenly combined. Use a light hand so that you don’t mash the potatoes or grind the <em>papri</em> to a fine powder—we want them to remain chunky. Serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This crispy, tangy, savoury &#39;chaat&#39; is a popular Calcutta street food dished out by phuchkawalas and is super easy to make.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
