<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Bong Eats | Bengali Recipe Videos</title>
  <subtitle>Bong Eats is about food from Bengal. And that&#39;s not just Bengali food.</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://bongeats.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-15T04:34:12.732Z</updated>
  <id>https://bongeats.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Bong Eats</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kamranga Nimki or Elo-Jhelo</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/nimki/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/nimki/</id>
    <published>2017-09-14T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-15T04:34:12.732Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A crisp, savoury, dainty tea-time snack</p>

<p class="post-intro">A Bijoya Doshomi essential, but also a great thing to have in your cupboard all year round.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span><em>amranga</em> or <em>elo-jhelo nimki</em> is a Bijoya staple in most Bengali households. It takes its whimsical name from its twisty-lacy structure. Also known as <em>kamranga nimki</em> after the shape of the fruit by the same name, this deep-fried shortcrust pastry is characterised by its elegant spindle shape. A perfect nimki is not chewy but crisp. It breaks with a satisfying snap. In this recipe, we show you how to achieve <em>nimki</em> of the desired shape, colour, texture, and of course, flavour.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 90 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 16 pieces</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>a pinch</td>
<td>Baking soda</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Jowan (carom seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25–30 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Lime juice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 250 g</td>
<td>Oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Jhhanjhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
<li><em>Jhuri</em> | colander | cooling rack</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Take flour, salt, sugar, baking soda, <em>jowan</em>, and <em>ghee</em> in a large bowl and mix together thoroughly. Like any shortcrust pastry, we need to distribute the fat (<em>ghee</em> in this case) well within the flour before we add the liquid. So, take your time and rub the flour between your fingers until it resembles bread crumbs in texture. </li>
<li>Now add water and lime juice, and bring everything together. For the <em>nimki</em> to be crisp and flaky we must ensure as little gluten-formation as possible. So, don’t overknead the dough.</li>
<li>Cover the dough and let it rest for about 30 minutes. After this time, divide it into little portions of 20 g each. Flatten by rolling it between your palms. Do this for all the dough balls and keep them covered so that they don’t dry out. </li>
<li>Roll each disc into a thin, round pastry with a diameter of 10 cm. </li>
<li>Using a knife, cut parallel lines inside the rolled circle, 7 mm apart, leaving the edges intact. WATCH the video for a clearer picture. Apply a little water on the two edges perpendicular to the direction of the cuts. Carefully lift the pastry and pleat the dampened edges. Pinch each side to secure all the pleats together. You should now have a spindle-shaped, lacy pastry. Repeat this for the remaining dough.</li>
<li>Heat oil (about 3 cm deep) in a frying pan to 150°C. The oil should not be too hot otherwise the pastry will remain chewy inside, whereas we want it to be crisp and have a nice snap. Lower the <em>nimkis</em> in the oil one by one. Do not overcrowd the pan. Turn over every 45 seconds and fry each batch for about 8 to 10 minutes until the <em>nimkis</em> take on a  rich, golden colour. Remove them from the oil and transfer to a basket or cooling rack.</li>
<li>Cool completely before storing them in an airtight jar, in which they should keep well for up to a month.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/doodh-cha/">Tea (Doodh Cha)</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Nimki (from ‘namkeem’ or savoury) is an elegant, golden, deep-fried, shortcrust pastry that’s perfect with a cup of hot milky tea.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="bijoya" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bijoya/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Calcutta Egg Rolls</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/kolkata-egg-roll/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/kolkata-egg-roll/</id>
    <published>2017-09-01T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-01T03:39:37.751Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Calcutta’s most popular and iconic street food</p>

<p class="post-intro">Of all the rolls, wraps, and frankies we have had, nothing comes close to a Calcutta roll—neither in taste, nor in sound architecture.</p>

<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he egg roll is certainly Calcutta’s most recognizable and popular street food. But what makes a good roll? It should be served hot. So the assembly process, once the <em>paratha</em> has been fried,  needs to be quick and efficient. The outer shell, the <em>paratha</em> itself, must be flaky yet soft. It should not be too chewy, that is to say, you should not have to tug at it with your teeth. Most importantly, the <em>paratha</em> should be fully cooked and crisp. The filling should be evenly distributed so you get a little of everything with each bite. Finally, the mark of an excellently wrapped roll is that you can eat it using just one hand. Simply bite into your roll and when you reach the paper, gently grip the roll with your teeth to slide it out as you go along. No overflowing filling, no leaking sauces. Everything is contained within a neat package that you can enjoy on the go.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 530 kcal per paratha</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE WRAP</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Dalda (shortening)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>180–200 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE FILLING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Eggs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Onions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 large</td>
<td>Lime</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1–2 tsp</td>
<td>Chaat masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1–2 tsp</td>
<td>Rocksalt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>80 g</td>
<td>Tomato ketchup</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cucumber (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 75 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
<li>Flat frying pan | skillet</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Sheets of thin, absorbent paper</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>For the outer <em>paratha</em>/wrap, add the flour, salt, sugar, and <em>dalda</em> to a mixing bowl. Combine the ingredients until the fat is well dispersed in the flour. Take your time and rub the flour between your fingers until it resembles breadcrumbs in texture. This will lead to a flakier crust.</li>
<li>Now add the warm water and knead the dough for about 5 minutes until it is soft and smooth. Coat it with oil, cover the bowl, and allow it to rest for 30 minutes.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, mix together finely sliced onions, chopped green chillies and the juice of half a lime. Pickling the onions in lime juice reduces their sharpness. If using cucumber, peel it and remove the central seeds. Then chop them into thin matchsticks. Create an assembly station where you gather all the items required for the filling. This will allow you to easily put together the roll once the <em>paratha</em> is off the stove.</li>
<li>Back to the dough: once it has rested, divide it in 130 g portions. For an extra-flaky exterior, we will roll the dough in the <em>lachcha paratha</em> style, incorporating layers of flour and oil. To do this, form a ball and roll it out to a disc about 12 cm large. Apply a thin layer of oil on the surface and sprinkle some dry flour. Make an incision on the disc along a radius and roll it in the shape of a cone [WATCH THE VIDEO]. Press down to flatten. Rest the dough for about 5 minutes to relax it again, after which roll it for a second time to disc 22 cm in diameter.</li>
<li>Beat an egg with a pinch of salt and keep at the ready.</li>
<li>Heat about 4 tsp oil (12 g) in a flat frying pan or skillet. Add the <em>paratha</em> and fry it on both sides until golden. Rotate the <em>paratha</em> continuously, flipping often, for a uniform crust. Pay special attention to the sides to ensure that they crisp too. Once the <em>paratha</em> is completely cooked, spread the beaten egg over it. Before it settles, turn over to fry the side with the egg. Transfer it to the assembly station, with the egg side facing up.</li>
<li>Sprinkle it with <em>chaat masala</em> and rocksalt. Add a row of the pickled onions a little off the centre of the <em>paratha</em>. Squeeze some lime juice over it. Top it with cucumber if you like. One of our favourite variations of the egg roll is the egg-potato roll. If we have it on hand, we like to add some leftover spicy <em>alu’r torkari</em> as well. Finish everything off with a few squirts of ketchup.</li>
<li>Form a tight roll, making sure the filling is all enclosed within the <em>paratha</em>. Wrap a paper around two-thirds of the roll and tuck any excess at the bottom.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Green chillies</li>
<li>Lime wedges</li>
<li>Thums up!</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      &lt;p class=&quot;post-byline&quot;&gt;Calcutta’s most popular and iconic street food&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post-intro&quot;&gt;Of all the rolls, wraps, and frankies we have had, nothing comes close to a Calcutta roll—neither in taste, nor in sound architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.&lt;/em&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Shami Kabab</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/shami-kabab/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/shami-kabab/</id>
    <published>2017-08-24T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-25T02:51:37.452Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Pan-fried, delicately spiced, ground-meat <em>kababs</em></p>

<p class="post-intro">If you are just getting into the wonderful world of <em>kabab</em>-making, these are the easiest ones to start with.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">S</span><em>hami kabab</em> is well loved not least because it is one of the easier <em>kababs</em> to make. While producing good <em>kababs</em> generally requires special grilling, charring or <em>tandoori</em> techniques, <em>shami kabab</em> can be easily prepared at home with no special equipment. Popular on the Indian subcontinent, this snack resembles a pan-fried, ground-meat patty. It is best made with a lean, boneless red meat of your choice (mutton, beef, lamb, etc.). It is important that the meat has a low fat but high muscle content. Fat within the meat tends to melt the kabab when it is fried, while we want it to hold itself together. More muscle and fibre, on the other hand, will ensure that the meat has some texture when it is ground, providing a satisfying resistance with each bite. The use of <em>chhola’r dal</em> (split Bengal gram) adds nuttiness. Besides that, the other flavours come from chopped mint leaves, green chillies, <em>garam masala</em>, and ghee. We use a beaten egg to bind everything together. Depending on the recipe, such kababs may sometimes be coated in eggs or bread crumbs before they are fried. We, however, fry them directly so that the meat itself forms a rich, brown, caramelised crust.  </p>
<p></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 2 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 16–17 kababs</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Boneless mutton or beef (lean)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Chhola’r dal (split Bengal gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Onions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Mint leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Raisins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Lime juice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td><a href="recipe/shahi-garam-masala/">Shahi garam masala</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1</td>
<td>Beaten egg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 200 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (1-cm deep, for frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
<li>Flat frying pan | skillet</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
<li><em>Jhuri</em> | draining rack | colander </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and soak <em>chhola’r dal</em> overnight. Drain the water in the morning.</li>
<li>In a boiling pot, add the boneless meat cut into 3-cm cubes, soaked <em>dal</em>, roughly chopped onions, ginger and garlic, bay leaves, dried red chillies, and salt. Add about 400 g water and set the pot to boil. For this dish, the meat needs to be absolutely tender, but remain dry. It’s best, therefore, to add water a little at a time and keep an eye on the pot so that the bottom doesn’t catch, and yet there’s no extra water. Once the meat has cooked (this should take about 60 to 90 minutes depending on the meat and your location), on high heat dry off any excess water. </li>
<li>Pick out the bay leaves from the pot and discard them.</li>
<li>Transfer the mixture to a grinder jar and grind it on the lowest setting until it is uniform. You may need to scrape the sides of your jar a couple of times. Remember that a good <em>shami kabab</em> has texture. Your grind should not be too smooth or pasty. Rather, the meat fibres should still be visible.</li>
<li>Transfer this ground mixture to a mixing bowl. Add chopped green chillies, chopped mint leaves, raisins, lime juice, <em>shahi garam masala</em> powder, ghee, and a beaten egg. Mix everything together thoroughly by hand.</li>
<li>Portion the mixture into balls weighing 60 g each. Apply some ghee on your palms so the mixture doesn’t stick to them and form discs 6 cm in diameter, making sure to patch up as many cracks as you can. This will prevent breakage while frying.</li>
<li>On medium flame, heat your flat frying pan or skillet. Once hot, add vegetable oil, about 1 cm deep. For a good crust, its level should reach half the height of the <em>kabab</em>. Once the oil is about 180°C, gently lower the <em>kababs</em> one by one. Do not crowd the pan; fry no more than 4 to 5 <em>kababs</em> at a time.</li>
<li>Fry each side for about 2 minutes until they are brown. Drain from the oil on to a perforated vessel to keep them crisp. </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Coriander and coconut chutney</li>
<li>Mint and yoghurt chutney</li>
<li>Tomato ketchup</li>
<li>Salad (onions, cucumber and tomatoes)</li>
<li>Slider buns</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A mellow spiced easy pan fried kabab made from ground beef, mutton, or lamb and popular in India, Bangladesh and Pakistan.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="beef" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/beef/"/>
    
      <category term="mutton" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mutton/"/>
    
      <category term="kabab" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kabab/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Churmur</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/churmur/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/churmur/</id>
    <published>2017-08-17T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-25T02:38:31.013Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">What you get when you deconstruct your <em>phuchka</em></p>

<p class="post-intro">This Calcutta street snack combines myriads of flavours and textures into a tangy-savoury-mushy-crunchy explosion in your mouth.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">C</span>hurmur is a type of <em>chaat</em> and one of the more inspired offerings to come out of a <em>phuchkawala</em>’s cart. It contains the usual suspects—potatoes, boiled <em>motor dal</em>, tamarind, green chillies, coriander, and a variety of spices and seasoning—all mixed together and heaped upon a <em>shalpata</em> plate. From its onomatopoeic name that recalls the sound (‘<em>chur-mur</em>’) a crisp <em>papri</em> makes when crushed to its vibrant amalgamation of flavours and textures, there’s nothing about this dish that is not delightful. When you are not ready to leave your <em>phuchka</em> stall yet, but must, it is <em>churmur</em>—<em>puchka</em> deconstructed—that you can take home with you in a paper bag. </p>
<p>In this video we should you how to reproduce this astoundingly addictive <em>chaat</em> at home.</p>
<p></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 2 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Potatoes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>60 g</td>
<td>Phuchka papri</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Chhola (whole Bengal gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Motor dal (whole yellow peas)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Tamarind</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 tsp</td>
<td>Lime juice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Rocksalt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td><a href="https://youtu.be/gGmCPwauVBs" target="_blank" rel="external">Bhaja masala</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Chilli flakes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pressure cooker | boiling pot</li>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak the <em>chhola</em> and <em>motor dal</em> for about 12 hours. Wash them after that. Drain the <em>chhola</em> and set it aside. Boil the <em>motor dal</em> until it softens but remains whole (it should not disintegrate). Drain the <em>motor dal</em> and leave it to cool.</li>
<li>Boil the potatoes till they are tender. Peel and dice into 1-cm cubes, and transfer them to a mixing bowl.</li>
<li>While the potatoes are boiling, add 75 g hot water to the tamarind and allow it to soak for 15 minutes. This will soften the tamarind and ensure easy extraction of the pulp. Work the tamarind between your fingers to separate the skin and seeds. Press to squeeze out all the juice and discard the seeds. You should be left with some smooth tamarind pulp.</li>
<li>At this point, also roughly crush the green chillies using a mortar and pestle, chop coriander leaves, and slice the lime.</li>
<li>Back to the mixing bowl with the diced potatoes: add soaked <em>chhola</em>, boiled <em>motor dal</em>, chopped coriander, crushed green chillies, lime juice, tamarind pulp, salt, rocksalt, chilli flakes and <em>bhaja masala</em>. Crush the _papri_s and add them too.</li>
<li>Mix until everything is evenly combined. Use a light hand so that you don’t mash the potatoes or grind the <em>papri</em> to a fine powder—we want them to remain chunky. Serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This crispy, tangy, savoury &#39;chaat&#39; is a popular Calcutta street food dished out by phuchkawalas and is super easy to make.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ilish Machh’er Tel Jhol</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-macher-tel-jhol/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-macher-tel-jhol/</id>
    <published>2017-08-09T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-11T02:47:01.930Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A light hilsa fish curry with aubergines</p>

<p class="post-intro">What better way to enjoy the season’s freshest hilsa than in a simple, mild curry?</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">‘T</span>el jhol’ is the name given to a light Bengali curry, which is infused with flavours of <em>kaalo jeere</em>, green chillies, and sharp mustard oil. Because it is sparsely spiced, this style of curry doesn’t overpower the star ingredient—the fish—but lets it shine on its own. This recipe for <em>ilish machh’er tel jhol</em> uses only seven ingredients, including the fish. Needless to say, it is designed to bring out the flavours of the fresh <em>ilish</em> in all their glory. If you have under 30 minutes and a batch of fresh <em>ilish</em>, this should be your go-to curry</p>
<hr>
<p>Ilish or hilsa is, however, is facing extinction due to high demand and overfishing. While <a href="http://cmsdata.iucn.org/downloads/iucn_hilsa_study.pdf" target="_blank" rel="external">policy initiatives</a> between India and Bangladesh <a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/news-ians/india-bangladesh-seek-to-save-the-delectable-hilsa-113062700390_1.html" target="_blank" rel="external">are underway</a> to tackle this alarming situation (hilsa conservation depends a great deal on water flow in the Padma-Meghna and Hooghly-Bhagirathi river systems), we can do our bit too. We can be mindful <em>not to buy any hilsa</em> that is under 500 g / 25 cm. Catching of hilsa before the spawning stage is detrimental to the progression of the next generation. It is equally important also to <em>not buy hilsa during the breeding season</em> (especially October to November, but even better, until March). In 2016, Bangaldesh was able to <a href="https://scroll.in/article/806667/how-king-hilsa-made-a-comeback" target="_blank" rel="external">increase its hilsa yield</a> by 50 per cent by putting measures in place to ban fishing in the breeding season. It also laid down and imposed specifications for net size to prevent the catching of juvenile hilsa. There is a need to create more consciousness about the importance of conserving a fish that is perhaps Bengal’s greatest cultural icon.</p>
<p><strong> How can you help? </strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Don’t to buy any hilsa that is under 500 g / 25 cm. Catching of hilsa before the spawning stage is detrimental to the progression of the next generation. </li>
<li>It is equally important also to <em>not buy hilsa during the breeding season</em> (especially October to November, but even better, until March).</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 340 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Ilish machh (hilsa fish, 3-cm-thick pieces)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Brinjal (5cm chunks)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking and garnish)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Atta (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>350 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Marinate the fish with ¾ tsp salt and ¾ tsp turmeric powder, and set aside.</li>
<li>Cut the brinjal into 5-cm chunks and slit the green chillies.</li>
<li>Before you begin, also make a paste of 18 g salt, 6 g turmeric, and 50 g water. </li>
<li>Heat 35 g mustard oil in a pan till it starts to smoke lightly and changes colour to a pale yellow. Add the brinjal and fry them till they are golden. On medium heat, this should take about 4 minutes. Drain from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Now, lower the fish pieces into the oil one by one and fry them for a minute on each side. Delicately flavoured fish such as the <em>ilish</em> does not need heavy searing, so fry very lightly. Remove from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Temper the same oil with <em>kaalo jeere</em> and 3 green chillies. Add the salt and turmeric mixture we prepared earlier. Fry until the smell of raw turmeric is gone. This should take about 6 to 7 minutes.</li>
<li>Add 350 g hot water. This will form the curry. Once it has come to a full boil, add the fried brinjal and allow it to bubble in the curry for about 2 minutes. Then, gently lower the fried fish. Be careful while stirring at this point because the fish is fragile and might break. </li>
<li>Boil on medium heat for about 5 minutes, after which take 2 tablespoons of the curry into a small bowl along with a couple of the softened green chillies. Add ¼ tsp of <em>atta</em> to this and mix everything until uniform. Mash the green chillies to release heat and flavour. Add this mixture back to the pan. Drizzle with 5 g of raw mustard oil and bubble for about 2 more minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A hearty Bengali Ilish (Hilsa) curry that takes just six ingredients and 30 minutes to cook.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="hilsa" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/hilsa/"/>
    
      <category term="tel jhol" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/tel-jhol/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Tingmo</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/tingmo/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/tingmo/</id>
    <published>2017-08-04T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-04T03:47:49.780Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A Tibetan steamed bread</p>

<p class="post-intro">Another Blue Poppy favourite, this soft, airy breadroll goes extremely well with <em>datshis</em>, pork shapta, or chilli pork.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>ingmo or ting momo is one of those breads that is extremely satisfying to get right. The distinguishing feature of this steamed dumpling is its layered appearance. Once properly proofed and steamed, all the layers of the bun seem to open up like a flower. In this recipe, we show you how to knead, roll, and shape the dough in order to get a perfect tingmo. </p>
<p><hr><br><strong>A note on the yeast:</strong> Yeast will need to be used depending on its type. Check the box/packaging to determine whether yours is an ‘instant’ yeast, ‘active dry’ yeast, or ‘fresh’ yeast. <strong>Instant yeast</strong> doesn’t need to be separately activated. It can be mixed directly into the flour and kneaded along with the other ingredients. <strong>Active dry yeast</strong> and <strong>fresh yeast</strong> need to be activated before they can be added to the flour. To do that, disperse the yeast in lukewarm water (in this case, about 145 g) along with the sugar (10 g). Cover and set aside for about 15 minutes, at the end of which, if your yeast is active, the mixture should take on a frothy appearance. Add this mixture to the flour and proceed as instructed. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 2 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 tingmos</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Dry instant yeast</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>145 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 tbsp</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for greasing)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
<li>Steamer</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>In a mixing bowl, combine the flour, salt, sugar, yeast, and water. See the note above to correctly activate your yeast. Once the ingredients have come together, transfer the dough to the work surface. </li>
<li>Knead the dough for 15 minutes, repeatedly folding the dough over itself to develop gluten. Round the dough by tucking all the edges at the bottom and return it to the mixing bowl, now greased with oil, to prevent the dough from sticking.</li>
<li>Cover and proof the dough in a warm place for 1 hour, until the dough doubles in size.</li>
<li>Dust the work surface with flour and transfer the dough to it. Flatten the dough into a rectangle with your palms. Using a rolling pin, roll the dough into a thin sheet, 40 cm by 45 cm in dimensions, maintaining its rectangular shape as much as possible. </li>
<li>Apply oil on the sheet and fold its longer side into thirds. </li>
<li>Use a knife to divide the folded dough into four equal parts. Divide each quarter further into 6 long strips. </li>
<li>Stack the strips in pairs of threes such that you now have four sets of strips.</li>
<li>Form the tingmo as shown in the video and place it on a greased steaming dish.</li>
<li>Once all the tingmos have been formed, cover the dish and allow them to proof for another 30 minutes before setting them over boiling water to steam. </li>
<li>These buns take no longer than 10 to 12 minutes to cook perfectly. Do not over-steam or the bread might become rubbery. </li>
<li>Serve immediately they are still warm.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/ema-datshi">Ema datshi</a> | kewa datshi</li>
<li>Pork shapta</li>
<li>Chilli pork</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Tingmo—a traditional Tibetan steamed bread—is soft, light, and airy. Goes perfectly with spicy pork or a datshi!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="bhutanese" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhutanese/"/>
    
      <category term="bread" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bread/"/>
    
      <category term="tibetan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/tibetan/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ema Datshi</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/ema-datshi/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/ema-datshi/</id>
    <published>2017-07-28T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-08-04T03:46:38.674Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A Bhutanese cheese and chilli preparation </p>

<p class="post-intro">This traditional Bhutanese dish is a favourite at Calcutta’s famous restaurant The Blue Poppy.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">E</span>ma datshi is the national dish of Bhutan, and rightly so. All across the country, residents and travellers alike can be seen eating this hearty concoction of cheese and chillies. Apart from Bhutan, this preparation is also consumed in several parts of Northeast India and Nepal. ‘Ema’ and ‘datshi’ literally stand for ‘chillies’ and ‘cheese’, and as such can be made using one or more varieties of either ingredient. ‘Datshi’ is also used to refer to any cheese-based soup (the version with potatoes, for example, is called ‘kewa datshi’ where ‘kewa’ means potatoes). </p>
<p>This dish can be prepared using an assortment of chilli peppers for flavour. We’ve used jalapeños, but look for slightly large chillies such as those commonly used for <em>achar</em> or pickles. We’ve combined them with green chillies, which provide the heat. As for cheese, any good, locally available melting cheese (such as that commonly found in New Market in Calcutta) will do. In a pinch, you can also use processed cheese. Avoid using a stringy cheese like mozzarella for this soup. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 25 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 2 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>220 g</td>
<td>Jalapeños (quartered)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>70 g</td>
<td>Onions (sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Garlic (roughly chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes (diced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Cheese (grated)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Butter</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Saucepan | <em>kadai</em> with lid</li>
<li>Cheese grater</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Remove the stalks off the chilli peppers and cut them in quarters lengthwise. Also slit the green chillies, slice the onions, roughly chop the garlic, and dice the tomatoes.    </li>
<li>Add all these ingredients to the pan along with the salt, oil, and 250 g water. </li>
<li>Turn on the heat and cover the pan with a lid. Allow everything to boil on medium heat for 15 minutes until the peppers have softened. </li>
<li>Turn off the heat and add the butter and grated cheese. Killing the heat before adding cheese will prevent it from curdling. Stir these in until the cheese has melted. </li>
<li>Check for salt, which will vary depending on how salty your cheese is. Serve hot. </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Red rice</li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Plain rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/tingmo">Tingmo</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Ema datshi, the national dish of Bhutan, is an easy-to-make, hearty soup with chilli peppers (‘ema’) and cheese (‘datshi’).
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="soup" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/soup/"/>
    
      <category term="bhutanese" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhutanese/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Aloo Paratha</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/aloo-paratha/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/aloo-paratha/</id>
    <published>2017-07-21T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-09-01T02:56:10.452Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A pan-fried flatbread stuffed with a filling of mashed potatoes</p>

<p class="post-intro">In this recipe, we take you through the process of mixing, stuffing, rolling, and frying the perfect ‘parathas’.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>lu porota or ‘alu paratha’ is wildly popular all over South Asia—no <em>dhaba</em> scene is complete without the sight of hot parathas with melting butter on top. Home kitchens have undoubtedly devised healthier ways of dishing out this family favourite. Not only are these <em>porotas</em> satisfyingly delicious when served piping hot right off the skillet, they also make for extraordinarily good packed meals. Ideal for school or work tiffin boxes or long train journeys, soft <em>alu porotas</em> need few accompaniments besides some chilled yoghurt and hot, tangy <em>achar</em>.</p>
<p>A good stuffed <em>porota</em> has a flaky exterior (you should be able to tear it with one hand) and a generous amount of well-spiced filling. Moreover, the filling should be evenly distributed within the <em>porota</em> so you get some with every bite. In this recipe, we take you step-by-step through the process of creating soft, well-balanced <em>porotas</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 45 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 parathas<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 385 kcal per paratha</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE DOUGH</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Atta (whole wheat flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100–110 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE FILLING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (boiled and peeled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>80 g</td>
<td>Onions (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Ginger (minced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Garlic (minced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Green chillies (chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Kasuri methi/curry leaves/coriander leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Chaat masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Bhaja masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Jowan (carom seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Oil for cooking/frying</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Steamer | boiling pot</li>
<li>Rolling pin</li>
<li>Skillet | <em>tawa</em></li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Napkin | paper towel (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Steamer</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—MIX THE DOUGH</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Add <em>atta</em>, salt, sugar, and oil to a mixing bowl. Mix to distribute the oil evenly among the other ingredients.</li>
<li>Add the water. Use hot water for soft <em>porotas</em>.</li>
<li>Knead the dough for about 5 minutes. It may seem tacky at the outset, but keep going. The dough should be soft and pliable so that it can hold a generous amount of filling.</li>
<li>Once the kneading is done, cover and rest the dough for about 30 minutes.   </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—PREPARE THE FILLING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Meanwhile, halve or quarter your potatoes (depending on their size) and steam them till they are tender. This should take about 20 minutes. Steaming ensures that the potatoes do not overcook or absorb any excess moisture from sitting in a pot of boiling water. The drier the filling, the easier it is to stuff the <em>porota</em> without any leakage.</li>
<li>Peel the potatoes and mash them while they are still hot to allow all the steam to escape. This will further ensure that the filling remains dry.</li>
<li>Finely chop the onions, ginger, garlic, and green chillies. Tear or roughly chop the curry or coriander leaves, whichever you are using.</li>
<li>Heat 7 g vegetable oil in a skillet. Add the onions and fry them for about 4 to 5 minutes till they turn brown. </li>
<li>Add the ginger and green chillies, and fry for another minute or so before adding the garlic and curry leaves/<em>kasuri methi</em>/coriander leaves. Do not cook the garlic too much; turn off the heat 30 seconds after adding it to the pan.</li>
<li>Transfer this mixture from the pan on to the mashed potatoes. Also add the salt, <em>chaat masala</em>, <em>bhaja masala</em>, and <em>jowan</em>.</li>
<li>Give everything a good mix until the filling is uniform. </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—STUFF, ROLL, FRY</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Divide the filling into four equal parts (each should weigh about 75 g). Give the dough a quick knead and divide it into four equal portions too (about 70 g each). Form each portion of the filling and dough into a neat ball and keep at the ready.</li>
<li>Using your hands, flatten a ball of dough until it has stretched to a diameter of 8 cm. Place a ball of the filling in the centre. </li>
<li>Bring the sides of the dough towards one another. The idea is to completely enclose the filling with the dough. Pinch the gathered sides to seal the package.</li>
<li>Coat the dough with some flour and place it on the workstation in front of you. Press down gently to flatten the dough and distribute the filling evenly within it.</li>
<li>Using a rolling pin, start rolling in two short, gentle strokes. Rotate 90 degrees between each set of strokes. Keep doing this until the <em>porota</em> is about 18 cm in diameter. Be sure to roll at the edges and not at the centre. This will ensure that the <em>porota</em> is of a uniform thickness throughout. </li>
<li>In a skillet set on medium heat, add 1 tbsp of oil. Once hot, lay the <em>porota</em> flat on it. Wait for a minute and apply 1 tsp of oil to the top. Flip the <em>porota</em>.</li>
<li>Keep flipping every minute until the <em>porota</em> is an even, golden colour on both sides. </li>
<li>Remove from the skillet and serve hot.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Yoghurt</li>
<li>Pickles</li>
<li>Green chilli</li>
<li>Raw onion</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Alu porota or ‘paratha’ needs no introduction. This popular flatbread stuffed with delicately spiced potatoes is a real treat.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="paratha" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/paratha/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ilish Machh’er Paturi</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-paturi/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-paturi/</id>
    <published>2017-07-15T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-17T01:03:47.941Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Hilsa in mustard sauce, steamed in a banana-leaf parcel</p>

<p class="post-intro">Eating the endangered hilsa responsibly is likely to ensure that we enjoy classics such as this for a long time to come.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span><em>lish machh’er paturi</em> combines three of Bengal’s greatest loves—the hilsa fish, the banana plant, and mustard. Even though it looks very polished, it is a fairly easy recipe to execute. It requires few ingredients, no special technique, and very little time.</p>
<p>Ilish or hilsa is, however, is facing extinction due to high demand and overfishing. While policy initiatives between India and Bangladesh are underway to tackle this alarming situation (hilsa conservation depends a great deal on water flow in the Padma-Meghna and Hooghly-Bhagirathi river systems), we can do our bit too <a href="http://cmsdata.iucn.org/downloads/iucn_hilsa_study.pdf" target="_blank" rel="external">[source]</a>.</p>
<p><strong> How can you help? </strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Don’t to buy any hilsa that is under 500 g / 25 cm. Catching of hilsa before the spawning stage is detrimental to the progression of the next generation. </li>
<li>It is equally important also to <em>not buy hilsa during the breeding season</em> (especially October to November, but even better, until March).</li>
</ol>
<p>In 2016, Bangaldesh was able to increase its hilsa yield by 50 per cent by putting measures in place to ban fishing in the breeding season. It also laid down and imposed specifications for net size to prevent the catching of juvenile hilsa. There is a need to create more consciousness about the importance of conserving a fish that is perhaps Bengal’s greatest cultural icon. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 324 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>280 g (or 4 pcs)</td>
<td>Ilish machh (hilsa fish, 3-cm-thick pieces)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Mustard seeds (soaked overnight)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Coconut (peeled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt (beaten)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="You-will-also-need"><a href="#You-will-also-need" class="headerlink" title="You will also need"></a>You will also need</h2><ul>
<li>Banana leaves (<em>kolapata</em>)</li>
<li>A spool of thin cotton string</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Flat pan | <em>tawa</em></li>
<li>Lid for the <em>tawa</em></li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak mustard seeds overnight in water.</li>
<li>Clean the <em>ilish machh</em> and cut it in 3-cm thick slices. <em>Kolapaturi</em> is best made with thick slices of fish. Set these pieces aside, preferably on a flat plate.</li>
<li>Drain the mustard seeds of the water they’ve been soaking in and add them to a grinder jar. Add 4 green chillies, roughly chopped, along with 100g water. Grinding green chillies with the mustard ensures that it doesn’t turn bitter. </li>
<li>Grind these to a fine paste. Take your time with this process. Scrape down the sides of the jar and grind as many times as it takes to form the smoothest possible paste. The finer the grind, the better the flavours.</li>
<li>Now, add the peeled and chopped coconut to the grinder jar, along with salt, sugar, and turmeric powder. Grind once again till everything is smooth and well combined. </li>
<li>Transfer this paste to a mixing bowl. Add the beaten yoghurt and mustard oil. Mix till the oil is fully incorporated. </li>
<li>Spoon this mixture over the <em>ilish machh</em>, dividing it equally. Turn the fish over and coat the other side as well. Use your hands to make sure every part of the fish, including its cavities, are well coated. Set it aside to marinate for 15 minutes.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, wash and cut up some <em>kolapata</em> into rectangular sheets, 20 cm by 50 cm in dimension. Gently toast them on a pan set on medium heat. This will increase malleability of the banana leaves, ensuring that they don’t crack when folded. Remove from heat and set aside.</li>
<li>Take a banana-leaf sheet in front of you. Spoon some mustard paste in the centre of one of the sheet. Set one piece of the fish on it. Top off with some more of the paste and a split green chilli.</li>
<li>Carefully wrap the fish with the banana leaf making sure that it is fully covered. If you find that your leaf is torn, wrap another layer of leaf around it. Tie this parcel up securely with a cotton string (don’t use synthetic or it will melt when heated). </li>
<li>Add a tablespoon of oil to the <em>tawa</em> (pan). Once hot, place the parcels on it side by side. </li>
<li>Cover and steam the banana-leaf parcels on low heat for 5 minutes on each side.</li>
<li>Unwrap and serve hot.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This recipe for hilsa in mustard sauce, steamed in banana-leaf parcels, involves only nine ingredients and is very easy to make.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="hilsa" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/hilsa/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Khichuri</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/khichuri/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/khichuri/</id>
    <published>2017-07-07T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-07T02:21:59.428Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">The Bengali variant of ‘khichdi’ made with roasted moong dal and fragrant <em>gobindobhog</em> rice</p>

<p class="post-intro"><em>Khichuri</em> is one of those rare dishes that effortlessly strides the boundary between what’s considered ‘ordinary’ and ‘special’ when it comes to cooking.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span>f there is one common thread linking the varied and multitudinous South Asian cuisines, it is <em>khichuri</em>. Essentially a porridge of rice and dal tempered with a handful of spices (that can vary from region to region), <em>khichuri</em> can be as plain or as rich as you want it to be. It ranges from the mild, runny, and carefully spiced version for when you are under the weather, to the steaming and slurpy one for those wistful rainy days, to the thick, gorgeous, ghee-laden offering made to your favourite goddesses during <em>pujo</em>. </p>
<p>Today’s recipe can double as an easy <em>bhog’er khichuri</em>, as well as a delicious, sustaining rainy-day meal. It is made with <em>shona moong</em>—little grains of golden <em>moong dal</em> commonly found in Bengal. The rice used is <em>gobindobhog chaal</em>, a scented, short-grained variety with which <em>polao</em> and <em>payesh</em> are also typically made. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour 15 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6-8 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 413 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Moong dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Gobindobhog rice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (5 cm chunks)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Cauliflower (5 cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes (quartered)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>80 g</td>
<td>Peas (blanched)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Grated coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Garam masala powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.8 litres</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Large <em>kadai</em> | frying pan | boiling pot</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Colander or draining nets</li>
<li>Electric kettle | saucepan (to heat water)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder | grater (to grate coconut)</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Rinse <em>gobindobhog</em> rice thoroughly, spread it it over a colander or net, and leave it to air-dry completely.</li>
<li>Cut potatoes in 5-cm chunks, cauliflower into 5-cm florets, and tomatoes into quarters. Shell and blanch the peas.</li>
<li>Set a <em>kadai</em> on medium heat and add the <em>moong dal</em> to it. Dry-roast the <em>dal</em> for about 6 minutes or till it turns pinkish-brown giving off a nutty aroma. Stir continuously throughout to get an even roast.</li>
<li>Once roasted, transfer the <em>dal</em> to a large bowl or saucepan, and wash it. Rinse just once; overrinsing will cause the <em>moong dal</em> to lose its nutty scent. Strain over a colander and set aside.</li>
<li>Back in the <em>kadai</em>, heat 5 g vegetable oil. Add the washed <em>gobindobhog</em> rice to it.</li>
<li>Fry the rice for about 4 to 5 minutes, stirring frequently, till it takes on a glassy look. Frying activates the sweet smell of <em>gobindobhog</em> rice. Once done, transfer the rice to a plate; set aside.</li>
<li>In the same <em>kadai</em>, add 15 g more vegetable oil. Fry the potatoes till they develop a golden film. Remove from oil and set aside. Add the cauliflower to the pan, fry till the florets are lightly coloured, and set those aside too.</li>
<li>In a small bowl, mix the ginger paste, turmeric powder, and cumin powder with 50 g water. Keep it ready. Also set water to boil on the stove or in an electric kettle.</li>
<li>Now, add 15 g mustard oil to the pan, set on medium heat. Once the oil is hot, temper it with dried red chillies, bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and cumin seeds. </li>
<li>Add the grated coconut. Fry for about 3 minutes until the coconut turns golden.</li>
<li>Add the ginger-turmeric-cumin paste to the pan. Fry the spices on medium heat till the their raw smell is gone and oil starts oozing from the mixture. This should take about 8 minutes. If you find during this time that the mixture has run dry, add about 50 g more water and continue frying.</li>
<li>Add the tomatoes, cover, and cook for about 2 minutes. </li>
<li>Next, add the fried <em>gobindobhog</em> rice, roasted <em>moond dal</em>, and 2 slit green chillies. Stir them into the spices and cook for about 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Add 1.8 litres of hot water along with the salt. Cover the pan and allow its contents to boil for about 5 minutes. The heat should be set at low from this point onwards.</li>
<li>Once the water is bubbling, add the fried potatoes and cauliflower. Cover and cook for about 15 minutes. <em>Dal</em> tends to settle at the bottom and stick to the pan, so don’t forget to stir occasionally, scraping the bottom thoroughly. </li>
<li>After 15 minutes, add the sugar, blanched peas, and 3 more slit green chillies. Stir everything in and cook for 3 to 4 more minutes.</li>
<li>Garnish with ghee and garam masala powder. Turn off the heat, cover the pan, and allow the <em>khichuri</em> to rest for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/">Panchmishali torkari</a></li>
<li>Papad</li>
<li>Omelette</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/begun-bhaja/">Begun bhaja</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The Bengali variant of the ever-pervasive South Asian ‘khichdi’, made with nutty, roasted moong dal and fragrant gobindobhog rice.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="rice" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rice/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lau’er Shukto</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/lau-shukto/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/lau-shukto/</id>
    <published>2017-06-30T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-30T03:05:19.728Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">An easy <em>shukto</em> of bottle-gourd</p>

<p class="post-intro">This creamy, mellow, bottle-gourd appetiser is one of the quickest <em>shukto</em> recipes, that can be cooked in under an hour with very little preparation.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span>n Bengali cooking, <em>shukto</em> refers to a wide array of mild, sometimes bitter, milky curries. It is usually served as an appetiser for lunch, just after <em>shaak</em> (greens) and before <em>dal</em> (lentils). It opens up the palate for the oncoming spicier courses. While the most popular <em>shukto</em> is the one made from a selection of vegetables—such as <em>kachkola</em> (raw bananas), <em>sheem</em> (flat beans), sweet potatoes, brinjal, <em>korola</em> (bitter gourd), and so on—the one we show you here is made of just <em>lau</em> or bottle gourd. In places where they are available, the tender stalks and shoots of the <em>lau</em> are also added to the curry.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 35 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>CALORIES PER SERVING</strong> 85 kcal</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>750 g</td>
<td>Lau (bottle gourd), along with tender shoots, if available</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Dal’er bori</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Poppy paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Mustard seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder | <em>sheel-nora</em> (to make poppy paste)</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak the poppy seeds in hot water for at least two hours. After that, grind them to a fine paste. When you rub some of the paste between your fingers, it should feel smooth, that is, the individual poppy seeds should not be discernable. The finer you grind the poppy seeds, the better the flavour.</li>
<li>Peel the <em>lau</em> and cut it into 3-mm-thick matchsticks.</li>
<li>Set a pan on medium heat and add in the <em>lau</em> along with half of the salt (about 10 g) and 30 g of water. Cover and allow the <em>lau</em> to steam for 8 minutes. This will give the vegetable a head start while cooking.</li>
<li>Once the <em>lau</em> is soft remove it from the pan and reserve in a bowl along with the juices.</li>
<li>Set the <em>kadai</em> back on the heat. Wipe it dry so that when you add oil to it, it doesn’t splatter.</li>
<li>Heat 20 g vegetable oil. Once hot, drop the <em>dal’er bori</em> and fry them till they are golden. This should take about 20 seconds. Drain them from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Before proceeding any further, mix 20 g water in the ginger paste and keep it ready.</li>
<li>Temper the same oil with bay leaves and mustard seeds.</li>
<li>Wait for the seeds to crackle before adding the ginger paste. Fry it for about 4 minutes.</li>
<li>Next, add the steamed <em>lau</em> along with the reserved juices. Mix everything well.</li>
<li>At this stage, also add the remaining salt (12 g) and all of the sugar. Also stir in the poppy paste.</li>
<li>Let everything bubble for about 6 minutes on medium heat. If you find that juices are running dry, drop the heat or cover the pan.</li>
<li>Break the fried <em>bori</em> into shards and add it to the shukto.</li>
<li>Mix the flour into the milk and add that to the shukto too. The flour will help thicken the juices and allow them to coat the <em>lau</em>.</li>
<li>Cook for another 2 to 3 minutes, after which add the ghee, cover, and rest before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | roti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This mild, creamy, bottle-gourd appetizer served for lunch—lau’er shukto—is the quickest shukto you can make.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
      <category term="lau" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/lau/"/>
    
      <category term="shukto" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/shukto/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Khichra—Bohra-Style Haleem</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/khichra-bohra-haleem/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/khichra-bohra-haleem/</id>
    <published>2017-06-16T05:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-17T06:35:22.907Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A slow-cooked stew of meat, grains, and pulses.</p>

<p class="post-intro">Of the many migrant communities that make up the rich tapestry of Calcutta’s modern history, the Bohra Muslims might not be the most visible, but they are a thriving culture. By some accounts, Calcutta is estimated to have under 5,000 ‘Bohris’. Mostly traders and businessfolk, the earliest settlers arrived in the city from western parts of India in the late 1800s</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span><em>hichro</em> is a typically Bohra Muslim preparation. Like the more popular <em>haleem</em> found in Calcutta during Ramzan, <em>khichro</em> is made by slowly cooking meat and grains together till the meat falls off the bone. <em>Khichro</em> is a special dish, being most prominently consumed communally on the tenth day of Muharram by Bohras across the globe, but it is also a very homely preparation, eaten throughout the year. It is deceptively light. In spite of the fact that a lot of onions, spices, meat, milk, and ghee goes into the dish, it is, underneath all that, a very hearty porridge of various kinds of grains. The <em>khichro</em> is distinctive in that it is pale in colour; it doesn’t make use of turmeric powder, chilli powder, jeera powder, and other such spices. Apart from meat, its main ingredient is broken wheat (dalia can also be used), whereas <em>haleem</em> is made predominantly with a mixture of dals.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Day 1</th>
<th>Day 2</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Soaking grains</td>
<td>Chopping meat</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Making <em>birasta</em></td>
<td>Cooking grains</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cooking meat</td>
<td>Blending everything together</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Separating meat, stock, and bones</td>
<td>Garnishing</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 5 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>GRAINS</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>180 g</td>
<td>Broken wheat or dalia</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Masoor dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Moong dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Chhola’r dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Rice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE MEAT</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>800 g</td>
<td>Beef (or any red meat of your choice)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Onions</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 pcs</td>
<td>Peppercorns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/">Shahi garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>33 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>LIQUIDS</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.5 kg</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>650 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FAT</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>GARNISH</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 bunch</td>
<td>Mint leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 wedges</td>
<td>Lime</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Large dish or pot (for soaking grains)</li>
<li>Heavy-bottomed boiling pot with lid</li>
<li>Pressure cooker</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khhunti</em> | long stapula</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—SOAKING GRAINS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Take the broken wheat, dals, and rice in a bowl. Rinse them well and soak overnight, for at least 12 hours.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—FRYING ONIONS (<em>BIRASTA</em>)</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Slice 650g onions thinly, cutting off the root that holds the bulb together.</li>
<li>Using you hand, scrunch up the slices to separate each layer. Chopping off the root will ensure that each strand separates from the rest.</li>
<li>Heat vegetable oil, 3 cm deep, on medium heat. Once hot, drop a handful of the onion slices. Be sure not to overcrowd the pan; the onions must fry in a single layer.</li>
<li>Using a fork, move the onions around every so often so that they fry evenly.</li>
<li>Just as the onions start to turn golden (do not wait until they have already turned golden), start removing them from the pan and draining them over a perforated vessel such as a colander or <em>jhuri</em>. Keep a close watch, as the onions tend to burn very quickly towards the end. Remove them from the oil <em>before</em> they have taken on the desired colour; they will continue to cook in the residual heat.</li>
<li>Allow them to cool and crisp up. This caramelised onion is called <em>birasta</em> and it is used in several Mughlai preparations. Raw onions weighing 650 g should yield about 165 g <em>birasta</em> (so about 25 per cent the weight of raw onions). It can be stored in an airtight container for 2 to 3 weeks.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—COOKING MEAT</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Using a grinder or mortar and pestle, form a smooth paste of 15 g ginger, 10 g garlic, and 10 g green chillies. Set aside.</li>
<li>In a <em>kadai</em>, heat 35 g vegetable oil. Once hot, fry the meat in batches, from all sides, till it is golden. Browning the meat enhances the flavour of the dish.</li>
<li>Remove from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>Temper the same oil with bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and peppercorns.</li>
<li>Add 350 g sliced onions, along with 15 g salt. Stirring intermittently, fry on medium heat for about 10 minutes till the onions turn brown.</li>
<li>Next, add in the ginger-garlic-green-chilli paste and fry for another 3 minutes, until the smell of the raw spices is gone.</li>
<li>Add <a href="/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/"><em>Shahi garam masala</em></a> powder and 35 g of the <em>birasta</em> we prepared earlier. Using a combination of sautéed and caramelised onions adds a depth of flavour to the preparation.</li>
<li>Add the browned pieces of meat to the onion mixture and sauté for about 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Transfer everything from the <em>kadai</em> to a pressure cooker. Add 1.5 kg of water, close the lid, and pressure cook for about 1 hour. The meat should be completely soft by this stage, such that it easily falls off the bone.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP IV—SEPARATING MEAT, BROTH, AND BONES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Pick out the meat pieces from the pressure cooker. Just as they are cool enough to handle, remove the bones, cartilage, and any hard, unrendered collagen that is still in the meat. Discard these, along with the bay leaves.</li>
<li>You should now be left with a gorgeous meaty broth, and some boneless pieces of tender meat. At this stage, you can put the meat and broth in the fridge and complete the rest of the preparation the following day.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP V—CHOPPING MEAT</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Chop the meat, against the grain, into 3-cm chunks. Chilling the meat before chopping hardens the collagen rendered from the meat, making it easy to cut into cubes.</li>
<li>Divide the meat into two piles. The first will be ground along with the grains, and the second added whole to the haleem towards the end.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP VI—BOILING GRAINS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Strain the water from the soaked grains, and transfer the latter to a heavy-bottomed pan. Add the broth we prepared earlier to the pan. (If you placed the broth in the fridge overnight, do not forget to first bring it to  boil before adding it to the grains.)</li>
<li>Also add 18 g of salt and the first pile of the chopped meat.</li>
<li>On low heat, let it all bubble for at least one hour, stirring occasionally, till the the grains are soft. Boiling the grains in the broth rather than in water intensifies the meaty flavour of the dish.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP VII—BLENDING EVERYTHING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Transfer the boiled grains into a blender and grind till everything breaks down. However, be careful not to reduce everything to a uniform, smooth paste, as we want some semblance of texture. Depending on the size of your blender jar, you may have to do this in batches.</li>
<li>Return the <em>haleem</em> to the pan. Add the remaining chunks of meat, along with 650 g hot milk. Mix until uniform. Bring to a boil before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP VIII—GARNISHING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>For the garnish, julienne some ginger, cut limes into wedges, split green chillies lengthwise, and finely chop the mint leaves.</li>
<li>Drop ladles of the <em>haleem</em> into a serving dish. Top it with a generous amount of <em>birasta</em> and chopped mint leaves.</li>
<li>Heat a pan till it is extremely hot. Add a spoonful of ghee and wait for it to smoke. Then add some julienned ginger and split green chillies. Fry for about 5 seconds and pour the contents of the pan (along with the ghee) over the serving dish.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Bread rolls</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Khichra, the Bohri version of haleem, is hearty dish is made by stewing meat, wheat and pulses. It is garnished with ghee, ginger, mint, and fried onions.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
      <category term="ramzan recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/ramzan-recipe/"/>
    
      <category term="bohra recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bohra-recipe/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Prawn Cocktail, Mocambo-Style</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/prawn-cocktail/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/prawn-cocktail/</id>
    <published>2017-06-09T04:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-09T02:57:31.288Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A favourite from Calcutta’s legendary Mocambo</p>

<p class="post-intro">It doesn’t take a wizard to figure out why a Marie Rose sauce with a generous sprinkling of <em>chingri machh</em> is so popular in Calcutta.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his is a cool, refreshing, satisfying prawn cocktail, inspired by the item on the Mocambo menu. It essentially comprises flavourful, juicy prawns (boiled in an aromatic court bouillon), coated with a delicious, sharp, punchy Marie Rose (cocktail) sauce.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 2 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>10 pieces</td>
<td>Prawns (shelled, deveined, beheaded)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 slice</td>
<td>Onion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Half</td>
<td>Lemon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 sprig</td>
<td>Parsley</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 tbsp</td>
<td>Mayonnaise</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 tbsp</td>
<td>Ketchup</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 tsp</td>
<td>Horseradish (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Worcestershire sauce</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 drops</td>
<td>Tabasco sauce</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>Heavy cream</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Paprika (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pinches</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Pepper</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Whiskey or brandy (optional)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Scissors (to clean and devein the prawns)</li>
<li>Saucepan with lid</li>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Whisk</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Refrigerator</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Before you begin, place a clean, empty plate in the freezer to chill.</li>
<li>Start by cleaning and deveining the prawns. We don’t need the heads for this dish, so remove them. You may keep the tails for presentation, but you can also get rid of them if you like.</li>
<li>Now, in a saucepan, add a slice of onion, three slices of lemon, a bay leaf, a sprig of parsley, and ½ tsp of salt. Fill the pot with 4-cm-deep water, cover, and set it to boil. Let everything bubble for 5 minutes. This will form a <em>court bouillon</em>, which is an aromatic poaching liquid.</li>
<li>Add the prawns to this liquid and poach them for no more than 2 minutes. Cooking the prawns for longer than this time will make them chewy. Transfer immediately to the plate we chilled earlier and put it back in the refrigerator to cool.</li>
<li>It’s time now to make the Marie Rose sauce. In a whisking bowl, add the mayonnaise, ketchup, horseradish, worcestershire sauce, tabasco sauce, cream, salt, pepper, paprika, juice of half a lemon, and whiskey. Mix them together till they are well combined.</li>
<li>Add the poached and chilled prawns to the cocktail sauce and fold them in.</li>
<li>Serve chilled, in cocktail glasses, over ice, if possible.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A cool, refreshing, satisfying prawn cocktail recipe, inspired by the item on the menu of Calcutta’s legendary restaurant, Mocambo.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="prawns" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/prawns/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="cocktail" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/cocktail/"/>
    
      <category term="appetizer" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/appetizer/"/>
    
      <category term="mocambo" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mocambo/"/>
    
      <category term="restaurant food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/restaurant-food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kumro’r Jhal</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/kumrar-jhal/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/kumrar-jhal/</id>
    <published>2017-06-02T04:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-30T02:28:19.407Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A light pumpkin curry with coconut, green chillies and nigella seeds</p>

<p class="post-intro">This light yet vibrant curry is probably unlike anything you’ve ever tasted.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span> <a href="/tags/jhal"><em>jhal</em></a> is a type of Bengali curry characterised by the sharpness of its flavours, unlike its close cousin, the <em>jhol</em>, which is usually more mellow. This recipe, <em>kumro’r jhal</em>, is defined by the heat and aroma that comes from freshly crushed green chillies and <em>kaalo jeere</em>. In a way, the green chilli and <em>kaalo jeere</em> combination is a timeless one when it comes to Bengali cooking—these two work hand-in-hand to temper several classic dishes. In this recipe, these are not only used as <em>phoron</em> but they are also pasted and added to the curry itself. Apart from that, this unusual <em>jhal</em> recipe also makes use of coconut paste, some milk, and a pinch of flour, all of which render a light, yet creamy, gravy. This dish is extremely easy to make (it doesn’t require you to spend several minutes sauteing spices) and can be knocked out in under 30 minutes.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong>  25 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Kumro (ripe or green pumpkin or butternut squash)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Pasted coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Saucepan or boiling pot with lid</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder | <em>sheel-nora</em> (to paste coconut)</li>
<li>Mortar and pestle (to crush green chillies and <em>kaalo jeere</em>)</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Peel the pumpkin and cut it into 4-cm-large cubes.</li>
<li>Transfer the cubes to a saucepan. Add 200 g water and 10 g salt. Cover and boil the pumpkin till it is 90 per cent tender. This should take roughly about 10 minutes. Do not drain the water, as we’ll need it later to form the curry.</li>
<li>While the pumpkin is boiling, crush ¼ tsp <em>kaalo jeere</em> and 1 green chilli with a pinch of salt using a <em>sheel-nora</em> or mortar and pestle. <em>Kaalo jeere</em> and green chillies are the main flavours of this dish, so make sure they are freshly crushed.</li>
<li>Also make some coconut paste using a grinder or <em>sheel-nora</em></li>
<li>Now, heat 15 g mustard oil in a pan. Once it starts to smoke lightly and changes colour to a pale yellow, temper it with 2 dried red chillies, 1 bay leaf, 1 green chilli, and ⅛ tsp <em>kalo jeere</em>.</li>
<li>Next, add the boiled pumpkin along with the water.</li>
<li>Then add the pasted coconut and stir it in.</li>
<li>Bubble for a minute before adding the crushed <em>kaalo jeere</em> and green chillies mixture. Also add the sugar at this point.</li>
<li>Mix the <em>maida</em> into the milk, and add the solution to the pan. Let everything boil for about 4 to 5 minutes, so that the <em>maida</em> can help thicken the gravy slightly, before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      An easy, vibrant, light curry of pumpkin infused with the classic combination of flavours of green chillies and nigella seeds.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
      <category term="curry" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/curry/"/>
    
      <category term="jhal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/jhal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Teto’r Dal Lau Diye</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/tetor-dal-lau-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/tetor-dal-lau-diye/</id>
    <published>2017-05-26T04:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-30T02:28:39.086Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">An easy-to-make, mildly bitter <em>moong dal</em> recipe</p>

<p class="post-intro">This nutritious <em>moong dal</em> contains healthy portions of bitter melon (<em>korola</em>) and bottle gourd (<em>lau</em>). But that doesn’t make it any less delicious.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his is a wonderful <em>dal</em> for the spring-summer months. <em>Teto’r dal</em>, or as the <em>Bangals</em> (Bengali immigrants from the eastern part of undivided Bengal) call it, <em>tita’r dal</em>, is light, mellow, and nutritious, to say nothing of delicious. This <em>dal</em> gets its name from the fact that it contains <em>korola</em> or bitter gourd; ‘<em>teto</em>’ literally means bitter.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Moong dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Lau (bottle gourd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Korola (bitter gourd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Shorshe (mustard seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Methi (fenugreek seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Grated coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>13 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Saucepan or boiling pot with lid</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grater or grinder (to grate coconut)</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and rinse the <em>moong dal</em> thoroughly, and boil it with 550 g water till the <em>dal</em> is soft. This should take about 15 minutes.</li>
<li>While the <em>dal</em> is boiling, chop the <em>korola</em> into 5-mm-thick rings. Peel the <em>lau</em> and divide it in 4-cm-large chunks.</li>
<li>Transfer the <em>lau</em> to a saucepan and add just enough water to submerge the <em>lau</em>. With the lid on, steam them on medium heat till they are 90 per cent done. This should take about 10 minutes. Remove them from the water and set aside.</li>
<li>In a <em>kadai</em>, heat 20 g mustard oil till it starts smoking lightly and changes colour to a pale yellow.</li>
<li>Add the <em>korola</em> rings and fry them till they are golden (for about 4 minutes). Remove them from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Now, temper the same oil with the dried red chilli, bay leaf, mustard seeds (<em>shorshe</em>), and fenugreek seeds (<em>methi</em>).</li>
<li>Just as the <em>methi</em> turns reddish in colour, add the grated coconut. Fry it on medium heat for about 2 minutes till it turns light brown.</li>
<li>Now add half of the ginger (that is, 20 g) to the pan, and fry it for a minute or so.</li>
<li>Add in the boiled <em>moong dal</em>, along with salt and sugar.</li>
<li>Once it has come to a boil, add the fried <em>korola</em>, boiled <em>lau</em>, and the remaining 20 g of ginger paste. This will accentuate the gingery flavours of the dish.</li>
<li>Let everything bubble for a good 6 to 7 minutes. By this point the dal should be infused with the flavours of ginger and <em>korola</em>, and the <em>lau</em> should be fully tender.</li>
<li>Add some ghee, stir it in, cover, and let it rest for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/bhaja/"><em>Bhaja</em></a> | <a href="/tags/torkari/"><em>torkari</em></a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
<script type="application/ld+json">
{
  "@context": "http://schema.org/",
  "@type": "Recipe",
  "name": "Plain mosur dal",
  "author": "Bong Eats",
  "image": "https://res.cloudinary.com/dmpeew57x/image/upload/v1478835725/thumbs/plain-mosur-dal_thumbnail_small.jpg",
  "description": "This is one of the simplest dals you can make. It is light and hearty, and goes well with almost any bhaja or torkari. Because it is sparsely spiced, it is a perfect component of a day-to-day meal.",
  "prepTime": "PT10M",
  "totalTime": "PT20M",
  "recipeYield": "5",
  "recipeIngredient": [
    "Mustard oil    15 g",
    "Kaalo jeere    ¼ tsp",
    "Dried red chillies    2 pcs",
    "Green chillies    2 pcs",
    "Bay leaf    1 pc",
    "Turmeric powder    ½ tsp (or 1 g)",
    "Salt    8 g",
    "Water    500 g",
    "Coriander leaves 6 g",
    "Mosur dal    100 g"
  ],
  "recipeInstructions": [
    "1 Rinse the dal well and drain the water",
    "2 Place washed dal in a pressure cooker with 500g water",
    "3 Boil till you see the broken grains of dal. If using a pressure cooker, cook on medium-high heat till you hear the first whistle. Turn off the heat and let the pressure release on its own",
    "4 Whisk the boiled dal till you can no longer see the individual grains",
    "5 Heat up your pan",
    "6 Add mustard oil and allow it to smoke lightly",
    "7 Add kaalo jeere, dried red chillies, green chillies, and bay leaf",
    "8 Add the whisked dal",
    "9 Add turmeric and salt",
    "10 Allow it to boil on medium heat for 4–5 minutes",
    "11 Garnish with the chopped coriander"
   ]
}
</script>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This easy and nutritious moong dal, bittersweet and gingery, contains the goodness of bitter melon (korola) and bottle gourd (lau).
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
      <category term="moong dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/moong-dal/"/>
    
      <category term="teto" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/teto/"/>
    
      <category term="korola" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/korola/"/>
    
      <category term="lau" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/lau/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Panta Bhaat</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/panta-bhat/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/panta-bhat/</id>
    <published>2017-05-19T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-19T02:43:57.462Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Mildly fermented rice</p>

<p class="post-intro">Enjoy this centuries-old recipe with some of our exciting serving suggestions.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">B</span>engal, even today, is largely agrarian. It shares many of the characteristics of other eastern societies that developed around wet rice cultivation—a method that dates back to the Neolithic ages. India is the largest cultivator of paddy in the world, and West Bengal grows most of it. Bangladesh is the fourth largest producer of rice with 75 per cent of its arable land used for paddy cultivation. Suffice to say that rice—not just its consumption, but also its production—defines the Bengali culture more than we realise ourselves.</p>
<p>In this tropical land, summers are harsh. Farmers, labourers, artisans, who go out to work in the the fields carry with them a tiffin box of rice soaked in water, some salt, some green chillies, and a wedge of onion. This rice ferments to form <em>panta bhaat</em>. Sometimes, water is added to the cooked rice at night and had for breakfast. <em>Panta bhaat</em> originated as, and still is, means of sustenance for the poor. Different parts of eastern India have different names for this recipe—in Orissa they call it <em>pakhala</em>, and in Assam <em>poita bhaat</em>.</p>
<p>The fermentation of the rice carbohydrates by good bacteria increases the availability of a lot of micronutrients and minerals in the rice. The table below shows a comparison of available nutrition of 100 grams of cooked rice and <em>panta bhaat</em>:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Minerals</th>
<th>Cooked Rice</th>
<th>Panta Bhaat</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Iron</td>
<td>3.4 mg</td>
<td>73.91 mg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sodium</td>
<td>475 mg</td>
<td>303 mg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Potassium</td>
<td>21 mg</td>
<td>839 mg</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.telegraphindia.com/1110804/jsp/northeast/story_14328967.jsp" target="_blank" rel="external">The Telegraph, 4 August 2011</a></p>
<p>Consumed in summer, <em>panta bhaat</em> supplies probiotic bacteria and plenty of micronutrients that aid digestion. It produces a soporific effect that is conducive to a siesta that Bengalis love.</p>
<p>In spite of its humble origin, <em>panta bhaat</em> is loved and enjoyed by many people, rich and poor. There is no real recipe for <em>panta bhaat</em>. So, these are our serving suggestions based on what our family commonly eats with <em>panta</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 13 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings (75g rice per person)</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><ul>
<li>300g Rice (small-grained, unperfumed, and parboiled)</li>
<li>Potatoes (halved)</li>
<li>Lime or <em>gondhoraj lebu</em></li>
<li>Green chillies</li>
<li>Sliced onions</li>
<li><em>Kasundi</em> (Bengali mustard)</li>
<li>Salt</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Boiling pot</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>The first step in this recipe is boiling the rice. Wash the rice thoroughly and fill your pot with water. As usual, we need at least five times as much water as the rice. For details, check out our video on <a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">how to cook the perfect rice</a>.</li>
<li>In the same pot as the rice, add some peeled and halved potatoes. This is so the potatoes are boiled at the same time as the rice.</li>
<li>Set the pot on the stove and boil the rice for 10 minutes longer than you normally would—for this recipe, we need the rice to be soft and mushy.</li>
<li>Extract the boiled potatoes from the pot. Strain the rice and set it aside to cool completely.</li>
<li>Once the rice is cool, add regular water to the pot. The water level should be about 2 cm over the level of rice.</li>
<li>Using your hands, gently break up the lumps in the rice.</li>
<li>Cover and place the pot in a cool, dark place for 12 hours. This will give the rice a chance to ferment and develop good bacteria.</li>
<li>While eating, take fistsful of rice from the pot and squeeze as much water out of it as possible. Transfer to a serving bowl.</li>
<li>Using your hands, mash the rice thoroughly. Also mash in half a boiled potato along with it.</li>
<li>Add some freshly squeezed lime juice, crushed green chillies, salt, and <em>kasundi</em> to the rice. Mix to combine.</li>
<li>Next, add a couple of ladles of chilled <a href="/recipe/tok-dal-aam-diye/"><em>kacha aam diye tok dal</em></a> and sliced onions, and mix well.</li>
<li>Top off with some of the water in which the rice was fermenting. Mix again.</li>
<li>Serve with fresh coconut slices, onions, fried red chilli, and green chillies. <a href="/tags/bhaja/"><em>Bhajas</em></a> such as <em>alu bhaja</em>, <em>dal’er bora</em>, and <a href="/recipe/rohu-katla-fish-fry/"><em>machh bhaja</em></a> go very well with <em>panta bhaat</em>, as does <a href="/recipe/alu-sheddho/"><em>alu bhorta</em></a> (mashed potatoes with fried onions, garlic, and green chillies).</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Fresh coconut slices</li>
<li>Raw onions</li>
<li>Fried, dried red chilli</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/tok-dal-aam-diye/">Kacha aam diye tok dal</a></li>
<li>Alu bhaja</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/alu-sheddho/">Alu bhorta</a></li>
<li>Dal’er bora</li>
<li><a href="/recipe/rohu-katla-fish-fry/">Machh bhaja</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This recipe involves fermenting cooked rice overnight. Panta bhaat is probiotic, rich in micro-nutrients, and eaten during summer.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
      <category term="rice" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rice/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lau’er Ghonto, with Moong Dal &amp; Bori</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/lau-ghonto-with-moong-dal-bori/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/lau-ghonto-with-moong-dal-bori/</id>
    <published>2017-05-12T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-30T02:28:49.965Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A spicy, dry bottle-gourd curry</p>

<p class="post-intro">This bottle-gourd preparation is mellow, spicy, and nutty, all at the same time.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">L</span><em>au’er <a href="/tags/ghonto/">ghonto</a></em> is a dry, hot-and-spicy curry that is prepared by steaming the bottle gourd in its own juices. This dish benefits from a low-and-slow cooking method, which really helps draw out all the flavours of the <em>lau</em>. The vegetable is to be cut into about 3-mm-wide matchsticks. Larger pieces will not only fail to yield curry of the desired texture, but will also prevent the seasoning and spices from entering the <em>lau</em>. Throughout the cooking process, keep the heat low and the pan covered. Stir occasionally to ensure that the <em>lau</em> doesn’t stick to the pan. In this version of the <em>lau’er ghonto</em>, besides the usual suspects (ginger, cumin powder, <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/"><em>garam masala</em></a>, etc.), we have also added some roasted <em>moong dal</em> and fried <em>dal’er bori</em>. Both of these lend the preparation an amazing nutty undertone, along with a subtle bit of crunch. This dish can be absolutely delightful if prepared right.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>700 g</td>
<td>Lau (bottle gourd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Moong dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Dal’er bori</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Clove</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>16 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Lid for cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Divide the bottle gourd into 6–8 cm segments and remove its skin. Now, cut each segment into slices, 3 mm wide. Then bunch up about 3–4 of the slices at a time, and further cut them into matchsticks, 3 mm wide.</li>
<li>In a small bowl, make a paste by mixing the ginger, turmeric, cumin powder, and 25 g water. Set aside.</li>
<li>In a pan set on medium flame, add the <em>moong dal</em>.</li>
<li>Dry-roast the <em>dal</em>, stirring continuously, till it changes colour to a pinkish-brown. This should take about 4 minutes.</li>
<li>Once the <em>dal</em> is roasted, remove it from the pan, and set aside for later.</li>
<li>To the same pan set on medium heat, add 15 g mustard oil.</li>
<li>Once the oil has started to smoke lightly and changed colour to a pale yellow, add in the <em>dal’er bori</em>.</li>
<li>Fry the <em>boris</em> till they turn golden. Drain from the oil and set aside for later.</li>
<li>Temper the same oil with the dried red chilli, bay leaf, cardamom, cinnamon, clove, and cumin seeds.</li>
<li>Once the whole spices have started crackling, add the ginger-turmeric-cumin paste that we prepared earlier.</li>
<li>Fry the spices till they release oil (about 4 minutes). You may add an additional 25 g water to the pan if the spices turn dry and start to stick to the bottom of the pan.</li>
<li>Once the spices have fried, add in the roasted <em>moong dal</em> and cook everything for 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Then add all the shredded <em>lau</em>, along with the salt. Mix till the vegetable is coated with the spices.</li>
<li>Cover the pan and let the <em>lau</em> steam for a good 20 minutes. During this time, the salt will help draw the moisture from the gourd and soften it. Don’t forget to stir occasionally to ensure that the <em>lau</em> doesn’t stick to the pan.</li>
<li>Once the gourd is soft, add the sugar and slit green chillies. Cover and cook for another 8 minutes.</li>
<li>Break the fried <em>bori</em> into shards and add them to the pan, along with freshly chopped coriander leaves. Cook everything for about 4 minutes before garnishing with <em>ghee</em>.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | roti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This delicious bottle-gourd (lau) preparation is packed with the wonderful flavours of fresh ginger, coriander, and garam masala.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="ghonto" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/ghonto/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
      <category term="lau" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/lau/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Keema’r Doi Bora</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/keemar-doi-bora/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/keemar-doi-bora/</id>
    <published>2017-05-04T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-06-30T02:29:02.525Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Warm minced-meat <em>koftas</em> topped with a generous helping of chilled, spiced yoghurt</p>

<p class="post-intro">The sub-continent’s favourite snack with a deliciously meaty twist.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span>t is impossible to overstate the impact of the Tagore family on the Bengali way of life. Even after two centuries, the Tagores define every aspect of what it means to be a Bengali—be it music, literature, art, philosophy, politics, or food.</p>
<p>Rabindranath grew up in a household with a deep knowledge of ancient Hindu as well as Islamic traditions. He travelled all over the world, imbibing the best aspects of every culture he encountered. He loved collecting menu cards and recipes from dinners and lunches on his travels. He would bring them back to his wife, Mrinalini, and request that the recipes be incorporated into the repertoire of the Tagore kitchen. According to accounts, some of his experiments with food were downright whimsical (pureed-garlic fritters, anyone?)</p>
<p>Indira Devi Chaudhurani (daughter of Satyendranath Tagore) was one of Rabindranath’s favourite nieces. Indira, among many of her achievements, went on to put tunes to close to 200 of her uncle’s songs. She did not herself cook. But she used to collect their household recipes and put them down in a diary. Purnima Devi, another Tagore family decedent, finally put these recipes, and some more of her own, into a book called <em>Thakurbarir Ranna</em>. With Rabindranath’s birth anniversary coming up on 25 <em>Boishak</em> (9 May), and given the bard’s love for <em>kababs</em> of all kinds, we thought of recreating this unusual take on the wildly popular Indian snack, <em>dahi vada</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 12 <em>boras</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE FRITTERS</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Beef or mutton keema (mince)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>85 g</td>
<td>Onions (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/">Shahi garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>90 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (boiled and peeled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g (or half an egg)</td>
<td>Beaten egg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE TOPPING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Mint leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Bhaja masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Ghee (melted)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>Tamarind sauce</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri hata</em> | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPARE THE TOPPING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a bowl, add the yoghurt, chopped mint leaves, bhaja masala, 2 g salt, and 5 g sugar. Beat together till everything is well combined.</li>
<li>Cover and leave it in the refrigerator to chill.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—PREPARE THE KOFTAS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Set a pan on medium heat and add 15 g vegetable oil to it.</li>
<li>Once the oil is hot, add 60 g of the finely chopped onions. Fry till they turn golden in colour (about 5 minutes).</li>
<li>Add 2 green chillies, finely chopped, and fry them for another minute.</li>
<li>Next, add the minced meat. Using your spatula, break up the lumps in the mince.</li>
<li>Stir in 5 g of salt and 1 tsp of <a href="/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/">Shahi garam masala powder</a> powder.</li>
<li>Cover and cook the mince on medium heat, till it is tender, for about 6 minutes (if using beef keema), or 15 minutes (if using mutton keema).</li>
<li>If your mince is particularly fatty, scoop out the excess rendered fat till the keema appears dry.</li>
<li>Transfer the cooked mince to a grinder jar and blitz in short pulses till it is completely smooth. Since the keema is dry, this process might take some time and patience. Scrape down the sides of the jar every so often and pulse again till smooth.</li>
<li>Once the mince is perfectly ground, transfer it to a mixing bowl.</li>
<li>Add the boiled potatoes and mash them in.</li>
<li>Also add half a beaten egg, 2 chopped green chillies, and 25 g chopped onions. Combine everything until you have a dough-like mixture.</li>
<li>Portion the mixture into 12 balls, each weighing 30 g. Press each ball in your fist to compact the ground mince. Then, roll it between your palms to form a smooth, crack-free ball.</li>
<li>In a frying pan, heat vegetable oil, about 4-cm deep.</li>
<li>Fry the balls till they are brown. Since the mince is already cooked, these koftas brown very quickly (in under a minute), so be prepared to extract them from the oil accordingly.</li>
<li>Drain from the oil and set aside.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—ASSEMBLY</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Melt some ghee in the microwave or on the stove. Get the yoghurt mixture out of the fridge.</li>
<li>In individual serving bowls, add the fried koftas. Drizzle some melted ghee on them. Top with generous portions of the beaten yoghurt mixture and a few dollops of tamarind sauce. Garnish with some chopped mint leaves, and serve immediately. (Remember that while serving, the boras should be hot, and the yoghurt, cold.)</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Keema’r doi bora—warm meat koftas topped with chilled yoghurt—is a meaty twist on the beloved Indian snack, the dahi vada.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="beef" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/beef/"/>
    
      <category term="mutton" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mutton/"/>
    
      <category term="rabindranath" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rabindranath/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Tok Dal with Green Mangoes</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/tok-dal-aam-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/tok-dal-aam-diye/</id>
    <published>2017-04-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-21T06:19:13.866Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A sweet and tangy lentil <em>dal</em> containing unripe, green mangoes</p>

<p class="post-intro">This <em>mosur dal</em> is incredibly cooling—perfect for hot summer afternoons.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<blockquote><p>সেই মনে পড়ে, জ্যৈষ্ঠের ঝড়ে রাত্রে নাহিকো ঘুম,<br>অতি ভোরে উঠি তাড়াতাড়ি ছুটি আম কুড়াবার ধুম।</p>
<footer><strong>Rabindranath Tagore</strong></footer></blockquote>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>s spring turns to summer in the lower-Gangetic plains, people start preparing for the oppressive heat of the months to come. Cooling foods slowly start getting incorporated into the diet to combat the rising temperatures. But perhaps nothing signals the arrival of spring in Bengal more than the <em>kalboishakhis</em> (nor’westers)—late-afternoon thunderstorms that are localized to the region. One byproduct of this storm is that it causes a lot of mangoes to prematurely fall off trees. While that is not good news for ardent lovers of this fleshy, tropical fruit, it gives us an opportunity to prepare a rather delightful <em>tok dal</em> out of the unripe, sour, green mangoes.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Mosur dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>650 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Unripe mango</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Mustard seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>38 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pressure cooker | boiling pot</li>
<li><em>Dal’er knaata</em> | balloon whisk</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and rinse the <a href="/tags/mosur-dal/"><em>mosur dal</em></a>, and place it in a pressure cooker or boiling pot, with 650 g water. Boil the <em>dal</em> till it is soft, but not mushy. If using a pressure cooker, boil for one whistle, and then release the steam immediately to stop the lentils from cooking any further.</li>
<li>Peel the unripe mango, and divide it into wedges, 2 cm thick. Reserve the cut pieces in a bowl of water till needed, to prevent the mangoes from oxidizing.</li>
<li>Heat a <em>kadai</em> and add 15 g mustard oil to it.</li>
<li>Temper the oil with the dried red chilli, green chillies, and mustard seeds.</li>
<li>Once the mustard seeds start to crackle, add the mango wedges, followed by about 2 g of salt.</li>
<li>Stir the salt in, cover the pan, and allow the mangoes to cook on low heat for about 5 minutes. The salt will help the mangoes soften. Stir occasionally to prevent the mangoes from sticking to the pan.</li>
<li>Once the mangoes are soft, add the boiled <em>dal</em>, turmeric powder, sugar, and rest of the salt.</li>
<li>Allow everything to bubble on medium heat for about 6 minutes. During this time, the mangoes will release their tartness into the <em>dal</em>.</li>
<li>This dish is sweet and tangy. Depending on the sourness of your mango, mash some of the softened pieces to a pulp and mix them with the dal.</li>
<li>Boil for another 2 minutes before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><p><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | <em>panta bhaat</em><br><a href="/tags/bhaja/"><em>Bhaja</em></a> | <a href="/tags/torkari/"><em>torkari</em></a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This delightful, sweet, tangy masoor dal—containing unripe, green mangoes—is incredibly cooling. Perfect for hot summer afternoons.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Korola Bhaja (in batter)</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/korola-bhaja-in-batter/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/korola-bhaja-in-batter/</id>
    <published>2017-04-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-28T03:40:21.026Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Crispy, batter-fried rings of bitter gourd</p>

<p class="post-intro">A deep-fried food that is also an antioxidant and immunity booster, <em>korola bhaja</em> is simply too good to be true.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span> balanced meal includes elements not just from all food groups, but from all flavour profiles as well—bitter, astringent, sour, salty, sweet, and so on. Bitter foods, in particular, are well-known antioxidants that contain immunity-boosting enzymes. In Bengal, these are generally consumed around springtime, when the weather transitions from chilly to hot and all manner of allergens/viruses are in the air. Over the years, Bengali cooks have devised clever and delicious ways to incorporate bitters in their diet—from fried <em>neem</em> leaves to <em>korola bhaja</em> to <em>shukto</em>.</p>
<p>Today we show you how to prepare <em>korola bhaja</em>—batter-fried rings of bitter gourd—in just 20 minutes. In this recipe, the <em>korola</em> is twice cooked—first steamed and then fried. The batter itself is simple. It is mildly seasoned with some salt, sugar, and green chillies. <em>Nigella seeds</em> provide a subtle fragrance, while <em>posto</em> (poppy) adds crunch. We top it off with a drizzle of raw, pungent mustard oil for crispiness.<br></p>

<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Bitter gourd (1-cm rings)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Maida (all-purpose flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Posto (poppy seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Green chilli (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 250 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for deep-frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Sauce pan | boiling pot (with lid)</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Forks</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri hata</em> | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Divide the <em>korola</em> (bitter gourd) into rings, 1 cm wide.</li>
<li>Transfer to a saucepan and add hot water, just enough to submerge all the rings. With the lid on, steam the <em>korola</em> for about 10 minutes. We don’t want to completely cook the vegetable at this stage. The rings will be deep-fried later on; the steaming will give the cooking process a head-start.</li>
<li>Drain the bitter gourd rings immediately and set aside to cool.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, prepare a batter by mixing the flour, salt, sugar, turmeric, nigella seeds, poppy seeds, green chilli, mustard oil, and water in the given proportions.</li>
<li>Mix the batter till well combined.</li>
<li>Set a kadai on the stove and heat it up. Add vegetable oil to the pan, at least 4 cm deep.</li>
<li>On medium flame, allow the oil to heat up completely. You can check by dropping some batter into the oil, and if it floats to the top immediately, with bubbles all around it, the oil is good to go. Remove the fried batter from the oil before proceeding, though.</li>
<li>Dunk the steamed <em>korola</em> rings in the batter, one at a time, and coat them well.</li>
<li>Gently lower them into the oil. You can fry about 8 to 10 rings at a time, depending on the size of your pan. But be sure not to overcrowd the pan, or they won’t turn out crispy.</li>
<li>Once they are golden-brown, drain the fritters from the oil.</li>
<li>Sprinkle with some rock salt and serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><p><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | <em>panta bhaat</em><br><a href="/tags/dal/"><em>Dal</em></a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The crispy, delicious korola bhaja—or bitter gourd rings dipped in batter and deep-fried till golden—is packed full of nutrients.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
      <category term="teto" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/teto/"/>
    
      <category term="korola" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/korola/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
