<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Bong Eats | Bengali Recipe Videos</title>
  <subtitle>Bong Eats is about food from Bengal. And that&#39;s not just Bengali food.</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://bongeats.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-11T06:21:59.308Z</updated>
  <id>https://bongeats.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Bong Eats</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Rosho-Puli</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/roshopuli/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/roshopuli/</id>
    <published>2019-01-10T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-11T06:21:59.308Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A Bengali winter pithe</p>

<p class="post-intro">Fresh coconut and semolina dumplings in milk.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">R</span>oshopuli is a type of “pithe” (pronounced pi-thay) or “pitha”. In this Bengali sweet recipe coconut and semolina (sooji) dumplings are cooked in milk flavoured with green cardamom. There is a variety of puli pithe that are made in winter in Bengal.</p>
<p><a href="/tags/pithe">Pithe</a> is an umbrella term used to describe a variety of sweets prepared during poush sankranti or the rice-harvest festival in Bengal, using rice, date-palm syrup (patali gur), coconut, milk, and flour.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 2 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>150g</td>
<td>Grated coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75g</td>
<td>Sooji</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.5tsp</td>
<td>Cardamom powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1L</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50g</td>
<td>Micchri</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.25tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Long spatula | <em>khunti</em> (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Heavy-bottom saucepan | Korai</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—MAKE THE PULI</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a heated pan add freshly grated coconut, semolina (suji), sugar and cardamom powder.</li>
<li>Stir the mixture on low heat until the sugar melts and the whole mixture turns sticky and forms a lump. This should take about 8 minutes.</li>
<li>Transfer the mixture on to a plate and allow it to cool—just enough to handle safely.</li>
<li>While still hot, divide the mixture into 8 gram portions.</li>
<li>Working quikly roll each portion into a round ball, then roll in a single direction to form an oval shape.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—COOK THE PULI</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Meanwhile heat milk in a pan. Once it comes to a boil, let it simmer for ten minutes.</li>
<li>Add a quarter of the total mishri now.</li>
<li>Add the salt. Don’t skip the salt, it balances the sweetness.</li>
<li>Add the puli now. Cook for five minutes while stirring gently and scraping the sides and bottom of the pan.</li>
<li>You will see that the puli will start floating to the surface. Cut into a puli and taste it to see if it has cooked all the way through to the centre.</li>
<li>Now, add the rest of the mishri.</li>
<li>Continue reducing the milk until it reaches a sauce like consistency—about 10 more minutes.</li>
<li>Serve while slightly warm.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Related-Recipes"><a href="#Related-Recipes" class="headerlink" title="Related Recipes"></a>Related Recipes</h2><ul>
<li><a href="recipe/patishapta-with-kheer-filling/">Patishapta</a></li>
<li><a href="recipe/nolen-gurer-payesh/">Nolen Gur’er Payesh</a></li>
<li><a href="recipe/lobongo-lotika/">Lobongo Lotika</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Fresh coconut and semolina dumplings in milk—a Bengali dessert winter dessert (pitha)
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="sweets" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/sweets/"/>
    
      <category term="pithe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pithe/"/>
    
      <category term="jolkhabar" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/jolkhabar/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Chocolate Cake</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/chocolate-cake/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/chocolate-cake/</id>
    <published>2018-12-20T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-12-21T05:28:37.034Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A chocolate cake for the ages</p>

<p class="post-intro">Rich, moist, tender chocolate cake with a silky dark chocolate ganache—classic!</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>s we bring the 2018 Christmas celebrations on this channel to a close, we leave you with a perfect dessert to ring in the new year. Our rich chocolate cake is constructed in two tiers. The sponge is moist and delicate, and melts in your mouth. Sandwiched between the sponges and smothered around them is a silky, decadent dark-chocolate ganache. This is a cake for birthdays and special occasions. But let’s be real, you (and we) would eat this any day of the week.</p>
<p>The tender crumb structure of the sponges comes largely from emulsifying the fat in the other liquids. Also unusual is this recipe’s use of boiling hot water, which apart from reducing gluten (which tends to make cakes chewy) also helps with the emulsion. Here, we’d be remiss if we didn’t credit <a href="https://www.chefsteps.com/activities/ultimate-chocolate-cake" target="_blank" rel="external">ChefSteps’ chocolate cake recipe</a>. Can’t thank them enough for turning us on to the hot-water technique. We’ve made several chocolate cakes in our day, and this was by far the best we’ve had.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hours 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 1 cake (12 servings)</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE SPONGES</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>225 g</td>
<td>All-purpose flour (maida)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Cocoa powder (we’re using dutch-processed; you can use any)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Baking powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Instant coffee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Baking soda</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Eggs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Vanilla extract</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>180 g</td>
<td>Melted butter (salted; if using unsalted, increase sat to 7g)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt (skip if using regular cocoa powder; replace with milk)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Boiling hot water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE GANACHE</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Dark chocolate (70% cocoa solids)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>350 g</td>
<td>Heavy cream (at least 30% milk fat)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Vanilla</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Two 9-inch round baking tins</li>
<li>Baking paper</li>
<li>Balloon whisk</li>
<li>Mixing bowls</li>
<li>Saucepan</li>
<li>Offset spatula (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Weighing scale</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><h3 id="Making-the-cake"><a href="#Making-the-cake" class="headerlink" title="Making the cake"></a>Making the cake</h3><ol>
<li>Line two round cake tins with baking paper after greasing them well with cold butter.</li>
<li>Dust the sides of the tins with cocoa. Pre-heat your oven to 150 degrees Celcius.</li>
<li>Sift together all the dry ingredients—flour, cocoa powder, baking powder, baking soda, instant coffee powder, salt and powdered sugar.</li>
<li>Whisk 3 eggs in a separate bowl.</li>
<li>Whisk as you pour the melted butter into the egg.</li>
<li>Add the yoghurt and whisk until smooth.</li>
<li>Add the milk and mix.</li>
<li>Add the wet mixture into the dry mixture and roughly mix. Don’t try to smoothen this now.</li>
<li>Add the boiling water and quickly whisk into a smooth velvety batter.</li>
<li>Divide the batter into the cake tins—roughly 650g of batter in each.</li>
<li>Bake for 40 minutes until a probe inserted into the center comes clean or an instant read thermometer registers 95 degree Celcius.</li>
<li>Cool the cakes completely in the tin.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="Making-the-ganache"><a href="#Making-the-ganache" class="headerlink" title="Making the ganache"></a>Making the ganache</h3><ol>
<li>Heat the heavy cream in a saucepan until hot. It should not simmer or boil.</li>
<li>Chop good quality eating chocolate into fine and even pieces and place in a bowl.</li>
<li>Pour the hot cream over the chocolate shards. Allow this to sit for five minutes.</li>
<li>Use a spatula to stir this into a silky ganache.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="Decorating-the-chocolate-cake"><a href="#Decorating-the-chocolate-cake" class="headerlink" title="Decorating the chocolate cake"></a>Decorating the chocolate cake</h3><ol>
<li>On a rotating cake stand overturn one of the cakes. The flat bottom of the cake should be facing upwards.</li>
<li>Pour some ganache and form a thin layer. Place the second cake, upside down on the top of the first cake.</li>
<li>Pour the rest of the ganache on top and coat all over.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Related-recipes"><a href="#Related-recipes" class="headerlink" title="Related recipes"></a>Related recipes</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Christmas cake</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/mishti-polao/">Old fashioned steamed pudding with tea-infused custard</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Rich, moist, tender chocolate cake with a silky dark chocolate ganache—classic!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="dessert" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dessert/"/>
    
      <category term="pudding" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pudding/"/>
    
      <category term="christmas" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/christmas/"/>
    
      <category term="bake" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bake/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pork Vindaloo</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/vindaloo/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/vindaloo/</id>
    <published>2018-12-06T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-12-07T06:05:58.047Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Vinho de Alhos to Vindaloo</p>

<p class="post-intro">Hot-sour-spicy Portuguese-Goan recipe of slow-cooked pork with spices, vinegar and garlic.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">V</span>indaloo was born in Goa sometime in the 16th or 17th century after the Portuguese set up colony there. The word vindaloo comes from the Portuguese recipe ‘vino de alhos’ where ‘vino’ refers to (wine) vinegar and ‘alho’ is the word for garlic. Vindaloo is a fusion of Portuguese, Goan and South Indian ingredients and cooking. </p>
<p>This particular recipe comes from the book ‘<a href="https://www.amazon.in/dp/0099437864?tag=bongeats0c-21" target="_blank" rel="external">Curry: A Tale of Cooks and Conquerers</a>‘ by Lizzie Collingham. The book, besides being one of the best writings on Indian food history, has some fantastic recipes such as this one. We looked at a lot of recipes, both online and in books, but honestly this recipe of vindaloo—though a little more elaborate in the number of spices—is in our opinion one of the best.</p>
<p>Considering just how good this vindaloo tastes, it is really easy to make if you have all the ingredients. While the original recipe used pork, you can use duck instead of pork too.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 3 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Pork shoulder</td>
<td>1000</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR SPICE MIX</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
<td>5g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Whole cumin</td>
<td>10g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Poppy seeds</td>
<td>5g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cloves</td>
<td>3g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Black pepper</td>
<td>3g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Whole mustard</td>
<td>5g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR MARINADE</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Garlic</td>
<td>20g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ginger</td>
<td>20g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Fresh red chillies</td>
<td>5g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tamarind pulp</td>
<td>10g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Palm vinegar</td>
<td>50g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Salt</td>
<td>27g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR COOKING</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Oil</td>
<td>30g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cinnamom stick</td>
<td>4cm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mustard seeds</td>
<td>½ tsp</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Onions</td>
<td>300g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Turmeric</td>
<td>3g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli</td>
<td>5g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Jaggery</td>
<td>10g</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Curry leaves</td>
<td>1 sprig</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Water</td>
<td>425g</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Korai/wok</li>
<li>Knife</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Weighing scale</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><h3 id="Making-the-pudding"><a href="#Making-the-pudding" class="headerlink" title="Making the pudding"></a>Making the pudding</h3><ol>
<li>To create the vindaloo spice mix, dry roast Dried red chillies whole cumin, poppy seeds, cloves, black pepper, and whole mustard and grind them into a powder.</li>
<li>Next, grind together garlic, ginger, fresh red chillies, tamarind pulp, palm vinegar, and salt to form a slurry.</li>
<li>Cut the pork shoulder into 4-cm pieces.</li>
<li>Marinate the pork with the dry spice mixture and the marinade slurry and leave it overnight in the fridge.</li>
<li>The next day heat mustard oil in a pan until smoking.</li>
<li>Temper with a stick of cinnmon and mustard seeds.</li>
<li>Add the sliced onions and fry them until brown, about 15 minutes.</li>
<li>Grind fresh ginger with twice the weight of water. You will need 50 grams of this paste for this recipe.</li>
<li>Tilt the pan to let the oil pool on one side. In the oil fry the turmeric and the kashmiri red chilli powder until bright red. Stire to mix it back with the onions.</li>
<li>Now add the marinated pork and fry on high for 10 minutes to brown the meat.</li>
<li>Now turn the heat to medium, cover and cook for 20 minutes. The pork will start releasing juices.</li>
<li>Chop jaggery and add it to the pan.</li>
<li>Once you are happy with the colour of the sauce, add water (about 425g). (At this point you could also cook it in a pressure cooker to cook it faster. The flavour won’t quite be the same.) Cover and cook on medium until the pork is soft but still retains a bite.</li>
<li>Once the meat is cooked and the consistency of the sauce is to your liking add the curry leaves, cover with a lid, and turn off the heat.</li>
<li>Once cool, put the vindaloo in the refrigerator. Vindaloo is almost like a pickle. Like any braised dish it gets better with time. Plan to make this at least a day ahead so that meat has the chance to soak in everything. Serve with <a href="/">plain white rice</a> or yellow rice.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li>Yellow rice</li>
<li>Fresh salad</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Hot-sour-spicy Portuguese-Goan recipe of slow-cooked pork with spices, vinegar and garlic
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="anglo indian recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/anglo-indian-recipe/"/>
    
      <category term="christmas" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/christmas/"/>
    
      <category term="pork" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pork/"/>
    
      <category term="slow-cooked" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/slow-cooked/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Steamed Carrot &amp; Ginger Pudding</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/steamed-carrot-ginger-pudding/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/steamed-carrot-ginger-pudding/</id>
    <published>2018-11-29T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-12-07T04:00:31.336Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">An old fashioned pudding, with tea-custard sauce</p>

<p class="post-intro">Anglo-Indian steamed cake with ginger, served with a tea-infused crème anglaise. Perfect for the colder months.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">S</span>teamed puddings are old-fashioned desserts that were common in England before households had reliable ovens. Steamed puddings lie somewhere in the middle of the cake–pudding continuum—neither as light and airy as a cake, nor as silky and moist as a modern pudding. We loved its unique texture when we tried it! This recipe is based on the original recipe in the book ‘<a href="https://www.amazon.in/dp/0140271376?tag=bongeats0c-21" target="_blank" rel="external">Anglo-Indian Food and Customs</a>‘ by Patricia Brown. We turned what was originally a carrot steamed pudding into a ginger pudding by adding ginger—both paste and candied. We also changed the proportions to match the sweetness and the texture that we wanted.</p>
<p>Steamed puddings are commonly served with a custard sauce—crème anglaise—which we decided to infuse with tea. The idea of a ginger pudding with a tea sauce sounded perfect, and to our surprise it really works!</p>
<p>Steamed puddings are traditionally made in pudding basins, which are made of metal or ceramic. Some have lids and some—like the one we are using—need to be covered with a foil and baking paper with a pleat that allows the pudding to expand. It also has a lip which lets you tie a string around it and create a sling with which the pudding pot can be safely lowered into and retrieved from the pot of boiling water. </p>
<p>If you enjoy the history of food and are not afraid to try something new you should try this recipe. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 3 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 1 pudding (6 servings)</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR PUDDING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>115 g</td>
<td>Salted butter (softened)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>175 g</td>
<td>Brown sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Eggs</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 large</td>
<td>Lemons (juice of 1, zest of 2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Gorom moshla</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Fresh ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>120 g</td>
<td>Plain flour (maida)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Baking soda</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Baking powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Carrot (grated)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Candied ginger (5mm pieces)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE TEA CUSTARD</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ginger (sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Tea</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3</td>
<td>Egg yolks</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Heavy cream</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ cup</td>
<td>Brandy (optional; for flambé)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pudding basin or a thick ceramic bowl</li>
<li>Cotton twine</li>
<li>Aluminium foil</li>
<li>Baking paper</li>
<li>Balloon whisk</li>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Frying pan</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Weighing scale</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><h3 id="Making-the-pudding"><a href="#Making-the-pudding" class="headerlink" title="Making the pudding"></a>Making the pudding</h3><ol>
<li>Grease the pudding dish with butter.</li>
<li>Using a foil and a baking paper create the lid for the pudding basin. Don’t forget to create a pleat to allow the pudding to rise. Follow the video to see how. Grease the bottom side (the baking paper) with butter.</li>
<li>Cut a baking paper to the shape of the bottom of your pudding basin. Line your pudding mould with the paper.</li>
<li>Sift together the plain flour (maida), baking soda, baking powder, and salt in a mixing bowl.</li>
<li>Zest the two large lemons. Don’t get to the white pith—it is bitter!</li>
<li>Peel and grate the carrots.</li>
<li>Chop the candied ginger into small 5mm pieces.</li>
<li>Grind fresh ginger with twice the weight of water. You will need 50 grams of this paste for this recipe.</li>
<li>In another mixing bowl whisk the room-temperature butter till it is soft.</li>
<li>Add the brown sugar and whisk until pale and airy.</li>
<li>Whisk in three eggs one at a time, taking care to mix one in thoroughly before adding the next.</li>
<li>Now add the flavouring agents—lemon zest, gorom moshla, and ginger paste to the mixture.</li>
<li>Squeeze the juice of one large lemon into the mix and whisk everything together. Now put the whisk away. We won’t be using it anymore.</li>
<li>Bring a kettle of water to boil. We will need this water to steam the pudding.</li>
<li>Next add the dry-ingredients mixture, grated carrots, and candied ginger to the wet mixture. Fold gently with a spatula to mix everything evenly. Don’t over-mix so as to not develop too much gluten.</li>
<li>The pudding batter can now be poured into the buttered and lined mould.</li>
<li>Cover the pudding basin with the pleated foil-baking paper lid. Tie a strong cotton twine all around below the lip of the basin. Now use another twine to create a sling. Watch the video to see how this is done.</li>
<li>Pour the boiling water into a large pot placed on the stove. Lower the pudding basin into the boiling water using the sling for safety. Pour more boiling water into the pot to bring the water upto two-third of the height of the basin.</li>
<li>Cover with a fitted lid and let this simmer on the stovetop. Make sure to refill with more water if the water level goes down a lot.</li>
<li>After 1 hour 45 minutes take out the pudding basin using the sling. Uncover the lid and let it cool for two hours. Serve while still a little warm.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Anglo-Indian steamed cake with ginger, served with a tea-infused crème anglaise. Perfect for the colder months.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="anglo indian recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/anglo-indian-recipe/"/>
    
      <category term="dessert" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dessert/"/>
    
      <category term="pudding" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pudding/"/>
    
      <category term="christmas" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/christmas/"/>
    
      <category term="steamed" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/steamed/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Phuchka Papri, Alu and Jol at Home</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/phuchka/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/phuchka/</id>
    <published>2018-09-07T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-09-07T09:03:40.103Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Eaten all over India, this version is unique to Bengal</p>

<p class="post-intro">Phuchka is arguably the spiciest and most delicious version of pani puri, golgappa, or gupchups</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">P</span>huchka is a way of life in Calcutta. Everyone has their favourite phuchkawala (phuchka seller). Every para (neighbourhood) must have at least a few phuchkawalas who set up their stalls around four in the afternoon everyday. They bring their already fried phuchka papri or puris in huge bags and arrange them neatly in a huge wicker basket or a glass box. Then they start preparing their mis en place and mixing the tawk jol (sour water). By the time they are done, customers start gathering around them and the day’s business starts.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="What-is-Papad-Khar"><a href="#What-is-Papad-Khar" class="headerlink" title="What is Papad Khar?"></a>What is Papad Khar?</h2><p>Papad Khar (or Saji khar) is an alkaline salt made up of Sodium Carbonate (Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>) and Sodium Bicarbonate(NaHCO<sub>3</sub>). The baking powder along with the Papad Khar help expand the papri when they are fried.</p>
<p>Sodium Bicarbonate is commonly sold as baking or cooking soda in grocery stores. Sodium carbonate is known as soda ash. You should be able to find Papad Khar in any big local grocery store in Calcutta.</p>
<h2 id="How-can-I-make-papad-khar-at-home"><a href="#How-can-I-make-papad-khar-at-home" class="headerlink" title="How can I make papad khar at home?"></a>How can I make papad khar at home?</h2><p>To make a substitute for papad khar at home, you need to start with baking soda (sodium bicarbonate). Papad khar is a mixture of Sodium Carbonate and Sodium Bicarbonate in a 2:1 ratio by weight. </p>
<h3 id="Step-1-Make-Sodium-Carbonate"><a href="#Step-1-Make-Sodium-Carbonate" class="headerlink" title="Step 1: Make Sodium Carbonate"></a>Step 1: Make Sodium Carbonate</h3><p>You can make sodium carbonate by simply heating sodium bicarbonate either in an oven or in a pot. When heated sodium bicarbonate releases water (vapour) and carbondioxide to turn into more alkaline sodium carbonate.</p>
<p>2 NaHCO<sub>3</sub> =&gt; Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> + H<sub>2</sub>O + CO<sub>2</sub></p>
<h3 id="Step-2-Mix"><a href="#Step-2-Mix" class="headerlink" title="Step 2: Mix"></a>Step 2: Mix</h3><p>Using a weighing scale mix Sodium carbonate and bicarbonate in 2:1 ratio by weight. Now you have Papad khar.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Immensely popular Calcutta street food of hollow crunchy whole-wheat balls filled with spicy potatoes and sour tamarind water
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="Calcutta-style food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Calcutta-style-food/"/>
    
      <category term="street food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/street-food/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>South Indian Filter Coffee</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/coffee/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/coffee/</id>
    <published>2018-07-12T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-13T04:59:08.439Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A strong coffee</p>

<p class="post-intro">Strong South Indian coffee that’s made from a blend of coffee and chicory.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he list below is compiled mostly with help from friends and fellow coffee lovers and are merely suggestive. Feel free to buy your coffee from wherever you like.</p>
<h2 id="Looking-to-buy-coffee-grounds-beans"><a href="#Looking-to-buy-coffee-grounds-beans" class="headerlink" title="Looking to buy coffee grounds/beans?"></a>Looking to buy coffee grounds/beans?</h2><h3 id="Stores-in-Calcutta-that-sell-coffee"><a href="#Stores-in-Calcutta-that-sell-coffee" class="headerlink" title="Stores in Calcutta that sell coffee"></a>Stores in Calcutta that sell coffee</h3><ol>
<li><p>If you are planning to buy coffee bean grounds in Calcutta, your best bet is to check out the South Indian grocery stores in the Lake Market—Rashbehari Avenue area. <a href="https://lbb.in/kolkata/eat-shop-drink-lake-market-kolkatas-mini-south-india/" target="_blank" rel="external">This LBB Kolkata article has compiled a nice list of stores</a> along with their Google Maps locations. This should get you started. Try out a few shops and a few different blends to see what you like best.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Another option is to buy coffee from Cafe Coffee Day. CCD is also a brand from South India, but their pricings are on the higher side. Some of their blends are great and it will still be cheaper than ordering online.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Look for a blend of Peaberry (PB) and Plantation-A coffee beans. If you plan to make filter coffee it is traditionally a mix of coffee and chicory (80:20 is ideal).</p>
<h3 id="Online-stores-that-deliver-coffee"><a href="#Online-stores-that-deliver-coffee" class="headerlink" title="Online stores that deliver coffee"></a>Online stores that deliver coffee</h3><p>If you want to try out some of the newer online sellers, take a look at the ones below. Bear in mind that online coffee prices can be more expensive especially when you take the delivery charges into account.</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://bluetokaicoffee.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Blue Tokai</a>—this according to most is one of the best options.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.devans.in/" target="_blank" rel="external">Devan’s</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.leocoffee.co.in/" target="_blank" rel="external">Leo Coffee</a>—traditional South Indian brand</li>
<li><a href="https://theindianbean.com/" target="_blank" rel="external">Indian Bean</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.cothas.com/products" target="_blank" rel="external">Cotha’s Coffee</a>—traditional South Indian brand</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Looking-for-a-coffee-filter-or-coffee-glasses-and-dabara"><a href="#Looking-for-a-coffee-filter-or-coffee-glasses-and-dabara" class="headerlink" title="Looking for a coffee filter or coffee glasses and dabara?"></a>Looking for a coffee filter or coffee glasses and dabara?</h2><p><strong>Click below</strong> to see a list of coffee filters in different sizes, coffee glasses with dabara (the bowl that the coffee glass is served in), coffee grinders, etc. These are affiliate links, meaning if you buy from Amazon using these links, we will earn a small commission. This goes towards running Bong Eats. Thanks!</p>
<iframe src="https://kit.com/embed?url=https%3A%2F%2Fkit.com%2Fbongeats%2Findian-filter-coffee-equipments" style="display: block; border: 0px; margin: 0 auto; width: 100%; height: 100vw; max-width: 700px; max-height: 700px" scrolling="no"></iframe>

]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A strong filter kaapi made from a blend of coffee and chicory brewed in a South Indian coffee filter.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="coffee" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/coffee/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ilish Bhaja</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-bhaja/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-bhaja/</id>
    <published>2018-07-05T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T03:27:22.729Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Ilish—deep-fried</p>

<p class="post-intro">Bengali’s favourite hilsa deep-fried in mustard oil until crunchy and sizzling. Serve this with a drizzle of the oil and green chillies.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span>lish Bhaja is Ilish in its simplest form. Bengalis love their fried fish, but very few things come close to the fatty Hilsa seasoned with just salt and turmeric, then fried in mustard oil until crunchy. The mustard oil gets flavoured with the rendered fat from the fish, and is then drizzled on top of steaming white rice and served alongside the ilish with some salt and hot green chillies.</p>
<p>Something like this does not really need a recipe, yet, no document on Bengali food would be complete without the simple joys of life like this one. Yes, we love our Ilish Paturi, Ilish Bhapa, Ilish Tel Jhol with Brinjal, but Ilish Bhaja has a place of its own in the heart of a Bengali.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 15 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 2 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2 pc</td>
<td>Ilish or hilsa steaks 3cm thick</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 cm deep</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Small frying kadai/wok</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Coat the ilish steaks with salt and turmeric and massage to cover the cavities well.</li>
<li>Heat a kadai with 2 cm deep mustard oil. Wait till the oil starts smoking and changes colour to pale yellow and the smell of the raw oil goes away. Use a small kadai to avoid using too much oil. The oil gets flavoured with the fat rendered from the fish. Too much oil will lead to flavourless oil.</li>
<li>Reduce the flame now and wait for the oil to stop smoking. Now add the fish pieces carefully.</li>
<li>Fry each side until brown. Unlike for jhol (curry) where ilish is lightly fried, for bhaja (fry) the fish must be crisp and golden.</li>
<li>Optionally, add a couple of green chillies towards the end to flavour the oil and the fish. </li>
<li>Drain the fish and serve hot with steaming hot rice, green chillies and salt. Drizzle a tablespoon of the frying oil on top of the rice. </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Bengali&#39;s favourite hilsa deep-fried in mustard oil until crunchy and sizzling. Serve this with a drizzle of the oil and green chillies.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="hilsa" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/hilsa/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ilish Bhapa</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-bhapa/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/ilish-bhapa/</id>
    <published>2018-06-28T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T03:05:27.710Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Hilsa fish steamed in mustard sauce</p>

<p class="post-intro">This prized Bengali recipe for hilsa steamed in mustard sauce looks gorgeous, but cooks quickly. Perfect for dazzling guests!</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span>lish bhaape, also known as Shorshe lish bhapa (or bhaape) meaning steamed mustard hilsa, is a Bengali recipe of hilsa fish (a type of shad) steamed in a potent mustard, doi (yoghurt) and coconut paste. Even though it looks very polished, it is a fairly easy recipe to execute, requiring few ingredients, no special technique, and very little time. </p>
<p>It is especially convenient for entertaining guests. You can keep everything ready in a tiffin box, and just as the guests are sitting down for the first course you can put the container to steam. It will be ready by the time the guests are finishing the vegetable courses. You can then bring this to the table and open the lid to reveal the beautiful steaming hilsa while your guests are suitably excited and impressed.</p>
<p><hr><br>Ilish or hilsa is, however, facing extinction due to high demand and overfishing. While policy initiatives between India and Bangladesh are underway to tackle this alarming situation (hilsa conservation depends a great deal on water flow in the Padma-Meghna and Hooghly-Bhagirathi river systems), we can do our bit too.</p>
<p><hr><br><strong>How can you help?</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Don’t to buy any hilsa that is under 500 g / 25 cm. Catching of hilsa before the spawning stage is detrimental to the progression of the next generation.</li>
<li>It is equally important also to not buy hilsa during the breeding season (especially October to November, but even better, until March).<br><hr><br>In 2016, Bangaldesh was able to increase its hilsa yield by 50 per cent by putting measures in place to ban fishing in the breeding season. It also laid down and imposed specifications for net size to prevent the catching of juvenile hilsa. There is a need to create more consciousness about the importance of conserving a fish that is perhaps Bengal’s greatest cultural icon.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Sources:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://cmsdata.iucn.org/downloads/iucn_hilsa_study.pdf" target="_blank" rel="external">http://cmsdata.iucn.org/downloads/iucn_hilsa_study.pdf</a></li>
<li><a href="https://scroll.in/article/806667/how-king-hilsa-made-a-comeback" target="_blank" rel="external">https://scroll.in/article/806667/how-king-hilsa-made-a-comeback</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/news-ians/india-bangladesh-seek-to-save-the-delectable-hilsa-113062700390_1.html" target="_blank" rel="external">http://www.business-standard.com/article/news-ians/india-bangladesh-seek-to-save-the-delectable-hilsa-113062700390_1.html</a> </li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 300 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>250 g (or 4 pcs)</td>
<td>Ilish machh (hilsa fish, 3-cm-thick pieces)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Mustard seeds (brown + yellow mixed, soaked for 2 hours)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Coconut (peeled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt (beaten)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>22 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | large pot or pan (with lid)</li>
<li>Steel tiffin box with tight-fitting lid</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak mustard seeds in water for 2 hours.</li>
<li>Clean the <em>ilish machh</em> and cut it in 3-cm thick slices. Ilish bhaape is best made with thick slices of fish. Fish without roe (eggs) is fattier and, therefore, ideal for this recipe. If your fish has eggs, remove them, as they may not cook fully when steamed. You can add them to your bhaja (fry) or jhol (curry).</li>
<li>Drain the mustard seeds of the water they’ve been soaking in and add them to a grinder jar. Add 4 green chillies, roughly chopped, along with the salt and 100g water. Grinding green chillies with the mustard ensures that it doesn’t turn bitter. </li>
<li>Grind these to a fine paste. Take your time with this process. Scrape down the sides of the jar and grind as many times as it takes to form the smoothest possible paste. The finer the grind, the better the flavours.</li>
<li>Now, add the peeled and chopped coconut to the grinder jar. Grind once again until the coconut has broken down completely. </li>
<li>Transfer this paste to a steel tiffin box. Add beaten yoghurt, sugar, turmeric, and mustard oil. Mix until the oil is fully incorporated. </li>
<li>Now add the fish, one piece at a time, and coat it with the spices. Use your hands to make sure every part of the fish, including its cavities, is well coated. </li>
<li>Slit four more green chillies and place them on the ilish pieces.</li>
<li>Fasten the lid of your tiffin box (you could also seal the top with thick aluminium foil) and set the fish aside to marinate for 15 minutes.</li>
<li>Heat up your pan and place a stand at the bottom. Pour hot water, making sure it doesn’t reach up to more than half the height of your tiffin box, or there’s a danger of water seeping in. Once the water has come to a boil, place the tiffin on the stand. Cover the pan and steam on medium heat for 15 minutes. </li>
<li>Remove from the pan and allow it to rest for another 5 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/mishti-polao/">Polao</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This prized Bengali recipe for hilsa steamed in mustard sauce looks gorgeous, but cooks quickly. Perfect for dazzling guests!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="mustard" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mustard/"/>
    
      <category term="hilsa" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/hilsa/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Chilli Chicken—Calcutta-style</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/chilli-chicken/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/chilli-chicken/</id>
    <published>2018-06-22T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T03:59:10.476Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Crunchy fried chicken in a hot-sour sauce</p>

<p class="post-intro">The secret technique to the crunchiest chilli chicken in a hot, sour and mildly sweet sauce. If you have been missing Calcutta’s Tangra chilli chicken, this is the recipe for you!</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">C</span>hilli chicken is perhaps the most popular Indo-Chinese dish found both in restaurants and street side stalls. No visit to Calcutta’s Chinatowns (especially Tangra) is complete without an order of chilli chicken. The dry chilli chicken works as a snack, appetiser as well as a side. The gravy chilli chicken is more popular as a side to either chowmein or with fried rice. There are various versions of the chilli chicken recipes. While you can play around with the sauces you like in your chilli chicken, most folks will agree that the best chilli chicken has the chicken still crispy when served. With that goal in mind we tested both the wet batter as well as the dry breading technique and finally went with breading. What yielded the crunchiest chicken was Kenji Lopez-Alt’s method which he had used in his <a href="https://www.seriouseats.com/2014/04/the-food-lab-bringing-home-general-tsos-chick.html" target="_blank" rel="external">General Tso’s Chicken recipe in Serious Eats Food Lab</a>. Do give this a try and let us know how it goes!</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Boneless chicken thigh (3-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE MARINADE</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Egg white of half and egg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Dark soy sauce</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Chinese cooking wine (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Garlic paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Pepper</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Baking soda</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 g</td>
<td>Cornflour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR BREADING THE CHICKEN</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ cup (30 g)</td>
<td>Cornflour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ cup (30 g)</td>
<td>All-purpose flour (maida)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Baking powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE SAUCE</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Onions (3-cm squares)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Capsicum (3-cm squares)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ginger (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Garlic (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Green chillies (2-mm thick, cut on the bias)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Dark soy sauce</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Light soy sauce</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Chinese cooking wine (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Vinegar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Tomato ketchup</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Red chilli sauce</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Chicken stock (or water)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>MSG</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Ground pepper</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3-cm deep, ~200 g</td>
<td>Oil for frying</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | wok</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/">Fried rice</a></li>
<li>Roomali rooti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The secret to the crunchiest chilli chicken—and a hot and sour sauce that takes you back to the restaurants of Calcutta&#39;s Chinatown.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="potato" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/potato/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="sheddho" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/sheddho/"/>
    
      <category term="bhorta" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhorta/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Doodh Potol</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/doodh-potol/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/doodh-potol/</id>
    <published>2018-06-14T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T02:22:40.488Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A creamy, delicate, small <em>potol</em> curry</p>

<p class="post-intro">A deceptively simple Bengali recipe of small potols (pointed gourds) stewed in a milk-based sauce. Don’t try this recipe with big potols. It won’t taste very good.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">D</span>oodh potol–this delightful Bengali niramish potol (pointed gourd or parwal) recipe is simple, quick, and tastes unbelievably good for the amount of time and effort it takes. It is a summer speciality as potol are in season. Doodh potol is made with ‘kochi’ potol or baby potol that do not yet have hard seeds. The vegetable soaks up the curry and becomes soft and juicy. Each potol, when eaten, bursts in your mouth releasing the delicate curry. Do not try and recreate this potol recipe using larger potol—it will not taste very good. This preparation is creamy yet light, and looks incredibly special even though can be put together in less than 30 minutes. A must-have during the summer months.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 88 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Small, <em>kochi</em> potol (pointed gourd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Hot milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | wok | cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khhunti</em> | large stirring spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Peel the potol entirely. Even though our other potol recipes call for removing peels in alternating strips, for this recipe, we want the potol fully peeled so that it soaks up the curry and becomes juicy. Once peeled, make shallow slits on both ends to allow juices to enter the potol.</li>
<li>Heat vegetable oil in a pan. Fry the potol on medium-high heat for about 8 minutes or until the potol turn golden. Remove from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Temper the same oil with cardamom, cloves, and cinnamon. Add cumin powder and turmeric, and fry these spices for about 15 seconds. Take care not to burn them. </li>
<li>Add the peeled potol back to the pan and fry them with the spices on medium heat for about 4 minutes.</li>
<li>Add hot milk to the pan, followed by salt and sugar. Bubble everything on medium heat for 6 minutes until the potol are tender. </li>
<li>When the potol have become soft and juicy, and the milk has reduced to a creamy sauce, add ghee. Turn off the heat and rest for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A deceptively simple Bengali recipe of small potols (pointed gourds) stewed in a milk-based sauce.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
      <category term="potol" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/potol/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Phirni—Calcutta-style</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/phirni/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/phirni/</id>
    <published>2018-06-07T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T02:08:13.130Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Creamy, mildly sweet, set rice pudding</p>

<p class="post-intro">In Calcutta no Mughlai meal is complete without a chilled phirni set in a <em>bhnaar</em> (earthen bowl). Plan ahead since phirni has to be set for 24 hours. </p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">D</span>ifferent parts of India have their own types of phirni—Punjabi phirni and Kashmiri phirni are especially well known. This particular style of phirni is popular in Mughlai eateries in Calcutta. No biryani meal is complete without phirni for dessert.</p>
<p>After testing various proportions of rice to milk, milk to sugar, as well as testing with different types of rice, we have finally settled on a phirni recipe that is quick and easy to make, but tastes exactly like the phirni we have eaten in our favourite Mughlai eateries in Calcutta such as Aminia, Arsalan, Shiraz, Aliah, Shabir, etc. This phirni is made with very simple ingredients—rice flour, whole milk, sugar and flavouring agents (we are using saffron or zafran in our phirni). Our version is made without any condensed milk or mawa because we found that they don’t make any noticeable difference to phirni. We also like our phirni to be creamy and plain, so we have left out any additional garnishes.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 234 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Basmati rice (non-parboiled or <em>aatop</em>)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 litre</td>
<td>Full-fat milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cardamom powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4–5 strands</td>
<td>Saffron</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Heavy-bottomed pan</li>
<li><em>Khhunti</em> | large stirring spoon</li>
<li>Ladle</li>
<li>Strainer</li>
<li>Mortar and pestle</li>
<li>New <em>maati’r bhnaar</em> or small, shallow terracotta dishes (to set the phirni in)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash the rice and soak it in water for 30 minutes. Be careful not to overwash or we’ll lose the starch, which we want to preserve for creaminess of the phirni. After 30 minutes of soaking, strain the rice over a colander and leave it to air-dry.</li>
<li>Soak the <em>bhnaar</em> in water for 30 minutes as well.</li>
<li>Once dry, transfer rice to a grinder and reduce it to a powder in 4 or 5 short pulses. The grind should neither be too coarse nor too fine. Take 1 cup of milk out of the total milk and mix the rice flour in it. Premixing rice flour with cold milk before adding it to hot milk will prevent clumping.</li>
<li>Gently toast some cardamom pods in a pan and crush them to a powder. Sift through a tea-strainer to ensure the powder is fine. We need ½ a tsp of cardamom powder; we got ours from 4 large pods of cardamom.</li>
<li>Heat milk in a heavy-bottomed pan and reduce it on medium heat for about 10 minutes. Then add the rice flour and cold milk mixture and stir immediately to prevent rice from clumping.</li>
<li>Add 4 or 5 strands of saffron OR 1 tsp of kewra water (whichever you are using) to the pan.</li>
<li>Continue reducing on low heat until phirni thickens. Keep stirring continuously, as that will help release starch and make the phirni creamy.</li>
<li>Once the rice is cooked, add sugar and a pinch of salt. Don’t skip the salt—it balances the sweetness and makes a big difference to the taste of phirni! Also add the cardamom powder now.</li>
<li>Keep cooking until the phirni reaches the right consistency. It should neither be too thick, nor too thin—when poured, it should just about find its own level.</li>
<li>Transfer to the <em>maati’r bhnaar</em> or any ceramic or glass bowl to set. Cover the bowls/dishes with a plastic wrap and place in the fridge for 24 hours to set completely. The plastic covering will prevent the phirni from absorbing any ‘funny fridge smells’. Enjoy chilled.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/kolkata-mutton-biryani/">Mutton biryani</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/beef-chaap/">Beef chaap</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      In Calcutta phirni is a creamy, mildly sweet, saffron-flavoured rice pudding set in earthen bowls—a must-have after a biryani!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="dessert" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dessert/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="mughlai" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mughlai/"/>
    
      <category term="phirni" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/phirni/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kolkata Mutton Biryani</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/kolkata-mutton-biryani/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/kolkata-mutton-biryani/</id>
    <published>2018-06-01T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T04:14:13.730Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A distinctive biryani full of flavour but low on spiciness and heat.</p>

<p class="post-intro">Fragrant rice and soft mutton get together in this classic Calcutta biryani dish. Contains potatoes!</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">C</span>alcuttans are truly passionate about their mutton biryani. Kolkata has its distinct style of biryani which is on a par with the best biryanis in India—including Lucknow-style biryani and the Hyderabadi biryani. Kolkata biryani, in spite of the usage of a staggering number of spices, is not spicy. It is subtle and fragrant without being dry. A good Kolkata biryani should be moist and can be eaten on its own—no raita or salan required. This style of biryani is descended from the Lucknow style biryani that came to Calcutta with the exiled Nawab of Awadh, Wajid Ali Shah (remember Satyajit Ray’s “Satranj Ke Khilari”?). </p>
<p>What started with just a handful of restaurants such as Royal India Hotel, Shiraz, and Aminia has become the most widely available and eaten street food in Calcutta. Many new restaurants have sprung up and the competition for excellent biryani in Calcutta is only getting tougher. Our recipe of the Kolkata mutton biryani isn’t perfect, but it is very, very close. With some practice, planning and patience this recipe will help you make a very good Calcutta-style biryani at home.</p>
<p><a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1oB_S9Aa_5V_AOBATlf2vTc3EW_4sFW4O/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="external">DOWNLOAD Biryani Timeline Chart</a> </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 4 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5–6 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> </p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Mutton (large pieces of ~100g each)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 whole</td>
<td>Potatoes (the starchy kind, e.g., ‘jyoti’, ~80g each)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Basmati rice (aged, long-grained, non-parboiled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE BIRISTA</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Onions (sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~150 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for deep frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR BIRYANI MASALA</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.25 g (6 pcs)</td>
<td>Green cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.75 g (1 pc)</td>
<td>Black cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.5 g (¾ tsp)</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>0.5 g (3 cm stick)</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.2 g (½ pc)</td>
<td>Nutmeg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.75 g (2 pcs)</td>
<td>Mace</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Shahi jeera</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Kabab chini</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 g (½ tsp)</td>
<td>Fennel seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>White pepper (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.25 g (½ tsp)</td>
<td>Black pepper (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR MARINATING MUTTON</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Birista</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Biryani masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Kewra water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Ground pepper</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE RICE</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.25 g (6 pcs)</td>
<td>Green cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1.5 g (2 pcs)</td>
<td>Black cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 g (6 cm stick)</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Fennel seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 kg</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR ASSEMBLY</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 to 10 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves (to line the pan with)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Alubukhara (dried plums)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Rose petals (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Birista</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Biryani masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Grated khoya kheer (‘mawa’ or solidified milk)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Yakhni</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Lime juice (from half a lime)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Saffron (steeped in 20g warm milk)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Yellow food colour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>180 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Kewra water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Rose water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 drops</td>
<td>Meetha attar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Butter</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
<li>Mortar and pestle</li>
<li>Strainer | colander</li>
<li>Large pot with lid</li>
<li>Cheesecloth and twine</li>
<li>Grater</li>
<li><em>Biryani’r hnari</em> | large pan with tight-fitting lid (for dum)</li>
<li>Heavy-duty aluminium foil | wet flour dough </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Spice grinder</li>
<li>Pressure cooker</li>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Weighing scale</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—FRYING POTATOES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Peel potatoes and smear on them yellow food colour. Keep the potatoes whole (each piece should be about 80 g) and go easy on the amount of food colour.</li>
<li>Heat vegetable oil, 3 cm deep, in a pan. Fry the potatoes until they are lightly coloured on all sides (about 4 minutes).</li>
<li>Drain them from the oil and set aside. </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—MAKING BIRISTA</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In the same oil, add sliced onions, a small handful at a time, to make birista. Watch the full video on how to make birista.</li>
<li>Weigh two separate portions of birista—20 g and 15 g—and keep ready.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—MAKING BIRYANI MASALA</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a pan set over medium heat, add all the spices in the given proportions for ‘biryani masala’ (see above). Gently toast them, stirring continuously.</li>
<li>Transfer the toasted spices to a spice grinder and blitz them to a fine powder.</li>
<li>Weigh two separate portions of biryani masala—8 g and 5 g— and keep ready.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP IV—MARINATING MUTTON</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Peel ginger and garlic, roughly chop them, and crush them into a fine paste.</li>
<li>In a large mixing bowl or pressure cooker, mix together yoghurt, ginger and garlic paste, birista, kewra water, biryani masala, red chilli powder, salt, and ground pepper, in the proportions given above for ‘marinating mutton’. </li>
<li>Add the mutton pieces and coat them well with the marinade, making sure to to massage it into the crevices too.</li>
<li>Cover and set aside for 1 hour.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP V—SOAKING RICE</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Meanwhile, wash the rice and soak it in water for 30 minutes. At the end of this time, drain the water and strain the rice over a net or colander. Set aside. Soaking leads to longer and fluffier rice grains. </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP IV—COOKING MUTTON</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>After the mutton has had 1 hour to marinate, transfer it to a pressure cooker. </li>
<li>Lay the fried potatoes at the bottom of the pressure cooker, followed by the mutton on top (we changed this step from the video because this yields juicier potatoes).</li>
<li>Add 150 g water and pressure cook it on medium-low heat for 30 minutes. Allow the steam to release naturally for another 15 minutes before opening the lid of the pressure cooker.</li>
<li><em>Separating mutton, potatoes, and <em>yakhni</em>:</em> Extract the potatoes and mutton pieces in separate dishes and set them aside. Now strain the liquid remaining in the pressure cooker. This is called ‘yakhni’ (a broth resulting from mutton and spices cooked together). We need just 200 g of it, so weigh it out and keep ready.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP VII—BOILING WATER FOR RICE</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Place the spices mentioned in the ‘rice’ section above in the given proportions on a small square of cheesecloth. Tie them with a piece of twine to form a bag.</li>
<li>In a large pot, take 3 kg water. Add 30 g salt to it.</li>
<li>Add the bag of spices to the water and allow it to come to a boil (should take about 20 minutes). </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP VIII—PREPARING FOR ASSEMBLY</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Meanwhile, prepare for assembly by weighing out all that you will need (see ‘assembly’ section above) and keeping ready.</li>
<li>This is the order in which you will need everything.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Bay leaves</li>
<li>Cooked mutton pieces</li>
<li>Cooked potatoes</li>
<li>Alubukhara</li>
<li>Birista</li>
<li>Rose petals (if using)</li>
<li>Biryani masala</li>
<li>Grated khoya kheer</li>
<li>Yakhni</li>
<li>Lime juice</li>
<li>Saffron and yellow food colour mixed in 20 g warm milk</li>
<li>Rose water, kewra water, and meetha attar mixed in 180 g warm milk</li>
<li>Ghee and butter, melted together in the microwave</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>STEP IX—COOKING RICE, ASSEMBLY, AND DUM</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Set the <em>biryani’r hnari</em> or pan you are using for dum on low heat. Grease it with ghee.</li>
<li>Lay bay leaves in a single layer to cover the bottom of the pan. These will impart an aroma and provide buffer against burning.</li>
<li>Place the mutton pieces in a single layer, and the potatoes on top of the mutton. Don’t place potatoes too close to the edge or you might accidentally cut into them while serving. </li>
<li>Strew alubukhara, birista, and rose petals evenly.</li>
<li>Take half the stipulated amount of biryani masala and khoya kheer, and spread evenly. We will use the remaining half in the next layer. </li>
<li>Now add the yakhni and lime juice.</li>
<li>By this time the water for your rice should have come to a boil and its colour changed. Extract the bag of spices and discard it. Add the rice and let it cook until 80% done, that is, until when the centre is no longer hard, but the grain is still firm. Our rice took about 5 minutes to reach this stage, but read your packet instructions.</li>
<li>Strain rice, a ladle at a time, and spread it directly in the pan. Repeat this until half the rice is added to the pan.</li>
<li>On top of this first layer of rice, spread the remaining biryani masala and khoya kheer. Also spread the saffron+colour mixture evenly. </li>
<li>Now strain the rest of the rice and add it to the pan. Flatten it gently.</li>
<li>On top of the second layer of rice, add milk mixed with the aromatics. Also add melted butter and ghee, making sure to drizzle it near the sides of the pan too. </li>
<li>Cover the pan with heavy-duty aluminium foil (if yours is thin, use double layers), sealing the sides well so that no steam escapes. Cover the pan with a tight-fitting lid. If you don’t want to use foil, you can also seal the lid with a wet flour dough.</li>
<li>Set the pan on dum on medium-low heat for 30 minutes. Turn of the heat and allow it to rest another 15 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><p>Served with</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/beef-chaap/">Chaap</a></li>
<li>Salad</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Fragrant rice and soft mutton get together in this classic Calcutta biryani dish. Contains potatoes!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
      <category term="mosur dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mosur-dal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Calcutta-style Beef Chaap</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/beef-chaap/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/beef-chaap/</id>
    <published>2018-05-24T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-05-25T02:57:37.280Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Thin slices of meat marinated and cooked slowly in fat</p>

<p class="post-intro">Ultimate Mughlai delicacy of thin slices of lean beef marinated in a nutty rich marinade and slow cooked in fat</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p>[<em>In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]</p>
<p><span class="dropcap">W</span>alk by any joint specialising in serving up Mughlai delicacies in Kolkata and its outskirts and you will most likely find a massive lagan of chaap being tended to right there on the footpath. Chaap is as ubiquitous in Kolkata’s Mughlai eateries, big and small, as biryani. Beef chaap is specially popular among aficionados. In this video, we show you how to recreate restaurant-style, tender, melt-in-your-mouth beef chaap, championed by joints such as Asma, Nafeel, Zam Zam, Afreen, Arafat, and their ilk, at home.</p>
<p>Chaap is basically a preparation where thin slices of meat are marinated, usually tenderised, and fried in oil at very low temperature over a long period of time. Bengali cuisines both sides of the border make varying kinds of dry and gravy-laden chaap preparations. The Kolkata chaap in particular has generous amounts of spicy gravy and is served with a drizzling of the oil it is cooked it. Enjoy it with naan, tandoori rooti, roomali rooti, porota, or a plate of warm aromatic biryani.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 2 hours 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> Really?</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Beef (1cm thick slices)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Onion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Garlic</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Cashew nuts</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Charmagaz (mixed melon seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Posto (poppy seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Chhatu (roasted-gram flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>120 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Khoya kheer or mawa (reduced, solidified milk)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Shahi garam masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Kewra water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Rose water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 drops</td>
<td>Meetha attar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Saffron (in 1 tbsp milk)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Yellow food colour (optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Kacha pepe (unripe, green papaya; optional)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>Dalda (vegetable shortening)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Mallet or pestle</li>
<li>Grater</li>
<li>Large, flat, heavy-bottomed pan</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated frying spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak poppy seeds, cashew nuts and charmagaz in water for at least 2 hours. Then, drain the water and make a paste, first of the poppy seeds, and then of cashew and charmagaz together. </li>
<li>Roughly chop onions, ginger, garlic, and green chillies, and make a paste of these too.</li>
<li>Transfer all the pasted ingredients to a large mixing bowl.</li>
<li>Mix in yoghurt, chhatu, shahi garam masala, kashmiri red chilli powder, turmeric, salt, kewra water, rose water, meetha attar, and saffron (mixed in 1 tbsp warm milk).</li>
<li>Grate khoya kheer and add it to the bowl too.</li>
<li>If your meat is particularly tough, you can add grated papaya to the mix. Papaya skin contains an enzyme called papain, which breaks down meat proteins and helps tenderise it.</li>
<li>Lay a beef slice between two sheets of plastic and use a mallet or pestle to gently flatten it. This will lead to tender chaap. However, be careful not to hammer too forcefully or the meat may fall apart. </li>
<li>Add the slices to the prepared mixture, making sure to coat each slice well on both sides. Leave them to marinate for 2 hours.</li>
<li>Heat a dalda, ghee, and vegetable oil in a large, flat, heavy-bottomed pan on low heat. We used these in the ratio 2:1:4. The fat should be 2cm deep. Don’t heat the oil up too much; chaap needs to be fried in oil at a very low temperature (150°C) for a long time.</li>
<li>Lower the marinated beef into the oil. Try and keep the meat as far away from the direct flame as possible. The best practice is to line the edge of the pan with the meat. </li>
<li>Fry for about an hour or until the meat is tender, turning over once in a while to cook it evenly from both sides.</li>
<li>Once the meat is soft enough that it breaks apart using just two fingers and the gravy has acquired a nutty brown colour, remove from the oil and serve.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Naan</li>
<li>Tandoori rooti</li>
<li>Roomali rooti</li>
<li>Porota</li>
<li>Biryani</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Ultimate Mughlai delicacy of thin slices of lean beef marinated in a nutty rich marinade and slow cooked in fat
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="beef" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/beef/"/>
    
      <category term="mughlai" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mughlai/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Aam’er Tok or Ambol</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/aamer-tok/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/aamer-tok/</id>
    <published>2018-05-17T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T01:25:37.163Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Sweet, savoury, sour and chilled</p>

<p class="post-intro">A chilled sweet, savoury and sour watery chutney made from small green mangoes with an added kick of pungent mustard oil.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>am’er tok (pronounced “tawk”) is a recipe for the hot Bengal summers when the mangoes are not ripe yet, and frequent nor’westers or afternoon storms keep knocking unripe green mangoes off the trees. Bengalis love making all sorts of cooling green mango recipes in these months. Besides a variety of <em>tok dal</em>, <em>achaar</em> (pickles) and <em>chutney</em>, <em>aam’er tok</em> or <em>ambol</em> too is popular during summers. It is a unique transitional course just after the fish and meat course and before dessert. Sometimes, on very hot days <em>ambol</em> or <em>tok</em> can even play the role of dessert in ending the meal. </p>
<p>For this <em>aam’er tok</em> recipe remember to select the smaller, more fragrant unripe green mangoes. The large, nearly ripe green mangoes don’t have the same tartness, flavour or texture. This can be cooked very quickly and easily, and stored in the fridge for a few weeks. Serve chilled towards the end of the meal and experience the cool-sweet-savoury-sour <em>tok</em> make its way to your soul. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 45 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 10 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 96 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Kacha aam (green mangoes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Mustard seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>130 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khhunti</em> | long frying spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Peel mangoes and cut them in 5-cm chunks. In small mangoes, remove the pit. Soak the mangoes in water for 30 minutes to reduce the astringent taste. Strain and set aside.</li>
<li>Heat 10 g mustard oil in a pan. Temper it with dried red chilli and mustard seeds.</li>
<li>Add mangoes and fry them on medium-high heat for 3 minutes. Add salt and cook for another minute before adding 500 g water.</li>
<li>Add turmeric and sugar. Since tartness of mangoes can vary widely, you may need a little more or a little less sugar than we’ve mentioned. </li>
<li>Bubble on medium heat until the mangoes are cooked. This should take about 5 minutes. Be careful not to overcook or the mangoes will disintegrate and turn mushy. </li>
<li>Remove from heat. Once cool you can store this in the fridge for about 2 weeks. Serve chilled.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A chilled sweet, savoury and sour watery chutney made from small green mangoes with an added kick of pungent mustard oil.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="tok" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/tok/"/>
    
      <category term="kacha aam" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kacha-aam/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kacha Moog Dal</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/kacha-moong-dal/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/kacha-moong-dal/</id>
    <published>2018-05-10T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T03:59:35.998Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Light, everyday dal made with unroasted moong</p>

<p class="post-intro">A quick and delicate dal tempered with radhuni, a type of seed that is quite unique to Bengal.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span>acha Moog’er Dal is a light dal made with moong lentils that is ideal for the summer months when it is too hot to eat the more decadent <a href="/recipe/bhaja-moong-dal-shobji-diye/">Bhaja Moog’er Dal</a>. This is also different from the <a href="/recipe/tetor-dal-lau-diye/">Lau diye Tetor Dal</a> (dal made with gourd and bitter gourd) in terms of the tempering used—plus this is very quick and very easy to make. Just serve the kacha moong dal with some <a href="/recipe/alu-sheddho/">aloo seddho</a> or <a href="/recipe/aloo-bhorta/">aloo bhorta</a> and it makes for a simple but nourishing lunch.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 111 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Moong dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Green chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Radhuni</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pressure cooker | boiling pot</li>
<li>Kadai | wok (with lid)</li>
<li>Khunti | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and rinse the dal, and boil it with 550 g water until cooked. The dal should be soft, but should not disintegrate.</li>
<li>Heat mustard oil in a pan, and temper it with dried red chilli, bay leaf, green chilli, and radhuni. </li>
<li>Add the boiled dal. Also add salt, sugar, and turmeric. Stir everything together and let bubble for 6 minutes on medium heat.</li>
<li>Add ghee before turning off the stove and serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/torkari/">Torkari</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A quick and delicate dal tempered with radhuni, a type of seed that is quite unique to Bengal.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
      <category term="moong dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/moong-dal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bhaat’er Kofta–Thakurbari’r Ranna</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/bhaater-kofta-thakurbarir-ranna/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/bhaater-kofta-thakurbarir-ranna/</id>
    <published>2018-05-03T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T03:58:51.961Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A snack of delicately flavoured, deep-fried rice balls</p>

<p class="post-intro">A 100 year old recipe from Rabindranath Tagore’s niece, Pragyasundari Debi’s cookbook <a href="https://www.amazon.in/dp/8172152175?tag=bongeats0c-21" target="_blank" rel="external">Amish O Niramish Ahar Volume 1</a>.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his recipe—bhaat’er kofta or deep-fried rice balls—is part of a series where we commemorate Rabindra Jayanti each year by cooking a recipe from a book written by members of the illustrious Tagore family. These bhaat’er koftas are from <em>Amish o Niramish Ahar</em> (Vol. 1), a well-known Bengali cookbook from the early twentieth century written by Pragyasundari Debi. She was Rabindranath Tagore’s niece who religiously tried out and recorded hundreds of recipes, both common and uncommon. </p>
<p>Fragrant, flavourful and creamy on the inside with a crunchy coating of yoghurt and semolina (<em>sooji</em>) on the outside, these koftas make a great tea-time snack. If they look uncannily similar to the Italian arancini, it is probably because they may be inspired by it. Give this recipe a go—it is quick and easy—and if you have tried any of the other recipes from <em>Amish o Niramish Ahar</em>, let us know in the comments section of our YouTube video. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 10 koftas<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 73 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Cooked gobindobhog rice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Nutmeg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Clove</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Raisins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Khoya kheer/mawa</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 large pinch</td>
<td>Saffron</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>for breading</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>for breading</td>
<td>Sooji (semolina)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>for frying</td>
<td>Vegetable oil + ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Kadai | frying pan</li>
<li>Jhhanjhhri | perforated frying spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak saffron in the milk and let it steep until the color enriches. Grind nutmeg, cardamom, cinnamon, and clove to a fine powder. In a little ghee, fry the raisins until they go puffy. </li>
<li>Now transfer the cooked gobindobhog rice to a mixing bowl. Add a chopped green chilli, salt, powdered spices, grated khoya kheer, and saffron-steeped milk. </li>
<li>Mix together thoroughly, mashing the rice as you go for a creamy texture. Once the rice looks well mixed, add the fried raisins and fold them in.</li>
<li>Divide the mixture in 30 g portions. Apply oil to your hands and roll each portion into a round kofta. </li>
<li>Make a paste of ginger and the remaining green chilli. Add it to the yoghurt and beat until you have a smooth mix. This should be thin (like beaten eggs!), so add water to the yoghurt mixture to adjust consistency. Also lay out the flour and semolina two separate flat dishes. </li>
<li>Bread each kofta by first dusting it in flour, then dipping it in the yoghurt, and finally coating it with semolina. </li>
<li>To deep-fry the koftas, heat oil in a kadai. You can also fry these in ghee. We usually flavour our oil with a tablespoon of ghee. Once hot, drop the koftas into the oil and fry on medium-high heat for about 3 minutes until they are lightly coloured. Serve piping hot.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Elegant saffron laden rice koftas—a 100 year old snack from Tagore&#39;s niece, Pragyasundari Debi&#39;s cookbook.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="rabindra jayanti" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rabindra-jayanti/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mocha’r Ghonto 2 Ways</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/mochar-ghonto/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/mochar-ghonto/</id>
    <published>2018-04-27T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T04:00:04.373Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A Bengali delicacy made with banana-plant florets</p>

<p class="post-intro">The most most flamboyant sibling of the mashed potato family, aloo bhorta is the easiest and tastiest thing to make with potato</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">M</span>ocha’r ghonto is special to anyone who has grown up in Bengal. Mocha is the banana blossom. The niramish (vegetarian) mocha’r ghonto with narkel (coconut) and chhola (Bengal gram) is loved as much as mocha chingri garnished with small freshwater prawns. In this video, we show methods of preparing both mocha’r ghonto as well as mocha with chingri. This also includes a very easy, step-by-step guide to cleaning, preparing and cutting mocha. Like any Bengali niramish recipe, this one uses no onion or garlic—the main flavours come from ginger, cumin, ghee and garam masala. Mocha provides a crunchy texture that is a canvas for all these flavours. Give this Bengali recipe of mocha a try. It is not the best looking dish, but once you taste mocha, it will change your life.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 2 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 150 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>550 g</td>
<td>Whole mocha (banana blossom)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pc</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (2-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Grated coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¾ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Garam masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Soaked chhola (Bengal gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Dal’er bora (recipe below)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Prawns (shelled and deveined)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pressure cooker</li>
<li>Strainer | colander</li>
<li>Kadai | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Clean and cut mocha <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G4Igr5VwEEQ" target="_blank" rel="external">as shown in this video</a>. A 550 g whole mocha roughly yields 300 to 350 g edible mocha. </li>
<li>Add chopped mocha to a pressure cooker with 10 g salt, ½ tsp turmeric, and 650 g water. Pressure cook on medium heat for one whistle and then allow the steam to release naturally. </li>
<li>Open the pressure cooker and strain the mocha over a net or colander. Once cool to the touch (in about 30 minutes), gently mash the mocha to get a mix of mushy and crunchy textures.</li>
<li>Heat mustard oil in a pan. If using prawns, coat them in a pinch of salt and turmeric, and fry them on medium heat for about 45 seconds. Remove from the oil and set aside. </li>
<li>To the same oil, add a tempering of dried red chilli, bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and cumin seeds. Once crackling, add the cubed potatoes and fry until golden (about 4 minutes). </li>
<li>Add grated coconut and fry for a minute before adding a slurry of spices made by mixing ginger paste, cumin powder, ½ tsp turmeric powder, and red chilli powder with 50 g water. Sauté the spices until they release oil. This should take about 10 minutes or so. Whenever the pan becomes dry, add a splash of water and continue frying. </li>
<li>Add green chillies and soaked chhola (if using). Sauté for another 3 minutes before adding boiled mocha.</li>
<li>Add salt and sugar. Sauté mocha with the spices for about 6 minutes on low heat. If the mocha becomes too dry, you may also add 1 tbsp of milk. </li>
<li>Add the fried prawns and/or dal’er bora (whichever you are using) and cook for 2 minutes to allow the flavours to mingle. Finish with ghee and garam masala.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Banana blossoms chopped fine and cooked with ghee, ginger and cumin into one of Bengal’s favourite vegetable sides.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="ghonto" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/ghonto/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
      <category term="prawns" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/prawns/"/>
    
      <category term="mocha" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mocha/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Kachkola’r Kofta’r Dalna</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/kachkola-kofta-dalna/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/kachkola-kofta-dalna/</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-20T04:00:40.958Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Green banana fritters in a spicy curry</p>

<p class="post-intro">Bengali special spicy green plantain fritters soaked in a warm gingery curry</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>mong the many kolagach (banana plant) products Bengalis have thought to turn into delectable food items, kachkola’r kofta (raw banana kofta) remains an eternal favourite. Kachkola’r kofta are delicately spiced, deep-fried raw banana fritters. Boiled kachkola are mashed with boiled potatoes, onion paste, ginger, green chillies, and a host of dry spices including bhaja masala, which gives the koftas their distinctive flavour. A little maida (all-purpose flour) binds everything together. This mixture is then portioned, shaped into discs, and dropped in hot oil. We like to fry our kachkola’r boras until they are dark brown in colour (as opposed to golden brown). This leads to richer, better tasting koftas, which also don’t break as easily once introduced to the curry. This brings us to the second part of the recipe—the kachkola jhol/dalna. This raw banana or plantain curry is hot, gingery, and slightly sweet. The addition of grated coconut gives the curry body in addition to a nice texture. As always we finish this particular dalna too with some ghee and Bengali garam masala. </p>
<p>The green banana koftas, once fried and completely cooled, freeze very well. We usually make a large batch and freeze half for up to 30 days. Be sure to store them in an airtight box or bag. The day before you want to make the curry, move them from the freezer to the fridge and let them defrost slowly. Oh, and do not discard the green banana peels while making kachkola recipe, as you could turn them into a delicious, fiery <a href="/recipe/kachkola-khosha-chochchori">khosha chachchari</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 90 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6–8 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 219 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE KOFTA</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Kachkola (unripe, green bananas)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>80 g</td>
<td>Boiled potato</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45 g</td>
<td>Onion paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Grated coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¾ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¾ tsp</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gGmCPwauVBs" target="_blank" rel="external">Bhaja masala</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Maida</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~150 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE DALNA</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (3cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Grated coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Coriander powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>14 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Bengali garam masala</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>450 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pressure cooker | boiling pot</li>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Kadai | wok (with lid)</li>
<li>Jhhajhhri | perforated frying spoon</li>
<li>Khunti | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—MAKE THE KOFTAS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Cut kachkola into 5-cm cross-sections and boil in a pressure cooker with 8 g salt, ¼ tsp turmeric, and 450 g water. On medium heat, one whistle should do the trick. Turn off the heat and allow the pressure to release naturally. However, do not let the kachkola sit in the water for too long or it will absorb water and become soggy. </li>
<li>Remove the kachkola peels and transfer the boiled bananas to a mixing bowl. Add the boiled potato (80 g) and mash the two together until lump free.</li>
<li>Now add onion paste, ginger paste, grated coconut, green chillies, cumin powder, coriander powder, turmeric, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gGmCPwauVBs" target="_blank" rel="external">bhaja masala</a>, salt, sugar, and maida. Mix everything until well combined.</li>
<li>Divide in 30 g portions and shape into discs. </li>
<li>Lower the koftas into hot (170°C) vegetable oil in a single layer. Fry them until they are dark brown in colour, turning them over often. This should take about 4 to 5 minutes. Drain from the oil and set aside.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP I—MAKE THE DALNA</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Peel the potatoes and cut them into 3-cm cubes. Make a slurry of spices by mixing ginger paste, cumin powder, coriander powder, turmeric, and kashmiri red chilli powder with 50 g water. Set aside.</li>
<li>Heat mustard oil in a pan. Temper it with dried red chillies, bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and cumin seeds.</li>
<li>Add the potatoes and fry them for about 4 minutes, stirring frequently, until they are golden.</li>
<li>Add the grated coconut and fry it for about a minute. Be careful not to let the coconut burn.</li>
<li>Now add the spice slurry prepared earlier and sauté it on medium heat. Whenever the mixture dries out, add a splash of hot water and continue frying. Add the salt and 2 slit green  green chillies, and after a couple of minutes add the sugar. Cover the pan and keep cooking the spices until oil separates and the potatoes are done (about 6 minutes).</li>
<li>Add 450 g hot water. This will form the curry. Once it comes to a boil, drop in the koftas. Simmer on low heat until the curry thickens. This should take about 5 minutes.</li>
<li>Garnish with ghee, <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Bengali garam masala</a>, and two more slit green chillies. Rest it covered for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Bengali special spicy green plantain fritters soaked in a warm gingery curry
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Chingri Malaikari</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/chingri-malaikari/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/chingri-malaikari/</id>
    <published>2018-04-12T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T03:58:59.975Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Creamy Bengali prawn curry with coconut milk</p>

<p class="post-intro">Inspired by Malay flavours, ‘malai’-kari is an iconic Bengali prawn recipe made using giant tiger or freshwater prawns and fresh, creamy coconut milk.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">C</span>hingri malaikari is an iconic Bengali prawn curry made by cooking large tiger prawns (bagda chingri) or giant freshwater prawns (golda chingri) in a super-subtle, super-creamy coconut-milk sauce. Don’t be fooled by the elegant appearance of this well-loved Bengali treat—chingri malaikari is looks deceptively complicated to cook, when in reality it is easier to make than even chicken or egg curry!</p>
<p>The name of this chingri macher recipe bears somewhat of a double meaning. ‘Malai’ meaning ‘cream’ recalls the coconut-milk base in which the prawns are cooked. However, this prawn recipe seems to have made its way into Bengali kitchens through contact with Malaysian traders; so ‘malaikari’ is actually ‘Malay’ curry, over time transliterated as ‘malai’ curry. </p>
<p>In this detailed video we show you how to prepare a gorgeous, creamy chingri malaikari, starting from a walkthrough of how you can clean and devein giant tiger (bagda) or freshwater (golda) prawns. With this step by step recipe video at your disposal, there is no reason why you should hop over to you nearest Bhojohori Manna to satiate your chingri malaikari cravings!</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 292 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Bagda or golda chingri (giant tiger or freshwater prawns)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Onion paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Kashmiri red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Coconut milk (first-press)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Coconut milk (second-press)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>24 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>36 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Bengali garam masala</a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Scissors | paring knife (for shelling and deveining the prawns)</li>
<li>Kadai | wok (with lid)</li>
<li>Khunti | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Shell and devein the prawns, leaving the flavourful head intact. You may remove the stomach of the prawn, located near its head. We are leaving the shells on, but you may peel them off if you like.</li>
<li>Coat prawns with 1 tsp salt and ½ tsp turmeric powder, and set aside.</li>
<li>In a grinder jar, add onions and blitz them to a fine paste. Also extract coconut milk, reserving the first-press (thick) and second-press (thinner) milk in separate jars, and keep it ready.</li>
<li>Heat vegetable oil in a pan. Once hot, lower the prawns one by one, and fry them in batches for about 45 seconds on each side. The longer you cook prawns the tougher they’ll become, so remove them from the heat immediately and set aside.</li>
<li>Now add ghee to the residual oil. Temper with dried red chillies, bay leaf, cardamom, cloves, and cinnamon.</li>
<li>Add onion paste along with sugar, and fry for about 8 minutes until the onions are brown. </li>
<li>Add ginger paste and fry for another 3–4 minutes, after which add turmeric and kashmiri red chilli powder. Stir intermittently so that the spices don’t stick to the bottom of the pan. When they do, add a splash of the thin, second-press coconut milk to loosen the mixture up and help fry it. Also add three slit green chillies and salt now.</li>
<li>Once oil starts separating from the spices, beat the yoghurt until it is lump free and add it to the pan. Drop the heat and stir vigorously to prevent the yoghurt from splitting. Cook it for 3–4 minutes.</li>
<li>Add the second-press (thin) coconut milk and simmer for about 2 minutes before adding the first-press (thick) coconut milk. Once it comes to a boil, add the fried prawns.</li>
<li>Allow the prawns to bubble in the curry, covered, for no more than 5 minutes. </li>
<li>Finish off with <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">garam masala</a> before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/mishti-polao/">Polao</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/bengali-vegetable-fried-rice/">Bengali fried rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Subtle but rich in flavour, chingri malaikari—giant tiger/freshwater prawns cooked in creamy coconut-milk curry—is a Bengali treat.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="Prawns" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/Prawns/"/>
    
      <category term="biyebari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/biyebari/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Mishti Polao | Basanti Polao</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/mishti-polao/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/mishti-polao/</id>
    <published>2018-04-05T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T03:59:52.639Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A sweet, rich Bengali-style polao with cashew and raisins</p>

<p class="post-intro">A bright yellow, sweet Bengali polao redolent with ghee, garnished with fried cashews and raisins.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">B</span>asanti polao or mishti polao is a sweet, ghee-laden rice dish made from fragrant gobindabhog or kalijeera rice, cashew nuts and raisins. This is the main rice dish of choice for any special occasion. Among the side dishes served with basanti pulao, kosha mangsho is the most popular. While there are many other kinds of polao made with different types of fruits, nuts, meat or fish, this one has become the most popular, featuring prominently on the menus of Bengali specialty restaurants such as Bhojohori Manna, Kewpie’s, etc.</p>
<p>Use aged, non-parboiled (<em>aatop</em>) gobindobhog rice for this dish. New rice breaks very easily and will lead to a mash instead of perfectly cooked individual grains. We fry the rice before boiling it to enhance its flavours and break down the starch (which prevents rice from turning sticky). Also be careful of the amount of water you add. For 500 g rice, we’re using 1050 g water. However, as quality of rice varies widely, it is best that you reserve some of the water (5–10%) and add only if necessary. </p>
<p>This polao tastes best the next day, so plan accordingly. Resting allows all the flavours to mingle nicely. It also ensures that all the moisture is absorbed by rice grains, leading to fluffier polao. </p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings<br><strong>CALORIES</strong> 520 kcal per serving</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Aged gobindobhog rice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>105 g</td>
<td>Bengali-style ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Ginger (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>70 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35 g</td>
<td>Cashew nuts</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35 g</td>
<td>Raisins</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1050 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and rinse rice, and leave it to air-dry over a strainer. </li>
<li>Once dry, transfer it to a mixing bowl. Add to it finely chopped ginger, turmeric, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, bay leaves, and Bengali-style ghee. Mix until rice grains are well coated with ghee and spices. Cover and rest for about an hour.</li>
<li>Before you start cooking, set water to boil in a pot or in an electric kettle.</li>
<li>Heat 5 g ghee in a kadai. Add the cashews and fry them until they are lightly coloured (about a minute). Now add the marinated rice. Fry it for about 6 minutes on medium until the rice takes on an opaque appearance. Add the raisins and fry for another 2 minutes.</li>
<li>Add about 1050 g (±5%) hot water, along with the salt. The amount of water is important. Add too much and polao will become soggy, add too little and it may stick to the pan.</li>
<li>Cover and cook on lowest possible heat for about 10 minutes. Rest before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/recipe/mutton-kosha/">Mutton kosha</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/chicken-curry/">Chicken curry</a></li>
<li><a href="/recipe/paneer-dalna/">Paneer’er dalna</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A bright yellow, sweet Bengali polao redolent with ghee and garnished with fried cashews and raisins.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="rice" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rice/"/>
    
      <category term="polao" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/polao/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
