<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Bong Eats | Bengali Recipe Videos</title>
  <subtitle>Bong Eats is about food from Bengal. And that&#39;s not just Bengali food.</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://bongeats.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-05-05T04:01:34.106Z</updated>
  <id>https://bongeats.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Bong Eats</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Keema&#39;r Doi Bora</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/keemar-doi-bora/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/keemar-doi-bora/</id>
    <published>2017-05-04T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-05-05T04:01:34.106Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Warm minced-meat <em>koftas</em> topped with a generous helping of chilled, spiced yoghurt</p>

<p class="post-intro">The sub-continent’s favourite snack with a deliciously meaty twist.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">I</span>t is impossible to overstate the impact of the Tagore family on the Bengali way of life. Even after two centuries, the Tagores define every aspect of what it means to be a Bengali—be it music, literature, art, philosophy, politics, or food.</p>
<p>Rabindranath grew up in a household with a deep knowledge of ancient Hindu as well as Islamic traditions. He travelled all over the world, imbibing the best aspects of every culture he encountered. He loved collecting menu cards and recipes from dinners and lunches on his travels. He would bring them back to his wife, Mrinalini, and request that the recipes be incorporated into the repertoire of the Tagore kitchen. According to accounts, some of his experiments with food were downright whimsical (pureed-garlic fritters, anyone?)</p>
<p>Indira Devi Chaudhurani (daughter of Satyendranath Tagore) was one of Rabindranath’s favourite nieces. Indira, among many of her achievements, went on to put tunes to close to 200 of her uncle’s songs. She did not herself cook. But she used to collect their household recipes and put them down in a diary. Purnima Devi, another Tagore family decedent, finally put these recipes, and some more of her own, into a book called <em>Thakurbarir Ranna</em>. With Rabindranath’s birth anniversary coming up on 25 <em>Boishak</em> (9 May), and given the bard’s love for <em>kababs</em> of all kinds, we thought of recreating this unusual take on the wildly popular Indian snack, <em>dahi vada</em>.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 1 hour<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 12 <em>boras</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE FRITTERS</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Beef or mutton keema (mince)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>85 g</td>
<td>Onions (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td><a href="&#39;/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/&#39;">Shahi garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>90 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (boiled and peeled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g (or half an egg)</td>
<td>Beaten egg</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE TOPPING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Mint leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Bhaja masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Ghee (melted)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>Tamarind sauce</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri hata</em> | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPARE THE TOPPING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a bowl, add the yoghurt, chopped mint leaves, bhaja masala, 2 g salt, and 5 g sugar. Beat together till everything is well combined.</li>
<li>Cover and leave it in the refrigerator to chill.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—PREPARE THE KOFTAS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Set a pan on medium heat and add 15 g vegetable oil to it.</li>
<li>Once the oil is hot, add 60 g of the finely chopped onions. Fry till they turn golden in colour (about 5 minutes).</li>
<li>Add 2 green chillies, finely chopped, and fry them for another minute.</li>
<li>Next, add the minced meat. Using your spatula, break up the lumps in the mince.</li>
<li>Stir in 5 g of salt and 1 tsp of <a href="&#39;/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/&#39;">Shahi garam masala powder</a> powder.</li>
<li>Cover and cook the mince on medium heat, till it is tender, for about 6 minutes (if using beef keema), or 15 minutes (if using mutton keema).</li>
<li>If your mince is particularly fatty, scoop out the excess rendered fat till the keema appears dry.</li>
<li>Transfer the cooked mince to a grinder jar and blitz in short pulses till it is completely smooth. Since the keema is dry, this process might take some time and patience. Scrape down the sides of the jar every so often and pulse again till smooth.</li>
<li>Once the mince is perfectly ground, transfer it to a mixing bowl.</li>
<li>Add the boiled potatoes and mash them in.</li>
<li>Also add half a beaten egg, 2 chopped green chillies, and 25 g chopped onions. Combine everything until you have a dough-like mixture.</li>
<li>Portion the mixture into 12 balls, each weighing 30 g. Press each ball in your fist to compact the ground mince. Then, roll it between your palms to form a smooth, crack-free ball.</li>
<li>In a frying pan, heat vegetable oil, about 4-cm deep.</li>
<li>Fry the balls till they are brown. Since the mince is already cooked, these koftas brown very quickly (in under a minute), so be prepared to extract them from the oil accordingly.</li>
<li>Drain from the oil and set aside.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—ASSEMBLY</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Melt some ghee in the microwave or on the stove. Get the yoghurt mixture out of the fridge.</li>
<li>In individual serving bowls, add the fried koftas. Drizzle some melted ghee on them. Top with generous portions of the beaten yoghurt mixture and a few dollops of tamarind sauce. Garnish with some chopped mint leaves, and serve immediately. (Remember that while serving, the boras should be hot, and the yoghurt, cold.)</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Keema’r doi bora—warm meat koftas topped with chilled yoghurt—is a meaty twist on the beloved Indian snack, the dahi vada.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="beef" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/beef/"/>
    
      <category term="mutton" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/mutton/"/>
    
      <category term="rabindranath" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rabindranath/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Korola Bhaja (in batter)</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/korola-bhaja-in-batter/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/korola-bhaja-in-batter/</id>
    <published>2017-04-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-28T03:40:21.026Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Crispy, batter-fried rings of bitter gourd</p>

<p class="post-intro">A deep-fried food that is also an antioxidant and immunity booster, <em>korola bhaja</em> is simply too good to be true.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span> balanced meal includes elements not just from all food groups, but from all flavour profiles as well—bitter, astringent, sour, salty, sweet, and so on. Bitter foods, in particular, are well-known antioxidants that contain immunity-boosting enzymes. In Bengal, these are generally consumed around springtime, when the weather transitions from chilly to hot and all manner of allergens/viruses are in the air. Over the years, Bengali cooks have devised clever and delicious ways to incorporate bitters in their diet—from fried <em>neem</em> leaves to <em>korola bhaja</em> to <em>shukto</em>.</p>
<p>Today we show you how to prepare <em>korola bhaja</em>—batter-fried rings of bitter gourd—in just 20 minutes. In this recipe, the <em>korola</em> is twice cooked—first steamed and then fried. The batter itself is simple. It is mildly seasoned with some salt, sugar, and green chillies. <em>Nigella seeds</em> provide a subtle fragrance, while <em>posto</em> (poppy) adds crunch. We top it off with a drizzle of raw, pungent mustard oil for crispiness.<br></p>

<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Bitter gourd (1-cm rings)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Maida (all-purpose flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Posto (poppy seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Green chilli (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 250 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for deep-frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Sauce pan | boiling pot (with lid)</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Forks</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri hata</em> | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Divide the <em>korola</em> (bitter gourd) into rings, 1 cm wide.</li>
<li>Transfer to a saucepan and add hot water, just enough to submerge all the rings. With the lid on, steam the <em>korola</em> for about 10 minutes. We don’t want to completely cook the vegetable at this stage. The rings will be deep-fried later on; the steaming will give the cooking process a head-start.</li>
<li>Drain the bitter gourd rings immediately and set aside to cool.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, prepare a batter by mixing the flour, salt, sugar, turmeric, nigella seeds, poppy seeds, green chilli, mustard oil, and water in the given proportions.</li>
<li>Mix the batter till well combined.</li>
<li>Set a kadai on the stove and heat it up. Add vegetable oil to the pan, at least 4 cm deep.</li>
<li>On medium flame, allow the oil to heat up completely. You can check by dropping some batter into the oil, and if it floats to the top immediately, with bubbles all around it, the oil is good to go. Remove the fried batter from the oil before proceeding, though.</li>
<li>Dunk the steamed <em>korola</em> rings in the batter, one at a time, and coat them well.</li>
<li>Gently lower them into the oil. You can fry about 8 to 10 rings at a time, depending on the size of your pan. But be sure not to overcrowd the pan, or they won’t turn out crispy.</li>
<li>Once they are golden-brown, drain the fritters from the oil.</li>
<li>Sprinkle with some rock salt and serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><p><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | <em>panta bhaat</em><br><a href="/tags/dal/"><em>Dal</em></a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The crispy, delicious korola bhaja—or bitter gourd rings dipped in batter and deep-fried till golden—is packed full of nutrients.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
      <category term="teto" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/teto/"/>
    
      <category term="korola" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/korola/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Tok Dal with Green Mangoes</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/tok-dal-aam-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/tok-dal-aam-diye/</id>
    <published>2017-04-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-21T06:19:13.866Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A sweet and tangy lentil <em>dal</em> containing unripe, green mangoes</p>

<p class="post-intro">This <em>mosur dal</em> is incredibly cooling—perfect for hot summer afternoons.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<blockquote><p>সেই মনে পড়ে, জ্যৈষ্ঠের ঝড়ে রাত্রে নাহিকো ঘুম,<br>অতি ভোরে উঠি তাড়াতাড়ি ছুটি আম কুড়াবার ধুম।</p>
<footer><strong>Rabindranath Tagore</strong></footer></blockquote>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>s spring turns to summer in the lower-Gangetic plains, people start preparing for the oppressive heat of the months to come. Cooling foods slowly start getting incorporated into the diet to combat the rising temperatures. But perhaps nothing signals the arrival of spring in Bengal more than the <em>kalboishakhis</em> (nor’westers)—late-afternoon thunderstorms that are localized to the region. One byproduct of this storm is that it causes a lot of mangoes to prematurely fall off trees. While that is not good news for ardent lovers of this fleshy, tropical fruit, it gives us an opportunity to prepare a rather delightful <em>tok dal</em> out of the unripe, sour, green mangoes.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Mosur dal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>650 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Unripe mango</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Mustard seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>38 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Pressure cooker | boiling pot</li>
<li><em>Dal’er knaata</em> | balloon whisk</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash and rinse the <a href="/tags/mosur-dal/"><em>mosur dal</em></a>, and place it in a pressure cooker or boiling pot, with 650 g water. Boil the <em>dal</em> till it is soft, but not mushy. If using a pressure cooker, boil for one whistle, and then release the steam immediately to stop the lentils from cooking any further.</li>
<li>Peel the unripe mango, and divide it into wedges, 2 cm thick. Reserve the cut pieces in a bowl of water till needed, to prevent the mangoes from oxidizing.</li>
<li>Heat a <em>kadai</em> and add 15 g mustard oil to it.</li>
<li>Temper the oil with the dried red chilli, green chillies, and mustard seeds.</li>
<li>Once the mustard seeds start to crackle, add the mango wedges, followed by about 2 g of salt.</li>
<li>Stir the salt in, cover the pan, and allow the mangoes to cook on low heat for about 5 minutes. The salt will help the mangoes soften. Stir occasionally to prevent the mangoes from sticking to the pan.</li>
<li>Once the mangoes are soft, add the boiled <em>dal</em>, turmeric powder, sugar, and rest of the salt.</li>
<li>Allow everything to bubble on medium heat for about 6 minutes. During this time, the mangoes will release their tartness into the <em>dal</em>.</li>
<li>This dish is sweet and tangy. Depending on the sourness of your mango, mash some of the softened pieces to a pulp and mix them with the dal.</li>
<li>Boil for another 2 minutes before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><p><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | <em>panta bhaat</em><br><a href="/tags/bhaja/"><em>Bhaja</em></a> | <a href="/tags/torkari/"><em>torkari</em></a></p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This delightful, sweet, tangy masoor dal—containing unripe, green mangoes—is incredibly cooling. Perfect for hot summer afternoons.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Katla Maachh Bhaja</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/rohu-katla-fish-fry/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/rohu-katla-fish-fry/</id>
    <published>2017-04-13T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-21T01:47:52.082Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A fry of <em>katla</em> fish, one of Bengal’s best freshwater carps</p>

<p class="post-intro">This recipe yields fried fish that is crunchy on the outside, and tender and juicy on the inside.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span><em>atla machh bhaja</em> is a <em>biyebari</em> (wedding feast) staple. The reason this dish occupies a special position on wedding menus is because the tender, flaky, pieces of sweetwater carp make for delicious and easy consumption. <em>Biyebari’r machh bhaja</em> is characterised by an extra-crunchy exterior, one that almost crackles when broken into. While fish fried in homes is seasoned with a sprinkling of basic salt and turmeric, caterers use ingredients such as arrowroot powder and corn flour to create an almost invisible crunchy outer layer. Deep-frying the fish (another <em>biyebari</em> trick) at the correct temperature allows for the development of an even, golden crust.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 pieces</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>250 g (4 large pieces)</td>
<td>Katla machh</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¾ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Arrowroot powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Corn flour</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 100 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for deep frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Frying spoon | perforated spoon | fork</li>
<li>Paper towels | napkin</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash the fish pieces thoroughly and pat them dry with a napkin or paper towels. Removing excess moisture from the fish will allow for the development of a crisp crust.</li>
<li>Place the fish in a mixing dish, and add the salt, turmeric powder, arrowroot powder, and corn flour.</li>
<li>Coat the fish pieces well. The arrowroot powder and corn flour in the marinade will absorb any remaining moisture, and allow the crust to turn golden when fried.</li>
<li>Heat 4-cm-deep mustard oil in a <em>kadai</em> till it starts to smoke and changes colour to a pale yellow. The frying temperature for this recipe is 180°C.</li>
<li>Gently lower the fish in the oil, skin side down. Make sure that the fish pieces are not piled one on top of the other, but placed side by side in oil. Also, do not overcrowd the pan (frying them two at a time should suffice), as we want the oil to freely flow around the fish.</li>
<li>Once the skin-side is golden (this should take about 6 minutes), turn the fish over to its flesh side. Fry this side for another 3 minutes.</li>
<li>Drain from the oil on by one, by holding the pieces against the side of the <em>kadai</em> for 20 seconds.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li>Wedge of lime | salt</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Fried katla fish (Bengal’s favourite freshwater carp)—a popular item on biyebari (wedding) menus—is crunchy on the outside and juicy inside.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="rohu" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/rohu/"/>
    
      <category term="katla" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/katla/"/>
    
      <category term="kata pona" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/kata-pona/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lobongo Lotika</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/lobongo-lotika/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/lobongo-lotika/</id>
    <published>2017-04-06T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-07T01:48:46.648Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Pockets of <em>kheer</em>, sealed with a clove, deep fried, and coated with sugar syrup</p>

<p class="post-intro">This recipe calls for only six ingredients, all of which you undoubtedly have on hand.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">B</span>engali cuisine is no stranger to sweet tea-time snacks, and certainly not to those that involve <em>kheer</em>, flour, and deep-frying. <em>Lobongo lotika</em>, like <em>mishti shingara</em> and <em>goja</em>, is a flaky, deep-fried, sugar-syrup-coated pastry. Like the <em>mishti singara</em>, it is also filled with <em>kheer</em>. But what gives <em>lobongo lotika</em> its whimsically poetic name is the fact that the <em>kheer</em> envelopes, once folded, are sealed with a single clove (<em>lobongo</em>).</p>
<p>This recipe calls for only six ingredients, all of which you undoubtedly have on hand. The preparation is elaborate. Deal with each stage, one at a time, as shown below. The filling (<em>kheer</em>) can also be prepared 3 to 5 days ahead of time, and stored in an airtight container in the refrigerator, till needed.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 3 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 10 <em>lobongo lotika</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE FILLING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Whole milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>45 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¾ tsp</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE SUGAR SYRUP</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE PASTRY</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>80 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 400 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for deep frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Heavy-bottom saucepan with lid (for the <em>kheer</em> and the sugar syrup)</li>
<li>Wooden spoon (for the <em>kheer</em>)</li>
<li>Mixing bowl (for the pastry)</li>
<li>Rolling pin (for the pastry)</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Frying spoon | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPARE THE FILLING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Take 1 kg milk in a heavy-bottom saucepan and set it to boil.</li>
<li>Once bubbling, stir in 45 g sugar.</li>
<li>Keep boiling the milk, while stirring it continuously, for about 90 minutes.</li>
<li>During this entire time, the pot should be on medium to low heat.</li>
<li>At regular intervals of 3–4 minutes, scrape the solids from the bottom and sides of the pot, and incorporate them into the boiling milk. This step, as well as the previous one, is crucial. We don’t want our <em>kheer</em> to burn at any point.</li>
<li>Once the milk has reduced and thickened (when you lift some of it on your spoon and drop it, it should falls in clumps), make a paste of ¾ tsp flour and 1 tbsp milk.</li>
<li>Add this paste to the pot. Stir and cook for another 5 minutes.</li>
<li>Divide the <em>kheer</em> into 10 portions of 20 g each.</li>
<li>Cover and chill in the refrigerator for at least two hours.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—THE PASTRY DOUGH</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a mixing bowl, take 200 g flour, 40 g <em>ghee</em>, and 4 g salt. Mix these ingredients well till they take on a bread-crumb texture. The idea is to distribute the fat among the flour particles, in order to make the pastry crisp and flaky.</li>
<li>Now, add in 80 g water.</li>
<li>Mix until the dough comes together. This is a tight dough, so don’t add more water even if it seems a bit dry at first.</li>
<li>Cover the dough and rest it for at least 20 minutes.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—SHAPING</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Once the <em>kheer</em> has chilled in the fridge for at least 2 hours, and the pastry dough is rested for at least 20 minutes, proceed to shaping each of them.</li>
<li>Shape each 20 g portion of <em>kheer</em> into 3 cm by 4 cm tablets. Put them back in the fridge to chill, till needed.</li>
<li>Divide the dough in 10 portions of 30 g each.</li>
<li>Shape each portion into a flat disc. Cover and rest, till needed.</li>
<li>This proportion—20 g <em>kheer</em> and 30 g dough—will give you the best filling to pastry ratio.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP IV—CONSTRUCTION</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Roll each portion of the dough into a 14 cm disc, about 1 mm thick.</li>
<li>Place a <em>kheer</em> tablet at the centre of the disc.</li>
<li>With your fingertips, apply water to the edges of the rolled pastry. This will act as a glue.</li>
<li>Fold the opposite ends over one another, overlapping them. Press gently to seal.</li>
<li>Turn the pastry over and apply water to the protruding wings. Fold them over each other, sealing them as you go.</li>
<li>Use a clove to seal the topmost layer of the envelope in place.</li>
<li>Follow these steps for all the pastries.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP V—THE SUGAR SYRUP</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a saucepan, add 400 g sugar and 200 g water.</li>
<li>Cover with a lid, and set it on medium heat for about 10 minutes, or till the sugar syrup starts bubbling.</li>
<li><p>For this recipe, we do not want a thick syrup. It should be the consistency of, say, packaged fruit juice.</p>
<p><strong>STEP VI—THE SUGAR SYRUP</strong></p>
</li>
<li>Heat oil in a frying pan to 150°C. The oil should be 5-cm deep.</li>
<li><strong><em>Lobongo lotika</em> is not fried in hot oil like other deep-fried snacks or crisps. Since this pastry has a lot of layers of flour, we must fry it at low temperatures to ensure that all the layers cook through. If you try to fry it at a high temperature, the outside may look brown and done, but the inner layers will still be gummy.</strong></li>
<li>Because of the slow frying, each batch of <em>lobongo lotika</em> will take about 30 minutes to cook completely.  </li>
<li>During this period, <strong>turn them every five minutes</strong> to ensure that the dough is getting cooked, and hardening, from both sides evenly. Otherwise, the <em>kheer</em> may start to ooze out of the softer end.</li>
<li>In case the filling leaks into the oil, you may remove the damaged pastry from the oil and put it inside an oven at 175°C for about 20 minutes.</li>
<li>Once the pastries are golden-brown in colour, drain them from the oil and dunk them in the sugar syrup. Coat well, shake off the excess syrup, and place them on a plate to cool.  </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Tea</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Lobongo lotika is a flaky parcel, filled with kheer (sweetened, reduced milk), sealed with a clove, deep fried, and coated with sugar syrup.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="sweets" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/sweets/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Shahi Garam Masala</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/</id>
    <published>2017-03-31T03:30:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-31T05:02:12.605Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A spice mix fit for kings</p>

<p class="post-intro">This sweet, fragrant blend of ‘royal’ spices is ideal for flavouring egg, chicken, mutton, beef, or lamb curries.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">W</span>hile the <em>garam masala</em> used in most northern and western Indian cooking might contain everything from coriander and cumin seeds to mustard seeds, the Bengali version, in its most basic form, is made up of just cardamom, cinnamon, and cloves. The ‘<em>shahi</em>’ (meaning royal) <em>garam masala</em> takes this basic spice blend to the next level. The inclusion of some additional aromatic spices such as mace (<em>joyitree</em>) and nutmeg (<em>jaiphol</em>) impart fragrance, while dried red chillies and black peppercorns provide a subtle bit of heat and flavour.</p>
<p>In Bengali cooking, <em>shahi garam masala</em> is especially used to flavour <a href="/recipe/dimer-dalna/">egg</a>, <a href="/recipe/chicken-curry/">chicken</a>, mutton, lamb, or beef curries. Along with ghee, it may also be used as garnish for several vegetarian preparations (most <em>ghontos</em> and <a href="/tags/dalna/"><em>dalna</em></a>, and <em>khichuri</em>).</p>
<p>The <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Bengali <em>garam masala</em></a> and <em>shahi garam masala</em> are both must-haves in the Bengali kitchen. But if you must pick just one, go the extra mile and keep a small reserve of the <em>shahi</em> version in your arsenal. You’ll be surprised at its transformative powers.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 10 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 15 g of <em>shahi garam masala</em> powder</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2 g (5-cm log)</td>
<td>Cinnamon (darchini)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g (30 pieces)</td>
<td>Cloves (lobongo)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g (30 pieces)</td>
<td>Green cardamom (elach)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Black cardamom (boro elach)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Nutmeg (jaiphol) shavings</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Mace (joyitree)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 g (4 pieces)</td>
<td>Bay leaves (tej pata)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 g (2 pieces)</td>
<td>Dried red chillies (shukhno lonka)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g (80 pieces)</td>
<td>Black peppercorn (golmorich)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | wok | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Airtight container</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder | mortar and pestle</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Measure out the whole spices in the given proportion. You may lightly crush them with a pestle or rolling pin before roasting, if you like.</li>
<li>Heat a pan on medium-low flame and add the whole spices to the pan.</li>
<li>Dry-roast them evenly on all sides, stirring continuously, for about 5 minutes. You should be able to smell the fragrance of the <em>shahi garam masala</em> by this point.</li>
<li>Add the toasted spices to a grinder and blitz them till you have a fine powder. You can also use a mortar and pestle to grind by hand.</li>
<li>Store the <em>shahi garam masala</em> powder in an airtight container.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A sweet, fragrant blend of ‘royal’ spices, ideal for flavouring egg, chicken, mutton, beef, or lamb curries.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="masala" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/masala/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Chicken Curry</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/chicken-curry/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/chicken-curry/</id>
    <published>2017-03-23T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-07T01:26:38.551Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Hot and spicy, decadent and comforting</p>

<p class="post-intro">This versatile chicken curry can be eaten with rice for a hearty weeknight dinner, or as part of an elaborate Sunday lunch.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his chicken curry recipe yields tender chicken pieces in a hot, flavourful, stew-like <em>jhol</em> (curry). The defining characteristic of the Bengali-style chicken curry is the presence of potatoes, which, when cooked in the curry, become soft and succulent, full of all the juicy goodness of the curry. This recipe has two parts: the first involves marinating the chicken, and the second, preparing the curry.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE MARINADE</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Onions (sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Garlic (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>60 g</td>
<td>Yoghurt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/">Garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Lime juice</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>FOR THE CURRY</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 kg</td>
<td>Chicken (cut and cleaned)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (halved or quartered; 6 pcs)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Onions (thinly sliced)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Dried red chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Bay leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 pcs</td>
<td>Cloves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pc</td>
<td>Cinnamon</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 pcs</td>
<td>Peppercorns</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (optional; finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Hot water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Microwaveable bowl (optional)</li>
<li>Cling film (optional)</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Refrigerator</li>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Microwave oven (optional)</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—MARINATING THE CHICKEN</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In a mixing bowl large enough to hold all the chicken, combine the components of the marinade: that is, sliced onions, chopped garlic, ginger paste, chopped green chillies, yoghurt, turmeric powder (10 g), red chilli powder, <a href="/recipe/shahi-garam-masala/"><em>garam masala</em></a> powder, salt (10 g), lime juice, and raw mustard oil. Don’t throw the lime peel away.</li>
<li>Give these a good mix and then add the chicken to the bowl.</li>
<li>Coat the chicken pieces in the marinade, making sure to get into all the nooks and crannies of the chicken. If you are also cooking the chicken liver, don’t toss it in the marinade along with the other pieces of the chicken, as it might disintegrate. Instead, add the liver after all the chicken pieces are well coated, and smear the liver with the marinade then.</li>
<li>Stick the used lime peel in between the chicken pieces.</li>
<li>Cover the bowl and rest the marinated chicken in the refrigerator for at least 2 hours. For best results, leave it to marinate overnight.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—PREPARING THE CURRY</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Peel and divide the potatoes into 4-cm halves or quarters. Put these in a microwave-safe bowl, add 2 tablespoons of water, cover the bowl with a cling film, and microwave for about 3 to 4 minutes. Alternatively, you can also parboil the potatoes in water on the stove.</li>
<li>Cut the onions in thin slices. Thinly sliced onions (as opposed to roughly chopped or diced onions) give the curry the perfect texture.</li>
<li>Heat 30 g mustard oil in a <em>kadai</em>. Once the oil has started to smoke lightly and changed colour to a pale yellow, temper it with dried red chillies, bay leaves, cardamom, cinnamon, cloves, and peppercorns.</li>
<li>Add in the onions, along with the sugar, and fry them for about 8 to 10 minutes, till the onions are brown in colour. (We add the sugar at this stage to help the onions caramelize quickly.)</li>
<li>Once the onions have caramelized, add 8 g turmeric powder and 18 g salt, along with 75 g of water.</li>
<li>Fry the spices on medium heat till the water dries up. This should take about 5 minutes.</li>
<li>Tip the marinated chicken into the <em>kadai</em> (don’t forget to remove the lime peel from the bowl!), and mix it with the onions in the pan. Cook the chicken on medium heat for about 15 minutes, stirring occasionally. This will ensure that the smell of raw spices from the marinade is gone.</li>
<li>Add in the parboiled potatoes and slit green chillies, and stir them in.</li>
<li>Add 400 g of hot water to the pan. This will form the curry.</li>
<li>Cover the pan and let the curry bubble for about 15 to 20 minutes, or till the chicken and potatoes are tender.</li>
<li>Garnish with chopped coriander leaves.  </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li>Roti | <a href="/recipe/luchi/">Luchi</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A hot, spicy, and delicious Bengali chicken curry, packed full of the flavours of ginger, garlic, and shahi garam masala.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="chicken" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/chicken/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Coffee House Egg Sandwich</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/coffee-house-egg-sandwich/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/coffee-house-egg-sandwich/</id>
    <published>2017-03-16T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-17T01:33:03.940Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A light, airy tea-time snack from Calcutta’s legendary Coffee House</p>

<p class="post-intro">Warm, fluffy triangles of bread with a buttery, yellow filling of boiled eggs at its centre, this is, quite possibly, the Coffee House’s daintiest dish.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><em>[In this series, we tip our hats to some of our favourite dishes available in the restaurants, cafés, and cabins of Calcutta. Our purpose in doing so is to document their existence, and give people a way to recreate them if they happen to live away from the city. Make these at home, or hunt them down from the source—irrespective of how you get your hands on these items, we hope you enjoy them.</em>]<br></p><p></p>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he Coffee Houses of Calcutta are part of the national chain of cafés called Indian Coffee House. They are managed and run as workers’ cooperatives, which makes the employees the owners of the café. The Coffee House is an institution in Calcutta, and has been at the centre of many a debate, discussion, and revolution. Even the current employee-owned nature of the chain is the result of a historic labour movement of the 1950s, spearheaded by Communist leader, A.K. Gopalan, which passed the ownership of the cafés into the hands of the workers.</p>

<p>Among the large number of items prepared in Calcutta Coffee House kitchens is an egg sandwich. It is light, airy, with a melt-in-your mouth filling of butter and eggs. On days when some of other dishes on the menu are too greasy for your liking, try these. Or just try them anyway with a cup of coffee. In this recipe we show you how to recreate them.</p>

<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 triangles</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>2 pieces</td>
<td>Eggs (boiled and peeled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Butter (softened)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Pepper (freshly crushed)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 slices</td>
<td>Bread</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Whisk</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Divide the softened butter into small cubes and transfer to a mixing bowl.</li>
<li>Using a whisk, cream the butter thoroughly until it changes color to a pale yellow. This will incorporate air into the butter, making the sandwiches light and fluffy.</li>
<li>Chop up the boiled eggs into fine pieces, and add them to the butter.</li>
<li>Add in the salt and pepper. The latter is the only flavouring used in this recipe. So make sure that the pepper is freshly ground.</li>
<li>Mix all the ingredients together till the butter and egg yolks combine to form a  creamy spread.</li>
<li>Take 50 g of this filling spread it evenly between two slices of bread.</li>
<li>Trim the edges, cut diagonally into triangles, and the sandwiches are ready to eat!  </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Tea</li>
<li>Coffee</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      These light and airy egg sandwiches à la Calcutta Coffee House make the perfect snack to accompany an evening cup of tea or coffee.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="snack" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/snack/"/>
    
      <category term="cabin food" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/cabin-food/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Jhuri Alu Bhaja</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/jhuri-alu-bhaja/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/jhuri-alu-bhaja/</id>
    <published>2017-03-09T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-10T03:49:25.220Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Crisp, golden, Bengali potato fries</p>

<p class="post-intro">This step-by-step recipe walks you through the process of making the perfect, crunchy <em>jhuri alu bhaja</em>.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">J</span><em>huri alu bhaja</em> needs no qualification to occupy a spot in the Bengali cooking canon. Crispy, fried potato juliennes—served alongside some steaming rice, hot <em>dal</em>, and a wedge of lemon—tend to justify their own existence.<br></p><p></p>
<p>For this recipe, we’ve borrowed the principles of French-fry making, and applied them to <em>jhuri alu bhaja</em>. Three important things need to be kept in mind: (1) The cut potatoes should be washed in plenty of water to rid them of starch; (2) before frying, the potatoes must be thoroughly dried—any moisture will yield limp fries; and (3) the potato juliennes must be fried in a pan full of oil, at a steady temperature of 180°C (that is, the oil should be hot, but not so hot that it begins to smoke).</p>

<p>Without further ado, let’s get into the step-by-step guide to making the perfectly crisp <em>jhuri alu bhaja</em> every single time.</p>

<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 45 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 8 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Potatoes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Peanuts</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 sprig</td>
<td>Curry leaves</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>500 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Pepper (crushed)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Rock salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Chaat masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Any good slicer</li>
<li>Sharp knife</li>
<li>2–3 clean, absorbent towels</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Frying spoon | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Using a slicer, cut the potatoes into 2-mm-thick slices. Alternatively, you can also use a sharp knife cut thin slices by hand. Reserve the slices in a large bowl of water to prevent the potatoes from oxidizing.</li>
<li>Wash the potato slices in plenty of water to remove the starch. Doing so will allow the <em>alu bhaja</em> to crisp up nicely. Change the water 2–3 times during this process to make sure that most of the starch is gone. Drain the water when done.</li>
<li>Now, lay out absorbent towels on a surface and spread out the washed potato slices in a single layer. We want the potatoes to be completely dry before we move on to the next stage—moisture will make the fries limp. Take your time. Dab them with another towel, or let them air dry for long as it takes for them to be completely dry.</li>
<li>Bunch together 5–6 slices at a time, and chop them into matchsticks, 2-mm-wide.</li>
<li>Heat about 500 g vegetable oil in a pan. The secret to non-greasy fries is to use a lot of oil. The excessive amount of oil will allow the potato juliennes to float freely, rather than lump together and trap steam. The temperature of the oil is also important for this recipe. It should be adequately hot (at around 180°C), but should never reach the smoking point.</li>
<li>Once the oil is hot, fry the peanuts for 20 seconds, drain, and reserve for later. Do the same with the curry leaves, frying them for 10 seconds.</li>
<li>Now, drop a small handful of potatoes into the oil. It is important not to overcrowd the pan. When the potatoes hit the oil, they will release a lot of steam. With time, the bubbles will gradually start subsiding (in about 3 minutes or so). The process of frying essentially serves to dehydrate the potatoes—and <em>that</em> is what lets them turn crisp, and stay crisp, longer. When the moisture has evaporated as steam bubbles, you know that the <em>alu bhaja</em> is crunchy. Fry for another 2 minutes for it to develop colour.</li>
<li>Strain the <em>alu bhaja</em> from the oil, and transfer to a perforated vessel (such as a colander or wicker basket) to cool. A basket allows the remaining steam to get out. Otherwise the steam will condense into water as the fries cool, making them limp.</li>
<li>Garnish with the fried peanuts and curry leaves.</li>
<li>FOR THE SEASONING, mix together the freshly ground pepper, salt, rock salt, chaat masala, and red chilli powder in the given proportions. Sprinkle this mix on the <em>alu bhaja</em> just before eating. Salt, being hygroscopic, tends to absorb moisture from the air, and turn the crisps soggy. Without the seasoning, the <em>alu bhaja</em> should keep for up to 7 days in an airtight container.  </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A step-by-step recipe that walks you through the process of making the perfectly fine, crisp, golden potato fries every single time.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Lau’er Khosha Bhaja</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/lauer-khosha-bhaja/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/lauer-khosha-bhaja/</id>
    <published>2017-03-03T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:47.033Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A tasty stir-fry made from the peels of bottle gourd</p>

<p class="post-intro">Simple, quick, and easy, the <em>lau’er khosha bhaja</em> is as nutritious as it is delicious.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>his recipe is part of that tradition in Bengali cooking which was born out of hardship. It makes use of vegetable parts that would otherwise have been thrown away—the <em>lau’er khosha</em> or peels of bottle gourd. Bengal has been unfortunate to witness a number of travesties throughout its history—two very major famines, the Partition, and a number of instances of large-scale migration. Even though the region has been blessed with agricultural abundance, these events, especially the famines, forced cooks to think of alternative means of sustenance. They turned to scraps, not-so-fresh vegetable rejects at the <em>bazaar</em>, and tough, fibrous parts of plants that no one thought to eat previously. The shrewd skills of the cooks, the women of the household, were called upon to make these throwaway items delectable. Several such recipes have survived to the modern day. Times may not be so tough, but the fact that we still actively seek out and prepare such dishes is testament to the sheer genius of our foremothers.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>175 g</td>
<td>Peels of lau (bottle gourd)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Dried red chilli</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pieces</td>
<td>Dal’er bori</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Grated coconut</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Green chilli (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grater | grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash the <em>lau</em> (bottle gourd) and divide it up in sections of 6 cm width.</li>
<li>Now, using a sharp knife, start peeling the <em>lau</em>, keeping the peels as thin as possible, but making sure not to break them.</li>
<li>Reserve the vegetable for use in another dish; for this recipe, we just need the peels.</li>
<li>Take each peel, one by one, and start cutting it in 2mm-wide strips. Basically, we first thinly slice 6cm-long sections of the peel, and further julienne them in 2mm-wide matchsticks. Take your time with the cutting, as this will determine the texture of the finished product.</li>
<li>Place the cut peels in a saucepan and cover them with water.</li>
<li>Steam them with the lid on for 5 minutes. We don’t want to cook the peels at this stage, just parboil them.</li>
<li>Strain over a colander and set aside.</li>
<li>Heat 15 g mustard oil in a <em>kadai</em> till lightly smoking.</li>
<li>Add the <em>dal’er bori</em> and fry them for about 20 seconds, till they are golden. Remove from the pan, roughly break them with your fingers into small shards, and set aside.</li>
<li>Now, temper the same oil with a dried red chilli, bay leaf, and <em>kaalo jeere</em>.</li>
<li>Add the parboiled peels and stir-fry them for 5 minutes.</li>
<li>Add in the grated coconut and a slit green chilli, and stir-fry again for a minute.</li>
<li>Next, introduce the salt and turmeric powder. Cover and cook on low heat for about 6 minutes. Stir every so often to prevent the peels from sticking to the bottom of the pan.</li>
<li>Mix in the sugar, and cook again for a couple of minutes.</li>
<li>Finally, sprinkle the chopped coriander leaves and shards of fried <em>bori</em>. Mix them in, and cover for 2 minutes to allow all the flavours to mingle together, before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A simple, quick, and easy stir-fry made from bottle-gourd peels, the lau’er khosha bhaja is as nutritious as it is delicious.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Pabda Machh&#39;er Tel Jhol</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/pabda-machher-tel-jhol/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/pabda-machher-tel-jhol/</id>
    <published>2017-02-23T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:31.816Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A flavourful, light curry with <em>pabda</em> fish</p>

<p class="post-intro">It is unbelievable that something with a handful of ingredients can taste so divine.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he <em>pabda machh</em> is one of the most beloved of Bengal’s fishes. It is sweet to the taste, flaky, and delicately flavoured. To top it all off, it is also extremely easy to eat, as it contains no bones besides the central skeleton. This recipe, <em>pabda machh’er tel jhol</em>, is a delicacy in Bengali cooking. ‘<em>Tel jhol</em>’ is the name given to a light curry, which is infused with <em>kaalo jeere</em>, green chillies, and mustard oil. Because it is sparsely spiced, this style of curry doesn’t overpower the star ingredient—the fish—but lets it shine on its own. If you have managed to procure a batch of fresh <em>pabda</em>, this should be your go-to <em>jhol</em>.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 30 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>450 g</td>
<td>Pabda machh (cut and cleaned)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>35 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for garnish)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Tomato (roughly chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 pieces</td>
<td>Dal’er bori</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Brinjal (5-cm segments)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g (plus ¾ tsp extra for marinating)</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g (plus ¾ tsp extra for marinating)</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Atta (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>400 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Electric kettle (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPPING THE INGREDIENTS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Smear the cut and cleaned <em>padba machh</em> with ¾ tsp turmeric powder, ¾ tsp salt, and 1 tsp mustard oil. Mix till the fish are well coated, and set aside.</li>
<li>Cut the brinjal into 5-cm segments. We need as many pieces of brinjal as there are fish—in this case, five.</li>
<li>Roughly chop the tomatoes.</li>
<li>Slit the green chillies.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—FRYING THE <em>BORI</em>, BRINJAL, AND FISH</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Heat your <em>kadai</em> well and add 35 g mustard oil to the pan.</li>
<li>Once the oil is completely hot (that is, once it has begun to smoke lightly and changed colour to a pale yellow), add the <em>dal’er bori</em>.</li>
<li>Fry the <em>boris</em> for about 20 seconds till they are golden brown. They colour very quickly, so be alert while frying them.</li>
<li>Remove the <em>boris</em> from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Next, add the brinjal pieces to the oil.</li>
<li>Stir-fry for about 4 minutes till they are golden. Remove them from the oil and set aside.</li>
<li>Now, in batches, fry the marinated fish. Fresh, sweetwater fish such as the <em>pabda</em> do not need heavy searing. Fry them lightly to preserve their delicate flavour. A minute on each side should do the job.</li>
<li>Remove the fried fish on a plate and reserve for later use.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—MAKING THE <em>JHOL</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Before we start, make a paste with 15 g salt, 6 g turmeric powder, and 50 g water. Mix and keep ready.</li>
<li>Heat 7 g mustard oil in the <em>kadai</em>. (If the oil that you fried the fish in is not burnt, you may use the same oil to prepare the <em>jhol</em>.)</li>
<li>Add the <em>kaalo jeere</em>, tomatoes, and 3 green chillies to the oil.</li>
<li>Fry them for a minute on medium heat.</li>
<li>Add the turmeric and salt mixture to the pan, and fry till the water in the spice mix dries up.</li>
<li>Now, pour 400 g of hot water (either heated in an electric kettle or on the stove) into the pan. This will form the curry.</li>
<li>Once the curry starts to simmer, add in the fried <em>boris</em>.</li>
<li>Simmer for another 2 minutes before lowering in the <em>pabda machh</em>, one by one. Also add the fish drippings that might have collected on the plate that held the fried fish; they are delicious.</li>
<li>Add the fried brinjal to the curry.</li>
<li>Let everything bubble for about 5 minutes. As the curry boils, you will notice that the colour of the <em>jhol</em> has changed from deep yellow to bright yellow. That’s when you know that the turmeric is cooked, and that the curry won’t taste of the raw spice.</li>
<li>Now, pick one of the softened green chillies from the curry onto a small bowl. Add ½ tsp <em>atta</em> to it, along with 1 tbsp of water. Mash the three together, until paste-like.</li>
<li>Add this mixture to the <em>jhol</em>. The mashed green chilli will release the heat, while the flour will help the curry thicken and develop body.</li>
<li>Garnish with 2 more slit green chillies, a drizzle of mustard oil (about 7 g), and chopped coriander.</li>
<li>Allow everything to bubble for a couple of more minutes, before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A light, hearty, delicious delicacy, the padba macher tel jhol is packed with the flavours of Bengal’s prized sweetwater pabda fish.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="pabda machh" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pabda-machh/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Panch Phoron</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/panch-phoron/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/panch-phoron/</id>
    <published>2017-02-16T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:27.029Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Bengali five-spice mix for tempering oil</p>

<p class="post-intro"><em>Panch phoron</em> is popularly used to temper dals, vegetables (such as <a href="/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/"><em>panchmishali torkari</em></a> or <em>shada alu’r torkari</em>), <em>chutneys</em> (those with tomatoes or raw mangoes), or <em>achaars</em> (such as raw-mango pickles).</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he cooking of most Bengali dishes starts with the <em>phoron</em>. What this typically involves is heating up the oil (usually mustard oil), and once hot, adding a selection of whole spices to it. This ‘tempers’ the oil, transferring the flavours of the spices to it. This might seem like a tiny, inconsequential step (the process of tempering doesn’t take more than a few seconds), but no Bengali cook has ever skipped it. Is is what prepares the oil for cooking. In many cases, the choice of <em>phoron</em> defines the flavour profile of the recipe (think of a dish like <a href="/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/"><em>panchmishali torkari</em></a>, or a fish curry like <em>tel jhol</em>). There are myriad combinations of spices used for <em>phoron</em> in Bengali cooking, and while that is subject for another post, here we look at the most definitive of Bengali tempering spices—the <em>panch phoron</em>.</p>
<p><em>Panch phoron</em> literally means five spices used for tempering. Apart from the Bengali cuisine, variations of this spice mix are used in Assamese, Oriya, and Nepali cooking as well. The Bengali version comprises <em>mouri</em> (fennel seeds), <em>methi</em> (fenugreek seeds), <em>kaalo jeere</em> (nigella seeds), <em>shorshe</em> (mustard seeds), and a typically Bengali spice, called <em>radhuni</em>. If you can’t find <em>radhuni</em> where you live, cumin seeds make an acceptable substitute.</p>
<p>The <em>panch phoron</em> is used like any other <em>phoron</em>. You heat up the mustard oil thoroughly, till it starts to smoke lightly and turns pale yellow in colour. You then add as much <em>panch phoron</em> as the recipe calls for to the oil. The spices will start cracking immediately (mostly because of the mustard seeds in the mix) and give out a distinctive, bitter-sweet-anisey aroma. However, watch the <em>methi</em> in the mix carefully; it tends to redden, burn quite easily, and turn bitter. So, always have the next ingredient in line prepped and ready, to add to the pan, and bring down the temperature of the oil.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 5 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 50 g of <em>panch phoron</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>mouri (fennel seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>methi (fenugreek seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>shorshe (mustard seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tbsp</td>
<td>radhuni</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>A small storage container</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p>Mix all the whole spices together in equal proportions and store in an airtight container.</p>
<h2 id="Used-to"><a href="#Used-to" class="headerlink" title="Used to"></a>Used to</h2><ul>
<li>Temper <a href="/tags/dal/">dals</a></li>
<li>Temper vegetarian dishes such as the delicious <a href="/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/">panchmishali torkari</a></li>
<li>Temper chutneys</li>
<li>Flavour pickles</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Easy-to-make, authentic, Bengali five-spice tempering mix, using fennel seeds, fenugreek seeds, mustard seeds, nigella seeds, and radhuni.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="masala" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/masala/"/>
    
      <category term="how-to" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/how-to/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Phulkopi&#39;r Bora | Cauliflower fritters</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/phulkopir-bora/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/phulkopir-bora/</id>
    <published>2017-02-09T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:14.024Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Crispy, golden cauliflower fritters</p>

<p class="post-intro">In all their batter-fried goodness, these humble fritters are sure to brighten up your meal.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">P</span><em>hulkopi’r bora</em> are ideal to make in the gorgeous winter months, when the cauliflower is in season. They are so easy to prepare that they make for excellent last-minute addition to the day’s menu. The batter is simple. It is flour and water, mildly seasoned with some salt, sugar, and green chillies. <em>Kaalo jeere</em> provides a subtle fragrance, while <em>posto</em> adds crunch. We top batter off with a bit of raw, pungent mustard oil for crispiness. Golden-brown and crisp from the outside, and soft inside, these fried <em>phulkopi’r bora</em> are best had with some <a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">hot rice</a> and <a href="/tags/dal/">dal</a>, although they make a pretty good afternoon snack too.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>150 g</td>
<td>Cauliflower (3-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>50 g</td>
<td>Maida (all-purpose flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>3 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 pinch</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 g</td>
<td>Posto (poppy seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>green chilli (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~ 250 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil (for deep-frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Sauce pan | boiling pot (with lid)</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Forks</li>
<li><em>Jhhajhhri</em> | perforated spoon</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Divide the cauliflower into florets, 3 cm large, and transfer them to a saucepan.</li>
<li>Add hot water to the pan and steam the florets, with the lid on, for 3 minutes. Remember, we don’t want to cook the cauliflower completely at this stage. The florets will be deep-fried later; we just want to give them a head-start. Three minutes of steaming should do the trick.</li>
<li>Drain the florets immediately and set aside to cool.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, prepare a batter by mixing flour, salt, sugar, turmeric, <em>kaalo jeere</em>, <em>posto</em>, green chilli, mustard oil, and water in the given proportions.</li>
<li>Mix the batter till well combined.</li>
<li>Set a <em>kadai</em> on the stove and heat it up. Add vegetable oil to the pan, at least 4 cm deep.</li>
<li>On medium flame, allow the oil to heat up completely (200 degree C). You can check by dropping some batter into the oil, and if it floats to the top immediately, with bubbles all around it, the oil is good to go.</li>
<li>Dunk the steamed cauliflower florets into the batter one at a time and coat them well.</li>
<li>Gently drop them into the oil. You can fry about 4 to 8 florets at a time, depending on the size of your pan. But be sure not to overcrowd the pan, or the florets won’t fry evenly from all sides.</li>
<li>Turning them over occasionally, fry the fritters till they are golden-brown.</li>
<li>Once done, remove them from the oil with the help of a perforated spoon. The best way to drain oil is by holding the <em>boras</em> against the side of the hot pan for about 20 seconds.</li>
<li>Sprinkle with some rock salt (<em>beet noon</em>) and serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Cauliflower fritters, coated with a simple flour batter and traditional Bengali spices, and deep-fried till golden-brown and delicious.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
      <category term="cauliflower" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/cauliflower/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Bhaja Moong Dal Shobji diye</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/bhaja-moong-dal-shobji-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/bhaja-moong-dal-shobji-diye/</id>
    <published>2017-02-02T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:14:17.107Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Roasted dehulled moong dal with fresh, winter veggies</p>

<p class="post-intro">Bright and colourful, the <em>shobji diye bhaja moong’er dal</em> is bound to floor you with its heady, nutty aroma.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">W</span>hat makes <em>bhaja moong’er dal</em> the most beloved of all <a href="/tags/dal/"><em>dals</em></a> is the fact that it is rich and comforting, without being entirely over-the-top. With this <em>dal</em>, you can get away with serving the simplest of <a href="/tags/torkari/"><em>torkari</em></a> or <a href="/tags/bhaja/"><em>bhaja</em></a> as it elevates any meal that it is part of. This version of the <em>bhaja moong’er dal</em>—one with cauliflower, carrots, and peas—is best enjoyed in the winter months, when these vegetables are fresh and in season. Even though this <em>dal</em> is reserved for special occasions, it is so incredibly simple to make that there is no reason it cannot become part of your regular winter fare.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Moong dal (split gram)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>550 g</td>
<td>Water (for boiling dal)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Dried red chilli (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaf (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Clove (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Carrots (1-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Cauliflower (2-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Tomatoes (roughly chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Peas (shelled)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td><a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/">Garam masala powder</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
<li>Boiling pot | saucepan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Weigh out the <em>dal</em> and add it to a dry pot (preferably a <em>kadai</em> or wok), set on medium heat.</li>
<li>Dry-roast the <em>dal</em>, stirring continuously, till it changes colour from yellow to a pinkish brown. Here, it is important to keep the <em>dal</em> moving while it is in the pan to ensure that all surfaces of the grains roast evenly. Be particularly alert once the <em>dal</em> has taken on a light, brown colour, as it is during this stage that the <em>dal</em> has the tendency to burn easily.</li>
<li>Transfer the roasted <em>dal</em> into a boiling pot immediately (do not hold it in the hot pan, as it will continue to brown when kept in contact with heat).</li>
<li>Wash and rinse the <em>dal</em> thoroughly.</li>
<li>Add 550 g water to the washed <em>dal</em>.</li>
<li>Boil it on medium heat for about 20 minutes. While we want the <em>dal</em> to be completely cooked, we still want the individual grains to remain unbroken. So, check frequently to ensure that the dal doesn’t turn into mush and lose its texture.</li>
<li>Chop the cauliflower into 2-cm florets, the carrot into 1-cm cubes, and the tomatoes roughly. Shell the peas and slit the green chillies.</li>
<li>Heat up the <em>kadai</em> once more and add 10 g mustard oil.</li>
<li>Once the oil has smoked lightly and lost its pungent smell, temper it with the dried red chilli, bay leaf, cardamom, cinnamon, clove, cumin seeds, and 1 green chilli.</li>
<li>Add the carrots and stir-fry them for 1 minute.</li>
<li>Next, add the cauliflower florets and fry them for another minute.</li>
<li>Add the tomatoes and peas, one at a time, and fry them for a minute after each addition.</li>
<li>Pour in the roasted, boiled <em>dal</em> with its water.</li>
<li>Add the salt, sugar and turmeric, and stir them in.</li>
<li>Allow the <em>dal</em> to bubble for about 6 minutes on low heat. Don’t increase the heat level or the liquid in the <em>dal</em> may dry up.</li>
<li>Garnish with chopped coriander leaves, a slit green chilli, <a href="/recipe/bengali-garam-masala/"><em>garam masala</em> powder</a>, and <em>ghee</em>.</li>
<li>Cover the pan with a lid and allow the <em>dal</em> to soak up the flavours from the garnish before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
<li><a href="/tags/torkari/">Torkari</a> | <a href="/tags/bhaja/">bhaja</a> | <a href="/recipe/alu-sheddho/">alu sheddho</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      A gorgeous-looking traditional Bengali vegetarian dal with roasted yellow mung beans, simmered with cauliflowers, carrots and peas.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/dal/"/>
    
      <category term="moong dal" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/moong-dal/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Panchmishali Torkari</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/panchmishali-torkari/</id>
    <published>2017-01-26T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:23.172Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Simple Bengali mixed veggies with <em>panch phoron</em> tempering</p>

<p class="post-intro"><em>Panchmishali torkari</em> is any Bengali mixed-vegetable preparation, in which the vegetables are first stir-fried and then steamed in their own juices till they are tender and well-integrated.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">A</span>s you might have guessed, the stars of this dish are the veggies themselves. This is not a preparation in which you spice up things with ginger or cumin powder or red chilli powder. The only spice this recipe calls for is a touch of turmeric. Mostly, it relies on the salt and sugar to help draw out the moisture from the vegetables, and allow their flavours to mingle while cooked together. We don’t add water to form a gravy. Rather we cook this <em>torkari</em> on low heat, with the lid on, for nearly 30 to 40 minutes. At the end of this slow cooking process, it reaches a state where no vegetable stands out, yet each has still held on to its flavours and integrity.</p>
<p>Coming to the selection of the veggies themselves, some type of starchy item such as a potato or sweet potato is used. These, being otherwise neutral in taste, are the perfect receptacle of the juices from the other vegetables. The mushy texture is usually contributed by pumpkin, while radish is used for the more sharper notes. Some kind of beans (such as <em>borboti</em> or <em>sheem</em>) add crunch and colour. In the winter months, cauliflower lends the most sublime flavour to the <em>torkari</em>, in addition to providing texture. Finally, slimier vegetables such as brinjals, or cabbage or leafy greens that are prone to wilting on application of heat and salt, coat the mix with their juices and hold everything together.</p>
<p>There are several versions of <em>panchmishali torkari</em>. The choice of <em>phoron</em> (or tempering) will depend on the vegetables used. In this particular recipe, we are using potatoes, sweet potatoes, pumpkin, cauliflower, <em>borboti</em> (yardlong beans), cabbage, and brinjal, with a tempering of <em>panch phoron</em>.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 60 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>OIL</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>TEMPERING (PHORON)</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pieces</td>
<td>Bay leaves (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pieces</td>
<td>Dried red chillies (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Green chilli (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Panch phoron</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>THE VEGETABLES</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Brinjals (5-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (4-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Sweet potatoes (4-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Pumpkin (4-cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>200 g</td>
<td>Cauliflower (5-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Borboti or yardlong beans (5-cm segments)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g</td>
<td>Cabbage (5-cm segments)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>THE SEASONING</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>12 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>THE GARNISH</strong></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (chopped)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>½ tsp</td>
<td>Bhaja masala</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPPING THE VEGETABLES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Peel and cut the potatoes, sweet potatoes, and pumpkin in 4 cm cubes.</li>
<li>Cut the <em>borboti</em>, brinjal, and cabbage in segments of 5 cm each.</li>
<li>Cut the cauliflower in florets, 5 cm large.</li>
<li>In order to cook <em>panchmishali torkari</em>, the vegetables are stir-fried, and the order in which they are added to the pan depends upon their hardness. So, the potatoes and sweet potatoes, which are the hardest of all the veggies, are the first to enter the pan, followed by pumpkin, cauliflower, <em>borboti</em>, and cabbage. We deal with the brinjals separately, as explained in the next step.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—FRYING THE VEGETABLES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Heat mustard oil in a pan till it starts to smoke lightly and the pungent smell is gone.</li>
<li>Keeping the pan on medium heat, add in the brinjals and fry them for about 3 minutes till they are golden.</li>
<li>Remove them from pan and reserve for later use. Frying the brinjals separately enhances their flavour.</li>
<li>Now, in the same oil, add the tempering of dried red chillies, bay leaves, green chilli, and <em>panch phoron</em>. <em>Panch phoron</em> is a mix of the following whole spices in equal proportion: fenugreek seeds (<em>methi</em>), fennel seeds (<em>mouri</em>), mustard seeds (<em>shorshe</em>), nigella seeds (<em>kaalo jeere</em>), and a typically Bengali spice called <em>radhuni</em>.</li>
<li>Once the spices start to crackle, add in the potatoes and sweet potatoes to the oil.</li>
<li>Fry these for about 3 minutes before introducing the next vegetable, that is, pumpkin.</li>
<li>Fry the pumpkin, sweet potatoes, and potatoes together for another 3 minutes before adding the cauliflower. Basically, at intervals of 3 minutes, we add the next vegetable and stir-fry it together with the veggies already in the pan.</li>
<li>Once the cauliflower is fried, add the <em>borboti</em>, and then, after 3 minutes, the cabbage.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—STEAMING THE VEGETABLES</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Once all the veggies have been fried, add in the salt and turmeric, and stir them in.</li>
<li>At this point, lower the heat and cover the pan with a lid. The salt will help release the moisture from the vegetables, and gently steaming them with the lid on will help soften them up.</li>
<li>Cook the vegetables like this for about 15 minutes. Stir occasionally to prevent them from sticking to the bottom of the pan. While doing so, be gentle, as the we don’t want the vegetables to turn into mush. (Always use a folding motion to stir the veggies around.)</li>
<li>After 15 minutes, add the sugar and the fried brinjals, and cover and cook for another 10 minutes or so, stirring occasionally.</li>
<li>You will know that the <em>torkari</em> is done when the vegetables are completely tender and have integrated themselves into the dish, but still have the integrity to not fall apart to the touch.</li>
<li>At this point, garnish with the chopped coriander leaves, green chillies, <em>bhaja masala</em>, and <em>ghee</em>.</li>
<li>Turn off the heat, cover the pan, and allow it to rest for 2 minutes before serving.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | Roti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Video recipe of authentic, vegetarian Bengali dish of cauliflower, beans, sweet potatoes, eggplants, cooked with panch phoron tempering.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Koi Machh&#39;er Jhol Phulkopi diye</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/koi-machher-jhol-phulkopi-diye/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/koi-machher-jhol-phulkopi-diye/</id>
    <published>2017-01-19T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:51.227Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Everyone’s favourite <em>machh’er jhol</em> for the winter months</p>

<p class="post-intro">This is a light curry of the climbing perch fish (<em>koi machh</em>) and fried cauliflower florets.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">K</span><em>oi machh</em> is a delicacy in Bengali cooking. Also known as the climbing perch fish because of its ability <em>climb</em> out of water and walk on land for short distances, <em>koi machh</em> is <em>always</em> bought live at fish markets. It has an extremely slippery exterior, making the use of ash rather necessary while handling the fish for cleaning. Even if the <em>koi machh</em> is scaled, degilled, and cleaned by your fish-seller, it might still be quite slimy to the touch. At home, you may need to rub the fish against an abrasive surface to get rid of the slipperiness (a perforated, steel colander-plate does this job quite well).</p>
<p>Coming to this recipe, its main ingredients, <em>koi machh</em> and <em>phulkopi</em> (cauliflower), are fried separately to enhance their flavours, and then added to the delicious <em>jhol</em>. The <em>jhol</em> itself is a hot, gingery, <em>garam-masala</em>-infused curry that is mildly sweet, but never too spicy. It uplifts the taste of anything it gets soaked up in—potatoes, cauliflower, <em>bori</em>, or the fish. Eaten with a generous helping of steaming hot rice, this dish, the <em>phulkopi diye koi machh’er jhol</em> is the Bengali’s favourite fish curry for the winter months.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 5 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for cooking)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>350 g (or 5 pieces)</td>
<td>Koi machh (climbing perch fish)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>150 g (or 5 pieces)</td>
<td>Cauliflower (5-cm florets)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>100 g (or 5 pieces)</td>
<td>Potatoes (cut lengthwise)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 pieces</td>
<td>Dal’er bori</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>20 g</td>
<td>Tomato (3-cm quarters)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Cumin seeds (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2 pcs</td>
<td>Cardamom (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Cinnamon (whole)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Bay leaf</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pieces</td>
<td>Green chillies (slit)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>7 g</td>
<td>Ginger paste</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Cumin powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 g (plus ¾ tsp for marinating)</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 g</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>18 g (plus ¾ tsp for marinating)</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>350 g</td>
<td>Water (hot)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6 g</td>
<td>Coriander leaves (finely chopped)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li><em>Kadai</em> | frying pan</li>
<li>Lid for the cooking vessel</li>
<li><em>Khunti</em> | long spatula</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—PREPPING THE INGREDIENTS</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Smear the <em>koi machh</em> with ¾ tsp each of salt and turmeric till they are evenly coated. Set them aside.</li>
<li>Cut a cauliflower into chunky florets, about 5 cm large. Take as many florets as there are pieces of fish (in this case, five).</li>
<li>Peel and cut the potatoes lengthwise. Again, we need as many pieces of potatoes as there are fish.</li>
<li>Chop the tomato into 3-cm quarters.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—FRYING THE <em>BORI</em>, CAULIFLOWER, AND FISH</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Heat a <em>kadai</em> till it is completely hot. Drizzle 30 g mustard oil into the pan till it starts smoking lightly, and changes colour from deep to pale yellow.</li>
<li>Add all the <em>dal’er bori</em> into the oil and fry them till they are golden. This should take about 15–20 seconds. The bori tend to brown quickly, so stay on the watch.</li>
<li>Remove the fried <em>bori</em> from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>Now, add the cauliflower florets, along with ¼ tsp of salt, to the pan and fry them till they develop a light-brown colour. This should take about 4 minutes in all.</li>
<li>Remove the cauliflower from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>Finally, add the marinated <em>koi machh</em> to the same oil, one at a time, and fry them for no longer than a minute on each side. This is a freshwater fish with delicate flavours. So be sure not to sear the fish too long.</li>
<li>Remove the fish from the pan and set aside.</li>
<li>You now have fried <em>bori</em>, fried cauliflower, and fried fish ready for use at a later stage, and can now move on to the preparation of the curry.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—MAKING THE <em>JHOL</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>At this point, inspect the oil in your pan. If it looks too burnt, replace it with 10 g of fresh mustard oil. If it is alright, use the same oil to cook the curry in as it contains all the flavour from the fried fish.</li>
<li>Temper the oil, set on medium heat, with the bay leaf, cardamom, cinnamon, cumin seeds, and 2 slit green chillies.</li>
<li>Add the potatoes to the pan and fry them, with the lid on, for 4 minutes.</li>
<li>While the potatoes are frying, make a paste by combining cumin powder, turmeric powder, red chilli powder, salt, sugar, and 50 g water.</li>
<li>Add this mixture into the pan and fry it, with lid on, till the water dries up.</li>
<li>Now, add in the ginger paste and the tomatoes, and incorporate them with the spices. Introduce another 50 g water to the pan and sauté the spices again till the water dries off.</li>
<li>The key here is to cover and cook because, alongside sautéing the spices, we also want to allow time for the potatoes to become tender.</li>
<li>Add in the fried cauliflower florets, fold them into the spices, and cook them for a minute or so.</li>
<li>Now, add 350 g of hot water to the pan. This will form the curry.</li>
<li>Once it comes to a boil, add in the fried <em>bori</em>, fried fish, and two (more) of the slit green chillies.</li>
<li>Using a spoon, gently try and submerge the fish in the curry. Be delicate as the fish is quite fragile at this stage.</li>
<li>Cover the pan and allow the curry to simmer for about 6 minutes.</li>
<li>Chop fresh coriander and add it to the pan. Let it simmer in the curry for another minute before turning off the heat.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Video recipe for traditional Bengali fish curry made with koi fish simmered in a light gravy along with cauliflowers, bori and potatoes
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="non-vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/non-vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="fish" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/fish/"/>
    
      <category term="koi machh" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/koi-machh/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Patishapta (with kheer filling)</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/patishapta-with-kheer-filling/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/patishapta-with-kheer-filling/</id>
    <published>2017-01-12T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-04-07T01:27:44.885Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A thin, delicate crêpe filled with sweetened, reduced milk or <em>kheer</em></p>

<p class="post-intro">Winter is a Bengali’s favourite season. And what would winters in Bengal be without all the sweet <em>pithe</em>?</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he rice-harvest festival in Bengal, <em>poush sankranti</em>, is celebrated by making the most wondrous of sweets—the pithe. This is an umbrella term used to describe a variety of items prepared using rice, date-palm syrup (<em>patali gur</em>, only available in winter), coconut, milk, and flour. <em>Pithe</em> is no single dish, but a category of sweets that are part of the Bengali cooking tradition dedicated exclusively to turning the season’s harvest into delectable foods.</p>
<p><em>Patishapta</em> is a type of <em>pithe</em>. It is a light crêpe filled with either <em>kheer</em> or a coconut-and-<em>gur</em> mixture. In this recipe, we show you how to make the version with <em>kheer</em>.<br></p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 3 hours<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 16–17 <em>patishaptas</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><p><strong>FOR THE CRÊPE</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>75 g</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Sooji (semolina)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Rice grains</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>280 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>30 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>5 g</td>
<td>Ghee (for greasing)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>FOR THE <em>KHEER</em> (FILLING)</strong></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1.5 kg</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>65 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 tsp</td>
<td>Maida (flour)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Balloon whisk | fork (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Ladle (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Non-stick pan | <em>appam chatti</em> (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Long spatula | <em>khunti</em> (for the crêpes)</li>
<li>Heavy-bottom saucepan | boiling pot (for the <em>kheer</em>)</li>
<li>Wooden spoon (for the <em>kheer</em>)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><p><strong>STEP I—MAKE THE CRÊPE BATTER</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Add the rice grains to an electric grinder and blitz them to a fine powder. You now have rice flour.</li>
<li>In a mixing bowl, add the <em>maida</em> (75 g), <em>sooji</em> (30 g), rice flour (10 g), sugar (30 g), salt (¼ tsp), and milk (280 g).</li>
<li>Mix the ingredients together till they are more or less combined. Do not over-mix or your crêpes may turn out chewy.</li>
<li>Cover the batter and set it aside to rest, for 2 hours. This will allow time for the <em>sooji</em> to swell up and the sugar to melt.</li>
<li>While your batter is resting, prepare the <em>kheer</em>, which will form the filling for our <em>patishapta</em>.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP II—MAKE THE <em>KHEER</em> <a href="https://youtu.be/PzFXjD8D3AY?list=PLGX3dcCcJDYweaL6mlxJ54UAoKZAjNluz" target="_blank" rel="external">[WATCH HOW TO MAKE <em>KHEER</em>]</a></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Take 1.5 kg milk in a heavy-bottom saucepan and set it to boil.</li>
<li>Once bubbling, stir in 65 g sugar.</li>
<li>Keep boiling the milk, while stirring it continuously, for about 90 minutes.</li>
<li>During this entire time, the pot should be on medium to low heat.</li>
<li>At regular intervals of 3–4 minutes, be sure to scrape the solids from the bottom and sides of the pot, and incorporate them into the boiling milk. This step, as well as the previous one, is crucial. We don’t want our <em>kheer</em> to burn at any point.</li>
<li>Once the milk has thickened such that when you lift some of it on your spoon and drop it, it falls in clumps, make a paste of 1 tsp flour and 1 tbsp milk.</li>
<li>Add this paste to the pot. Stir and cook for another 5 minutes.</li>
<li>Allow the <em>kheer</em> to cool before proceeding to the next stage.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>STEP III—MAKE THE <em>PATISHAPTA</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Divide the <em>kheer</em> in equal portions of 22 g each.</li>
<li>Give your batter a quick stir till it is uniform.</li>
<li>Now, set a non-stick pan on medium-low flame and allow it to heat up completely.</li>
<li>Once the pan is hot, smear it with a very, <em>very</em> light coating of <em>ghee</em> (remember, we are already using a non-stick pan).</li>
<li>Using a ladle, take about 25 g of the batter and drop it in the centre of the pan.</li>
<li>Swirl it around gradually to form a thin crêpe, about 12 cm in diameter.</li>
<li>Roll a portion of the <em>kheer</em> between your palms to form a log (about 8 cm long), and flatten it with your fingers.</li>
<li>Place it at one end of the crêpe and start folding the crêpe into a roll, with the help of a spatula. [Note that we are cooking only one side of the crêpe.]</li>
<li>Transfer the <em>patishapta</em> from the pan to a plate and proceed making the rest. These can be eaten hot, or they can be cooled and stored in the refrigerator for up to 7 days.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      This Bengali sweet recipe is a type of &quot;pithe&quot;. It is a light crêpe filled with either kheer (reduced milk) or a coconut-and-gur mixture.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="sweets" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/sweets/"/>
    
      <category term="pithe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/pithe/"/>
    
      <category term="jolkhabar" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/jolkhabar/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Doodh Cha | Spiced Milk Tea</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/doodh-cha/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/doodh-cha/</id>
    <published>2017-01-05T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:57.821Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">A sweet, milky, aromatic concoction steeped with orange pekoe tea</p>

<p class="post-intro">What better way to unwind your days with than with a steaming mug of <em>doodh cha</em>?</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">E</span>ven though commercial cultivation of tea in the country was introduced by the British in the early 19th century, there is nothing else that India has made more its own than its <em>chai</em>. A popular drink across most of South Asia, from posh drawing rooms to humble street shacks, this is a boiled concoction of water, milk, sugar, tea, and occasionally, aromatic spices. Ours is a lighter version of the famed “masala chai” (spiced tea), a perfect accompaniment to an evening snack, be it simple <em>moori-chanachur</em> or something more elaborate. Make yourself this cup of “doodh cha”, not when you desperately need it, but when you feel like you’ve deserved it.</p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 15 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 2 mugs of tea</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Water</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Milk</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Ginger</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Clove</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Cardamom</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Orange pekoe tea</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mortar and pestle</li>
<li>Saucepan with lid</li>
<li>Tea strainer</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Using a mortar and pestle, roughly crush the clove and cardamom pod. This will help release their flavours.</li>
<li>Wash, peel, and dice the ginger roughly.</li>
<li>Set a saucepan over medium-high heat and add the water, clove, cardamom, and ginger.</li>
<li>Cover the pan and let the water come to a boil. Allow the spices to bubble in water for about 4 minutes.</li>
<li>Add the milk, and once it has heated up, add in the tea and sugar.</li>
<li>Allow this milky mixture to boil vigorously. Just when the tea is about to boil over, drop the heat and let it simmer for about 4 minutes. You can see the tea change colour from light brown to a rosy kind of orange.</li>
<li>Strain and serve immediately.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li>Biscuits | rusk</li>
<li>Evening snack</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      The Bengali version of the famous masala chai, or tea steeped milk flavoured with cardamom, ginger and spices
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="drink" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/drink/"/>
    
      <category term="tea" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/tea/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Begun Bhaja | Spicy Fried Eggplant or Brinjal</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/begun-bhaja/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/begun-bhaja/</id>
    <published>2016-12-29T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:13:56.481Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">The goodness of perfectly seasoned, pan-fried brinjals</p>

<p class="post-intro">This is a recipe of brinjal fried to an amber-coloured crust on the outside, while remaining soft and mushy inside.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">T</span>he taste of <em>begun bhaja</em> is difficult to explain to anyone who hasn’t eaten fried brinjals. Suffice it to say that it is probably unlike anything you’ve ever tasted, especially if seasoned with the right amount of salt and sugar. And we won’t even go into how drop-dead gorgeous the finished product is. The recipe is ridiculously simple. You smear thickly sliced brinjals in turmeric and seasoning, and fry them on medium heat in a skillet. The sugar in the marinade allows the brinjals to develop a wonderfully amber-coloured crust, and deepens the flavour of the dish. If you have 20 minutes to spare, give this recipe a try. Eat it along with steaming rice and dal, and you will not regret it.</p>
<p>This recipe uses one large brinjal. When shopping for the vegetable, be sure to select a specimen of the male variety as it is likely to contain far fewer seeds than its female counterpart. You can identify the type of the brinjal by looking at the indentation on its bottom. If the indentation is elongated and deep, it’s a female brinjal. And if it is round and shallow, that’s the seedless, male brinjal.</p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 20 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 6 slices of <em>begun bhaja</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1 piece</td>
<td>Large brinjal</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Turmeric powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>a pinch</td>
<td>Red chilli powder</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¾ tsp</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>1½ tsp</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¾ tsp</td>
<td>Flour (atta)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>~80 g</td>
<td>Mustard oil (for frying)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Mixing bowl</li>
<li>Frying pan | skillet</li>
<li>Long spatula | <em>khunti</em> | fork</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Wash the brinjal and chop off its stalk. Cut the vegetable along the cross-section into discs, 2 cm thick. A large brinjal should yield about 6 slices.</li>
<li>In a mixing bowl, combine the turmeric powder, red chilli powder, salt, sugar, and <em>atta</em>.</li>
<li>Add the brinjal slices to the bowl and coat them with the spices.</li>
<li>Cover and let them rest for at least 15 minutes. During this time, the salt and sugar will draw out the water from the brinjal slices and soften them up. The moisture generated will also help all the flavours mingle nicely. So, don’t skip this step.</li>
<li>Now, heat mustard oil in a skillet till it starts smoking lightly. For even frying, the depth of the mustard oil in the pan should be at least 1 cm.</li>
<li>Lower the marinated brinjal slices into the oil one by one and fry them on each side, for about 3 minutes, till they are golden. Make sure that the pan is set on medium-low heat; we want to cook the brinjal slices from the inside while allowing them to develop a nice crust on the outside. Also, keep a close eye on the pan, as the sugar in the marinade may burn.</li>
<li>When golden, lift the <em>begun bhaja</em> from the oil. Hold them against the side of the pan for about 20 seconds to drain out excess oil, or use paper towels to soak it up. Serve hot.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | <em>luchi</em></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Begun Or baingan bhaja is a Bengali vegetarian recipe of shallow-fried eggplant disks. Crunchy outside, soft inside. Cooks in 15 minutes!
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="bhaja" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/bhaja/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Jhinge Alu Posto</title>
    <link href="https://bongeats.com/recipe/jhinge-alu-posto/"/>
    <id>https://bongeats.com/recipe/jhinge-alu-posto/</id>
    <published>2016-12-22T17:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2017-03-03T06:15:54.346Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-byline">Potatoes and ridged gourd cooked in a poppy paste</p>

<p class="post-intro">Subtle to taste and mellowing in its effect, this classic preparation is the ultimate comfort food of the siesta-loving Bangali.</p>

<a id="more"></a>
<p><span class="dropcap">J</span><em>hinge-alu posto</em> is a classic Bengali dish. Sparing in its use of spices, this preparation relies on the flavours inherent in the vegetables (potatoes and ridged gourd) for its taste. What stands out, however, is the nutty flavour of the roasted poppy paste, which also provides body and texture to the gravy. Overall, the taste of this dish is so understated that it is difficult to imagine how its key ingredient, the poppy seed, was actually a residual by-product of the violent history, fraught with all manner of power imbalances and exploitation, of opium trade.</p><p></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>COOKING TIME</strong> 40 minutes<br><strong>YIELDS</strong> 4 servings</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="Ingredients"><a href="#Ingredients" class="headerlink" title="Ingredients"></a>Ingredients</h2><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Quantity</th>
<th>Ingredient</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>15 g</td>
<td>Poppy seeds (soaked in water for at least 4 hours)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>4 pieces (2 for the paste + 2 for phoron)</td>
<td>Green chillies</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>40 g</td>
<td>Onions (cubed)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>25 g</td>
<td>Vegetable oil</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>¼ tsp</td>
<td>Kaalo jeere (nigella seeds)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>300 g</td>
<td>Potatoes (2 cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>250 g</td>
<td>Jhinge or ridged gourd (2 cm cubes)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10 g</td>
<td>Salt</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>8 g</td>
<td>Sugar</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>125 g</td>
<td>Warm water</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h2 id="Equipment"><a href="#Equipment" class="headerlink" title="Equipment"></a>Equipment</h2><ul>
<li>Frying pan | <em>kadai</em></li>
<li>Long spatula | <em>khunti</em></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Appliances"><a href="#Appliances" class="headerlink" title="Appliances"></a>Appliances</h2><ul>
<li>Stove</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Method"><a href="#Method" class="headerlink" title="Method"></a>Method</h2><ol>
<li>Soak the poppy seeds in hot water for at least 4 hours. You can also soak them overnight in water at room temperature.</li>
<li>Drain the water and place the poppy seeds in a small grinder jar, along with 2 green chillies and cubed onions.</li>
<li>Grind these to a smooth paste, using about 50 g of water. The finer the grind, the better the flavour. So take your time with this step. Once done, set the poppy paste aside.</li>
<li>Heat 25 g vegetable oil in a pan. We don’t use mustard oil in this recipe to preserve the white colour of the dish.</li>
<li>Temper the oil with <em>kaalo jeere</em> and 2 slit green chillies.</li>
<li>Once the spices start crackling, add the cubed potatoes and fry them on medium heat for 4 minutes. The potatoes should not brown, but remain white. Stir them frequently.</li>
<li>Next, add in the <em>jhinge</em>. Fry them for another 4–5 minutes.</li>
<li>Now, add the poppy paste to the pan, along with the salt.</li>
<li>Sauté the vegetables in the poppy paste for around 5–7 minutes. Keep the heat on low and stir often to prevent the paste from sticking to the pan.</li>
<li>Once the poppy paste starts releasing a nutty aroma, add 125 g of hot water along with the sugar.</li>
<li>Let simmer on low heat for another 8–10 minutes, till the potatoes are tender and the gravy has thickened.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="Served-with"><a href="#Served-with" class="headerlink" title="Served with"></a>Served with</h2><ul>
<li><a href="/tags/dal/">Dal</a></li>
<li><a href="/how-to/cook-the-perfect-rice/">Rice</a> | roti</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Bengal&#39;s favourite traditional vegetarian dish of potatoes braised in poppy seed paste. Perfect for your afternoon siesta.
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="recipe" scheme="https://bongeats.com/categories/recipe/"/>
    
    
      <category term="vegetarian" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegetarian/"/>
    
      <category term="vegan" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/vegan/"/>
    
      <category term="gluten-free" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/gluten-free/"/>
    
      <category term="torkari" scheme="https://bongeats.com/tags/torkari/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
